<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/793">Ḥabib</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): 
                     <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license">
                        used under a Creative Commons Attribution license 
                        <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/792"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/794"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks. Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
        <!-- See spear/793.xml -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-1" n="1">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-1">
                    <head type="main">The First History, of the Great and Divine Old Man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">Habib</persName>.</head>
                    <ab type="section" xml:id="section-1.1" n="1">
                 The relation of the history of this apostolic man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">Habib</persName> it is not easy
                 for any man to approach without fear to narrate it, inasmuch as on both
                 sides a cause of alarm springs from the relating of it; first, the fact that the
                 man who sets himself to enumerate the marvellous and great miracles and
                 acts of power, and fearful and apostolic signs, which he who performs the will
                 of those who fear him wrought through him will fall short of the sum; since
                 a tongue of flesh is indeed too small, and human mouths are not sufficient,
                 to speak of him as he is; and here there is danger lest a man wish to depict
                 this great and divine sea in an ill-ordered and faulty manner, and,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> diminishing 
                 his heavenly features because he is not suflicient for them, finally
                 incur the condemnation of a corrupter (of) spiritual beauties; secondly, even
                 if the great and marvellous deeds that can be easily wrought through
                 apostles only which God wrought through him be narrated, lest they be as
                 it were hard to believe; but, committing the greatness of these to the
                 knowledge of him who is true and does not lie, who said, <quote>Whoever belie<pb n="6"/>
                            <pb n="6"/>veth 
                    on me shall do greater than these signs which I do</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> we leave this
                 [also] to him and to those to whom it has not been hard to believe his word,
                 bringing these few things (a small proportion) to record for the glory of God.
                 This holy old man therefore came from the district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/493">Sophanene</placeName>, and was
                 trained by a man who was himself also great and holy and a worker of
                 miracles, whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3710">Bar Nbyl</persName>. This divine man therefore was
                 before our times; and, inasmuch as his end preceded our days, though this
                 great old man his disciple and many others used to tell us about the great
                 marvels which he used to perform, inasmuch as we declared before that we
                 shall omit men in whose case the sight of our eyes has not borne witness
                 to our handwriting,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> for this reason we have not touched the history of that
                 saint; who himself also again was trained by a divine blessed man whose
                 name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3203">Mar Dada</persName>; which things we have omitted to relate, in order to
                 tell only the things that concern this man who was our contemporary. This
                 man therefore came from a village called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2779">Fyțr</placeName>, from which his master
                 also came; and he first planted <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2778">that monastery</placeName>, and then this blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">Habib</persName>
                        <pb n="7"/>
                        <pb n="7"/>went to him, when he was about ten years old, and he received him, and
                 he continued to dwell with him, and he exercised him in spiritual ways of
                 life, marking his tender age, and what devoutness and what orderliness he
                 possessed from his youth. But, when that old man had completed ninety
                 years, he departed to his mansion in heaven, and left his monastery in the
                 hands of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">Habib</persName>, after he had lived with him twenty years; and
                 so, having seen his ways of life and his obedience and his humility, he made
                 him heir of the inheritance of his blessings, and left him to succed him. For
                 the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">Habib</persName> was so humble and obedient even in his old age that I do
                 not think it was strange to him [...<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/>]
                 And from that time the fear of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">the blessed man</persName> fell upon all men, so that
                 many from fear, before he himself spoke to them, of their own free will
                 made a remission; and then afterwards <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">the blessed man</persName> used to perform
                 frequent mighty works in every place against those who contended against
                 him, and when he spoke God would perform in action everything that he
                 <pb n="8"/>
                        <pb n="8"/>said without delay, because he saw his zeal and readiness and the keenness
                 of his purpose. But, when the owner of the ass heard it, his knees knocked
                 together in fear, lest the power of the saint's curse should light upon him
                 also; and he arose and took all his parchments (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χάρτης</foreign>), and brought them
                 to him, and entreated him to forgive him. Again there was another rich
                 man in another village, who had an ancient debt, many years old; and he
                 also used to plunder many people; and they came and told <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">the blessed man</persName>
                 about him, and he set out to go to him. And, when he heard <quote>Lo! <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">Habib</persName>
                    is coming</quote>, inasmuch as he was not prepared to do good, he arose and took
                 the parchments (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χάρτης</foreign>), i. e. the deeds, and left him and fled. And when
                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">the blessed man</persName> heard it he was distressed and said : <quote>Because his will was
                    thus prepared to do evil toward these poor men, if God wills their deliverance,
                    let them never see him again</quote>. And the same night that man died, and
                 fear fell on all who heard it. And <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">the blessed man</persName> went on continuing
                 to busy himself greatly in matters of debt-remission, becoming a deliverance 
                 for the poor and his<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> fame increasing. But the wife of the man
                 <pb n="9"/>
                        <pb n="9"/>who had died and his children took all their parchments <foreign xml:lang="grc">χάρτης</foreign>, and
                 brought them to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">the blessed man</persName>, and thus returned them to their owners.
              </ab>
                    <ab type="section" xml:id="section-1.2" n="2">
                 Again there was another man, and he kept ancient deeds some years old
                 against poor men, and they came and told the saint, and they brought him,
                 and he went; and that because from his boyhood and down to his old age
                 he retained his humility and obedience which itself also distinguished him,
                 so that a widow or a poor woman or poor man who begged him to go with
                 him on any business whatever, he<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> did not as being a man of high reputation
                 refuse to go, but, in order to satisfy him, would go with him at once
                 without delay. When therefore he had gone to that man, inasmuch as
                 Satan had filled that man's heart, he was roused to fury against him, saying,
                 <quote>Will not this fellow go and sit in his monastery and be quiet? for see!
                    he comes out and wanders about to eat and drink</quote>. And when the blessed
                 man heard these things he was distressed, and he returned to his monastery,
                 having prayed and said : <quote>Lord who knowest what is in the hearts of all,
                    if thou knowest that I came out in this business in order to eat and drink,
                    forgive this man. And again, if thy grace knoweth that it is for the sake
                    of thy name and for the sake of the deliverance of the wronged that I have
                    come out, in order that this same thing may be made known to this man and
                    <pb n="10"/>
                            <pb n="10"/>to everyone else, do with him as thy grace knoweth how</quote>. Then Grace
                 exacted forthwith from the man requital for the old man; and that same day
                 the Lord smote him, and half of him became withered, one of his eyes and
                 one of his arms, and the whole of his side, and one of his feet, and he
                 fell into grievous aflliction. And, when he understood that it was a sentence 
                 emanating from justice, which had overtaken him of on account of his
                 blasphemy, he sent intercessors to the saint to ask him to pray for him; and
                 he on his side did not withhold his kindness from him, but immediately sent
                 his disciple whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName>; on whom from that time he poured part
                 of the gift of the power of his prayer like the blessed <persName>Elijah</persName> upon his
                 disciple <persName>Elisha</persName>, so that after him he became even more distinguished than
                 himself. This man therefore he sent, saying: <quote>Go, my son; we for our
                    part will not close the door, and pray for him. But the rest of the sentence
                    has gone forth against him, that he shall depart from life; and this we cannot
                    reverse</quote>. And, when he had gone and prayed over him, immediately his
                 soul departed from his body, and he died, and without his consent a remission
                 was brought about for these injured persons whom he himself was prepared
                 to subject to afflictions. And in consequence of this fear everyone who had
                 debtors of ancient standing would remit the debt; and some of them brought
                 their deeds to the blessed man himself, and entreated him to bless them;
                 <pb n="11"/>
                        <pb n="11"/>while the fear and the terror of him went out thenceforth in every place
                 because he himself also travelled in all the districts of Syria. And, as it is
                 written in the blessed Job, <quote>Who hath contended with him and hath had
                    peace?</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> so was it fulfilled in this spiritual old man, so that no one resisted
                 him in this matter, and transgressed his orders, and raised his head again.
              </ab>
                    <ab type="section" xml:id="section-1.3" n="3">
                 There was again another <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3196">rich man</persName> in the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/134">Maiferkat</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> who was a
                 banker (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τραπεζίτης</foreign>) and had many bonds (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γραμματεῖον</foreign>) several years old, and
                 used to exact cruelly and mercilessly. And certain persons came and
                 informed the old man; and he rose forthwith and directed his steps to the
                 city [...<quote>...<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/>]
                    five years I have not seen the light, and, when I came near you with everyone,
                    my eyes were opened</quote>; though indeed even the old man was astonished at
                 this, and as if by way of precaution against being deceived said to her,
                 <quote>Your own faith has given you light; and, if not, I for my part am a sinner</quote>. 
                 And so this miracle was proclaimed all over the city, while everyone
                 <pb n="12"/>
                        <pb n="12"/>gave thanks to God. While he was exerting his activity in the same city,
                 certain persons from the country of the <persName>Persians</persName> heard of it because he was
                 near there, and they brought him two women, one who was persecuted by a
                 demon, and another who was barren of offspring, having been many years
                 with her husband and not having had children; and they continued entreating him 
                 to pray for them. But he on his side came up and made the sign
                 over the possessed woman, and prayed, and laid an inhibition upon that
                 demon, and he immediately came out of her, and she was healed. But in the
                 case of the one who was barren he prayed and made the sign over her and
                 said, <quote>Go and keep guard over yourself, that you sin not; and at this time
                    next year lo! you shall have a son</quote>. And that woman believed, and went
                 away; and she received conception and bare a son; and, after a year had
                 passed, she took him in her arms, and came to the blessed man in his
                 monastery; and he baptized and blessed him; and she returned rejoicing and
                 praising God.
              </ab>
                    <ab type="section" xml:id="section-1.4" n="4">
                 Again there was a certain man, and he had a large vineyard, and had
                 spent much money upon it; and for three years running hail came down
                 and made terrible havoc of that vineyard; and, when that time came in
                 the fourth year, he set forth and went weeping to the old man, and continued
                 <pb n="13"/>
                        <pb n="13"/>entreating him to pray for him. But the old man said to him : <quote>Wherefore,
                    my son, is havoc made of that vineyard?</quote>. And he said : <quote>Sir, I know not</quote>,
                 The old man says to him : <quote>Has that plantation done any sin or crime, or
                    offended God?</quote> He says to him, <quote>No</quote>. He says to him: <quote>Know and see
                       that it is consequently on account of your own sins that things which
                       have not sinned are being chastised, that you may repent. But go make an
                       oblation, and let us go there; and do you keep guard over yourself</quote>. That
                 man went as he ordered him, and made a particle of bread. And the old
                 man set out and went, and offered the oblation there. And, when they had
                 partaken and sat down to receive the blessing after their oblation, suddenly
                 that cloud ascended in terrifying fashion, and came to the place; and this
                 perhaps so that God might make it known that he had accepted the old
                 man's oblation and his prayer, and had done his will. And, when the
                 hailstones began to fall, the old man rose from the table and stretched out
                 his hands to heaven, and said, <quote>Our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, whose signal and
                    word of command governs everything that is in heaven and that is on earth,
                    because, my Lord, this vineyard has been deemed worthy to have thy living
                    and life-giving body and blood offered in it, accept the person of the sinner
                    thy bondman, my Lord, and cause this cloud to pass away from him</quote>. And
                 <pb n="14"/>
                        <pb n="14"/>the Lord heard the old man's voice; and that cloud passed away, and did not
                 harm even one leaf in it; and lo! from that time, through the power of the
                 blessed man's prayers, that vineyard remained without hail falling in it,
                 while havoc was made of every thing round it, and it alone escaped.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/>
                 Again they brought a certain woman to him who had a demon in her,
                 and he laid an inhibition upon him, and he came out of her. And after
                 some years the old man fell sick, and was constrained to die; and his
                 disciples came near and besought him to remove his inhibitions; and the
                 blessed man removed all his inhibitions that he had made. And immediately
                 that fiend returned, and appeared in that woman. And, when they said to
                 him, <quote>How have you presumed, when you were laid under an inhibition by
                    the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">Habib</persName>?</quote>, he said to them, <quote>Last evening he removed every 
                       inhibition laid by him, while I was standing there, and I came</quote>. And when they
                 came and told the blessed man he sent him a message, <quote>As for you, you
                    are not at liberty to dwell in a human being for ever and ever</quote>. And so
                 he was again expelled by the power of God's word. There was again another
                 woman in a certain village who had a mad demon in her, a woman who
                 barked at people like a noxious beast, and tore their clothes, and violently
                 assaulted many, and, when they brought her to the old man, she continued
                 <pb n="15"/>
                        <pb n="15"/>howling at him and seeking to run away. And the old man stretched out
                 his hand, and made the sign over her; and he laid an inhibition upon him
                 and said, <quote>In the name of the Lord you are barred from his creation</quote>
                 And the same hour he went out of her, and she was healed; and that woman
                 became quiet, while everyone wondered and gave thanks to God.
              </ab>
                    <ab type="section" xml:id="section-1.5" n="5">
                 There was again another poor widow woman, and she had been taught
                 the art of drawing, and used to practise it and labour at it for her necessities,
                 and she used to teach pupils. And two of her pupils, after a long time
                 during which she had spent labour upon them, went away when they had
                 learned and defrauded her, and did not give her her fee. And, because
                 everyone who was defrauded whether of little or of much had recourse to the
                 holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">Habib</persName> as to a deliverer of those who were wronged, this woman came
                 to him, and informed him of her affair. And he wrote a letter to these
                 pupils of hers the same hour, telling them not to make use of her art till they
                 paid her the fee for her labour. But they acted presumptuously and treated
                 the old man with contempt, and did not comply with his order, and they
                 began to practise the art. And the same day the sentence for their presumption 
                 overtook them; for the tongue of one was seized with an impediment
                 so that she could not speak at all, and the arm of the other withered and
                 <pb n="16"/>
                        <pb n="16"/>became like wood, and would not turn. And immediately [certain persons]
                 ran carrying [that] poor woman's fee to her, weeping, and entreating [her] to
                 go with them and [entreat] the old man; and she went with them, and they
                 continued entreating him to forgive them. But [he] in order not to requite
                 the evil-doer according to [his] evil-doing set forth incense and prayed and
                 [made the sign over] them, and the bonds were loosened, while he cautioned
                 them not to act presumptuously against the word of God.
              </ab>
                    <ab type="section" xml:id="section-1.6" n="6">
                 Again there was a certain <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3196">rich man</persName> in the city against whom many poor
                 men used to complain that he had retained parchments (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χάρτης</foreign>) against them
                 for many years, and, when they had been paid, he used to demand them again.
                 And, when the blessed man heard it, he set out and went to him to entreat
                 him. And, when that man heard of it, he ordered them to stop him at his
                 door, and the door to be shut in his face so that he should not come in;
                 and the old man continued standing at the door and sending him an
                 entreaty [the whole day]. And he [...] was distressed and he wept [...]<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/>
                        <pb n="17"/>
                        <pb n="17"/>distressed [...] in confidence in the divine
                 power that was in him, he said to them, <quote>Go; and, when you have seen
                    these beasts, say to them [in] a loud [voice], <quote>
                                <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">Habib</persName> the sinner [says that] you
                       are not permitted [...] to taste of [... in this] village</quote>
                        </quote>.
                 [... ]and to the company [...] they said [...] day [...] we comprise in the few
                 acts that have been recorded in order to glorify him who performed them,
                 neglecting the rest, while all of us who are at this time in the body testify to
                 the truth of the things that have been written, and have seen and know clearly
                 each one of them, together with the blessed men the disciples of the saint as
                 well, among whom the first and the most eminent are <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName> [and Hanan]ya;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/>
                 which blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName>, of whom we will also compose a [special] record,
                 [began] vigorously to walk wholly in the footsteps of the saint. But, after
                 the [old] <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">Habib</persName> had marvellously run in this path of heroism, and of acts
                 of power [and] miracles and signs [and] mighty deeds, and deliverance [of]
                 <pb n="18"/>
                        <pb n="18"/>those who are wronged and of orphans [and of] poor men and of widows,
                 he was carried to the mansion that is a release from the troubles [of] the
                 body, and fell asleep in peace, having confitently committed his monastery
                 and his labour and the care of the distressed to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName> his disciple, who
                 himself also trafficked zealously with the talent of his gifts all his days,
                 insomuch as to amass double profits. And so the great old man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">Habib</persName>
                 began and ended his days in the course of heroism in all his relations,
                 and ended his course and received his crown;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> by whose prayers may we
                 merit?<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> [...]
              </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-1">
                    <ab type="section" xml:id="trailer-1.1" n="7">
                 The history of the great and divine old man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">Habib</persName> is ended.
              </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 5, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 6, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>John, XIV, 12.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 6, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>P.3.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 7, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>A leaf or two is missing</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 8, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 9, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 11, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Job, IX, 4.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 11, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Martyropolis.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 11, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>A leaf or two is missing.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 14, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Cf. ch. 7, where a similar story is told.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 16, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Some lines missing.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 17, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See end of ch. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 18, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>II Tim., IV, 7, 8.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 18, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>A leaf or two missing.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
