<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/795">John the Nazarite</title>
                <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): 
                     <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license">
                        used under a Creative Commons Attribution license 
                        <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/794"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/796"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks. Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/795.xml -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-3" n="3">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-3">
                    <head type="main">Next the Third History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1320">John</persName> the Perfect Nazrite.</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-3.1" n="1">
                  When we set ourselves to approach and record the history of this holy
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1320">John</persName>, we exposed ourselves to a multitude of conflicting thoughts, in
                  consequence of the fact that, if we take upon ourselves to narrate severally
                  the signs that were wrought through each of these same saints, we shall
                  wander and extend into a great number of unending writings; and for this
                  reason we considered that the triumphs only that belong to the labours
                  of each of them are enough to excite the praise of God that is in those
                  who hear them, and how they bore themselves manfully in the course of
                  justice all the days of their life without shrinking, while by reason of this
                  fact and the fact further that even one only of the triumphs of each of the
                  saints that has been related is sufficient to indicate the divine power hidden
                  in him who wrought it, just as it is in the power of expert tasters to know
                  <pb type="vol" n="37"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="37"/>the whole taste of a tree from one fruit only, on this account we abstain from
                  recording many signs in order, only presenting the triumphs gained by their
                  labours and the manner of the signs to the memory of expert hearers. This
                  perfect blessed man therefore, who is in truth one worthy to be third in this
                  series of saints, received his training from his boyhood in the great and
                  renowned monastery called that of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/358">Zuknin</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> while from the very beginning
                  of his training he would consider in himself and say, <quote>What profit have I
                     from the fact that I feed this body the end of which was doomed to be
                     loathsome and disgusting decay? and wherefore do I by a quantity of food
                     amass and lay up store in it for a multitude of creeping things and of
                     worms?</quote>; since he heard further what the blessed apostle writes saying,
                  <quote>Food belongeth to the belly and the belly to food; but God shall make an
                     end of both</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> and further that also which is written reproachfully to those
                  who concern themselves with the sustenance of their bodies, <quote>Ye took your
                     pleasure upon the earth and were wanton, and ye fed your bodies as for a
                     day of slaughter</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/>
                    </ab>
                    <pb type="vol" n="38"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="38"/>
                    <ab xml:id="section-3.2" n="2">
                  When then the blessed man through hearing these things turned his
                  thoughts upon himself, he in zeal decided for himself that he would be a man
                  aloof from and a stranger to all pleasure that comes through the bodily tastes
                  which spring up in food, saying, <quote>I for my part did not depart from the
                     things of the world in order to turn back to them; but it is enough that
                     I have set myself to be a stranger to these transitory things, in order to
                     run after the things that pass not away; and through holding aloof from
                     corruptible things I remembered and desired the heavenly blessings which
                     the blessed <persName>Paul</persName> indicated and said, <quote>Eye hath not seen, nor ear heard,
                        nor hath it risen into the heart of man, what God prepared for them that
                        love him</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> These I must run after and pursue with all my strength,
                     casting all corruptible things behind me, except the ordinary nourishment
                     of my body in order to sustain it</quote>. And thenceforth the blessed man in
                  fervent zeal decided for himself that he would eat no food at all of any
                  kind except ordinary bread, and water and salt or ordinary lentils, while
                  in place of herbs he used to mix with these the leaves of a certain large
                  <pb type="vol" n="39"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="39"/>tree that was inside the court of that monastery called <foreign>shigra</foreign>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> eating from
                  it all the summer, and in the winter again drying the produce of it and
                  eating what was left, while all the members of his convent would urge
                  him to desist from this distressing practice that was distressing his body,
                  and in this only he did not obey; but the obedience and silence and
                  humility in all his other relations of life went even beyond the limits, qualities
                  that befit the humble and obedient; so that, if anyone stretched out his
                  finger and stuck it in his eye, he would not raise his face (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>) and
                  look at him, or open his mouth and speak with him, and, if he said to
                  him, <quote>Take an ax and come turn this rock over</quote>, or <quote>Come dig out this
                     boulder that is not dug out</quote>, he would again not delay for the purpose
                  of at least inquiring<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/>
                        <quote>How am I to<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> turn the mountain<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> over</quote> or 
                  <quote>dig out the rock?</quote>, but silently take the iron and begin; so that they often
                  <pb type="vol" n="40"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="40"/>made a kind of trial of him, and he would at once without delay begin
                  what was ordered him, until that man whoever he were said to him <quote>Stop</quote>,
                  and then he would cease.
               </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-3.3" n="3">
                  Again a place had been made by him in the monastery-enclosure, and he
                  would spend the rest of the day or of the night there, in vigil without
                  measure and prayers without ceasing, so that in consequence of these things
                  there was generated for him first sorrow of heart, and floods of tears of
                  great weeping by night and by day, insomuch that his eyelids shed their
                  lashes from weeping, and the hair of his head fell off in front, from the
                  number of times that he used to knock it<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> before God in supplication, while
                  all who saw him were amazed and wondered at him, and on this account they
                  used to call him, <quote>
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1320">John</persName> the perfect Nazirite</quote>, while he was thereby openly
                  preparing for the contest with the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3680">demons</persName> even to blood, insomuch that 
                  sometimes his mind received blows in the contest and was silenced, so that, if there
                  was anyone who was present and saw him, he thought that he had a <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3680">demon</persName>,
                  in that he had become silent and had secretly in his spirit entered upon a
                  secret contest with powers (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρχας</foreign>.) and authorities, and during the intervals
                  <pb type="vol" n="41"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="41"/>of the contest he was so hard smitten that others would approach him and
                  speak with him and think that he was dead. And so for ten years this saint
                  contended; and at last, when God saw his confidence in him and his
                  steadfastness, he gave him strength and victory over his enemies, and from
                  that time his mind was enlightened and his spiritual sight cleared, and he
                  attained to high and marvellous conceptions (<foreign xml:lang="grc">θεωρίας</foreign>) at which men marvelled,
                  though he had not laboured at reading the Scriptures, but instead of
                  everything he would utter a series of constant prayers; and through this
                  there was given to him great perspicacity in the Scriptures and the commentaries, 
                  so that men were unable even to comprehend and take in the height
                  of his words and the depth of his intellect, even <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3678">the scholastics and the other
                     men who were learned in the Holy Scriptures</persName> running to him to hear his
                  words, while they were amazed and praised and glorified God. And
                  afterwards he attained to authority over unclean spirits, and over great works
                  of healing; but, if we record these severally, as we have also stated above,
                  many sheets of parchment (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χάρτης</foreign>) will not suflice us. When the blessed
                  <pb type="vol" n="42"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="42"/>
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1320">John</persName> had completed twenty-five years in this life of perfection, heretical
                  machinations assailed his convent,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> and all the leading men in it submitted
                  under compulsion and great constraint (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άνάγκη</foreign>); and accordingly the blessed
                  man prepared to withdraw from among them, saying, <quote>For my part I have not
                     forgotten the words of our Saviour who says, Whoso shall deny me before
                     men, I also will deny him before my Father who is in heaven'<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/>
                        </quote>. Then he
                  left them, and departed, while about <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3679">thirty men among the chiefs of the brotherhood 
                     and the leading men of the convent</persName> also went out after the blessed
                  man, saving to him, <quote>Death with you, our father, is more desired by us than
                     life with others</quote>. And so they set forth and went to another district, hoping
                  in God, not even bread for the day being found upon them, while the blessed
                  man encouraged them and said, <quote>Would, my brethren, that we could attain
                     to the blessing of those who have been persecuted for righteousness' sake<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/>
                        </quote>.
                  And so they found a certain monastery and took up their abode in it, while
                  the fame of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1320">John</persName> was heard also over the whole district, and
                  <pb type="vol" n="43"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="43"/>accordingly all who were sick with various diseases and who had evil spirits
                  ran to him, and the divine power that was in him would confidently heal
                  them all, while everyone was amazed and thanked God; so that we also went
                  to him in the district of the saint's martyrdom, i. e. in his exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>), and,
                  when we had sat down to take food, five <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3680">demoniacs</persName> together with their hands
                  tied behind them and howling beat down the door and came and entered
                  foaming; but the blessed man rebuked them, and ordered them to go to the
                  martyrs' chapel and lie down; and so they went; and, after we had had
                  supper and everyone had gone away to rest, he himself went out and went
                  and made a prayer, and expelled them<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> all; and they were found in the morning 
                  at peace and in their right minds. And we saw it, and were seized with
                  amazement at the power of the saint's prayer. We were further specially
                  amazed at him, because after severe labour he was even so not remiss; for
                  there was an enclosure in that monastery, and one fig-tree inside it, and he
                  Went and brought sand and laid it on the south side of that tree, and he filled
                  <pb type="vol" n="44"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="44"/>a large jar with cold water and hung it on it; and he continued kneeling
                  over against it on that sand all through the extreme noonday heat, while
                  we were parched even by the shade in consequence of the heat. Again,
                  when they had passed a short time, they were again driven from that place
                  also, and that which had been sent to them by the grace of God was
                  taken by the heretics, while this also gave much pleasure to the blessed
                  man, who said, <quote>They have relieved us of a bodily burden that we may run
                     after spiritual things</quote>. But, after twelve years had been completed by the
                  holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1320">John</persName> in the conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of the martyrdom of persecution, he ended his
                  course in the same exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>), and went to the mansions of rest.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> Before
                  the time of the saint's end, when we were with him, when I had heard the
                  words of grace that used to come out of his mouth, we entreated him to
                  tell us what line of virtue seemed to him to be greater and more excellent than
                  the other lines in God's sight. The blessed man said : I. <quote>Among all the
                     courses of justice nothing is greater in God's sight than submission that is
                     perfect in performing its obligations, in which are comprised all the types of
                     <pb type="vol" n="45"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="45"/>virtue that bring near to God</quote>. II. Again a second question was presented
                  to the same blessed man by us. <quote>If, as you have said, our father, submission 
                     is thus greater than everything, how is it that we see triumphs won
                     by solitaries and hermits who had not submission, and by the other blessed
                     men moreover who also wrought miracles and great acts of power, and lo!
                     these did not live in submission, and their virtue was manifest to everyone?</quote>
                  The saint's explanation. <quote>Consider, our brother, the divine words, and
                     they will themselves show an example of the power that is hidden in
                     them. We hear the holy apostle saying, <quote>Every man's work shall be made
                        manifest; for that day shall make it manifest</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> And we have learned again
                     from him in that he says, <quote>There is great fear of falling into God's hands</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/>
                     And again we hear the prophet proclaiming of God's judgments, <quote>They are
                        like a great deep that is not fathomed at all</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> Whence is it now<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/> tell me
                     that on the dreadful day of judgment to many among those who as you said
                     were distinguished by acts of power and by signs and by miracles the words
                     of our Lord will be spoken in answer, which in his parables he said to those
                     <pb type="vol" n="46"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="46"/>who said to him, <quote>My Lord, have we not in thy name prophesied, and in thy
                        name done acts of power?</quote>, and he on his side will say to them, <quote>Verily I say
                           unto you I know you not</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/> And again in the case of those who finished
                     their courses in submission for God's sake, setting their will aside and doing
                     that of their masters and of their brethren, and despising men and shunning
                     even the appearance of virtue, whence is it tell me if that blessing is theirs
                     which was given by the Lord of blessings to the lowly, and to the poor in
                     spirit,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/> as he also states in the prophet, <quote>Better is one who doeth the will
                        than a thousand</quote>?<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a21" target="#n21" n="21"/> Whence can we understand the secrets of God's dreadful
                     final judgment, and his provision made in righteousness? And my opinion
                     is this, that those who have spent the days of their life in due submission,
                     according to the gospel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">εύαγγέλιον</foreign>) saying, come not to judgment, but have
                     passed from death to life.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a22" target="#n22" n="22"/>
                        </quote>
                    </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-3.4" n="4">
                  Again the third question. <quote>And what is the submission which is so great
                     in your eyes, O our father?, and how should the man conduct himself who
                     <pb type="vol" n="47"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="47"/>has set himself to practise submission, and how should he attain to this virtue
                     which have mentioned, which you have magnified beyond all classes of
                     virtue, and what models are suited for the man who is submissive to
                     observe?</quote> The answer of the same blessed man. <quote>There are many models;
                        and there is a submission which while appearing submission begets loss for
                        many by being accompanied by pride and by contumacy, and by the personal
                        wishes of the man who seems submissive and by all the other things; and
                        this leads to hell and not to life. But the submission which properly belongs
                        to religion is this (which should also vary according to difference of inclination), 
                        that he who is ready to snatch spiritual fruits should be ready
                        to listen to every order that is given him simply, and to carry it out
                        diligently, not judging the man who gave him the order, and thinking
                        <quote>This man has ordered me wrongly</quote>, unless he orders some act of sin
                        that is at variance with religion, carrying in himself the model of the
                        patriarch <persName>Abraham</persName>, who made no question or objection against him who
                        ordered him <quote>Take thy son thine only son him whom thou lovest, Isaac, and
                           <pb type="vol" n="48"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="48"/>go offer him up to me as a whole burnt-offering upon one of the mountains</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a23" target="#n23" n="23"/>
                        And, when this man received the order concerning his only son, he did not
                        judge the saying that preceded it which he said to him <quote>In Isaac shall thy
                           seed be called</quote>, and <quote>His seed shall be as the sand of the seas and as the
                              stars in heaven</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a24" target="#n24" n="24"/> and, when he said to him to whom this son was promised
                        for these purposes <quote>Go kill him</quote>, he accepted it simply, and only determined
                        to show perfect obedience, and to carry to slaughter him in whom he promised him 
                        that his seed should be called; and, what is greater than all,
                        with his own hands to sacrifice his only son, without thinking and saying,
                        <quote>Yesterday he said to me, <quote>In this son shall thy seed be called</quote>, and
                           now he said, <quote>Go sacrifice him</quote>, and how will seed be called in him after
                           he has been sacrificed?</quote> And yet more facts than these were to be found
                        in the affair of the blessed <persName>Abraham</persName>, if he had sought to raise objection
                        against him who ordered him to carry out these two orders which thus
                        seemed outwardly to be opposite to and inconsistent with one another; but he
                        even undoubtingly believed and trusted him who promised, and to him who
                        <pb type="vol" n="49"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="49"/>instigated him to kill the son of promise he assented, and he made ready to
                        do it without inquiry; so that in virtue of this will that was submissive to
                        faith and of obedience he attained the position of chief in the kingdom
                        of heaven. So therefore he who is made submissive for God's sake
                        should himself be ready to perform what has been ordered him without
                        judging the man who gave the orders; and the man who gave the
                        orders, whether he gave them wrongly or rightly, shall himself give account 
                        for the orders given by him; for the man himself also from whom
                        he receives them has one who will reprimand him if he give a wrong
                        order. Besides these things it is the duty of the man who professes
                        religion by means of submission to have in him discretion in all matters that
                        conduce to spiritual benefits, that whoever he is he may carry them out
                        discreetly; i. e. to wait upon the saints, to wash the feet of strangers,
                        to relieve them in all that they need, to clean their clothes, to mend
                        all that are torn, to visit the sick, to concern himself about the relief
                        of his brethren in all ways, to keep watch and vigil and pray and sigh
                        before God at all seasons, and <quote>keep his tongue from evil, and his lips
                           <pb type="vol" n="50"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="50"/>that they speak no guile, and eschew evil and do good, and seek peace and
                           run after it</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a25" target="#n25" n="25"/> and this is complete submission, and <quote>blessed is that bondman</quote>,
                        (i. e. disciple) <quote>whom his Lord shall come and find so doing</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a26" target="#n26" n="26"/> He who
                        serves God by these lines of conduct has nothing equal to his virtue in all the
                        classes of justice; and his standard surpasses ascetics and hermits and
                        solitaries, and all who travel on the narrow road that leads to life,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a27" target="#n27" n="27"/> even if
                        it is hidden from him and unknown, or<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a28" target="#n28" n="28"/> manifest to him; and to him I for my
                        part assign great blessing, since in all the courses of perfection nothing seemed
                        to me to equal his standard</quote>. Having been amazed at the opinion of this
                  saint, how great in his eyes was the quality of submission, I entreated him to
                  discuss also before me the subject of the abominable passion of fornication,
                  for the sake of my profit and that of the other hearers.
               </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-3.5" n="5">
                  He when he heard these things sighed and wept; and he began to speak
                  thus: <!-- The translation has an opening double bracket here that I don't understand. --><quote>Wretched man that I am! Who will deliver me from this body of
                     death?</quote>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a29" target="#n29" n="29"/> Who is he, pray, who will understand the wiles of this fiend, the
                  <pb type="vol" n="51"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="51"/>stainer and darkener of the soul, and will cry in affliction to God to come
                  to his aid, and rescue him from his fraud and from his filthiness? In the
                  case therefore of this passion, our brother, he who wishes to escape from
                  it and keep true purity, and be purified from all pollution of the flesh and of
                  the spirit, needs tears and prayers and many sobs, and parcity of food, and
                  abstinence from dishes of varying tastes, because the desire of dishes that
                  please the taste are<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a30" target="#n30" n="30"/> a deep cavern in which is no standing-ground. But
                  think not that precaution against fornication is this only, precaution against
                  that which consists in the open contact of body with body, but that also
                  which is many times greater than this, the secret fornication of the heart
                  and of the thoughts, is that against which we ought to take special precautions 
                  and be diligently on our guard; because many are the wiles by which
                  the rebellious fiends endeavour in secret fashion rather than in that which is
                  open to cheat and submerge and defile the soul that promises purity to its
                  Lord, and strive by their deceits rather than that which is open<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a31" target="#n31" n="31"/> to stain
                  and submerge with many kinds of filthinesses, from the mention of which
                  <pb type="vol" n="52"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="52"/>I am precluded by great shame. But by reason of the workings of these
                  filthinesses I am filled with many sighs, because there are many who, while
                  taking precaution against open fornication, are in other matters secretly by
                  means of fleshly desire grievously defiling the soul as well as the body
                  through the enticements of shame, men who need great weeping and sighs
                  of aflliction; and how shall they apply a plaster to this wound that thus they
                  may escape from the dreadful judgment of torture that is decreed against
                  those who take part in these things? He who takes equal precaution in his
                  secret and in his open acts also does not yield to the blandishments of
                  foulness and of shameful action, either secretly or openly, but more than his
                  open guard takes precaution against that which is done in secret, because
                  the wound secretly inflicted that is wrought upon the spirit penetrates
                  farther than that which is administered openly. But, if he be overcome
                  and somehow lapse, secretly or openly, even so he should not despair of
                  himself, and deliver himself to the service of foulness, but turn straightway,
                  bearing the affliction of his disease, to the gracious <persName>Physician</persName>, who will
                  <pb type="vol" n="53"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="53"/>easily apply the plaster of his mercy to his infirmity. And further, even if
                  the man who has been smitten receive healing, and after it be again
                  smitten with another stroke, he should not even so neglect to run a second
                  time to the <persName>Physician</persName>'s door, even if he be smitten many times, or refrain
                  from entreating for a plaster for his stroke, a thing which we see happen
                  in visible battles also to those who are smitten, that, as long as their life is
                  preserved in them, even if they be struck many times, they do not neglect
                  to take measures for their bodily healing with all carefulness. So those also
                  who have lapsed after the lapse of a spiritual fall must act, not falling into
                  despair of life, and delivering themselves into the hand of their enemies.
                  When these things are brought about in the case of any persons, that, after
                  they have been involved in any lapses, they thrust themselves into the deep
                  cavern of sin, they are worthy objects for great weeping and many sighs,
                  in that, having fallen through a lapse, and having been a little besmirched
                  with mire, instead of running to have their stains washed away, through
                  he shameful teaching of those who caused them to lapse they resolved to
                  <pb type="vol" n="54"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="54"/>throw themselves completely into the pit of filthiness, and voluntarily
                  remain in the very submersion of their putrescence, which leads them to the
                  submersion of condemnation in which there is no absolution, and to the
                  wound for which there is no remedy, and bitter lamentation for which there
                  is no consolation, and the dreadful judgment of torment which has no end
                  for ever and ever. In the case of those who after the lapse of a fall are
                  smitten with the same pleasure of sin, and remain in the same den of corruption
                  and perdition, without having concerned themselves for the resurrection of
                  their souls and the saving of their lives from the putrescence of sin, and
                  have delivered themselves to the service of Satan, to whose will they have
                  been made captive<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a32" target="#n32" n="32"/> by their free choice, the requiter of their service with
                  him will repay them with eternal torment that passes not away, and in
                  return for their affection with him and their remaining in his company will
                  make them to inherit part of his possessions, which are outer darkness,
                  wherein is weeping and gnashing of teeth, according to the saying of the
                  Life-Giver;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a33" target="#n33" n="33"/> since they have themselves seceded from him who have joined
                  themselves to the destroyer of their lives, with whom if they remain, they
                  <pb type="vol" n="55"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="55"/>will also be tormented with him; from whom and from all whose doings
                  may we all be preserved, by the abundant mercy of the Lord of all.
               </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-3.6" n="6">
                  These, our brother, are the words which at the instigation of your request
                  have been spoken on this subject; but they will be blamed by your sound
                  and great and spiritual knowledge on account of the fact that they were
                  spoken of fall and resurrection alike, and not according to the character of
                  perfection, as your questions also strongly demanded; because we see that
                  the disposition of all of us is inclined to and our will bent on a fall rather
                  than on hastening to perfection; and therefore we must inquire and ask and
                  speak about the forms of our illness and the remedies for it, lest the whole
                  body be struck with the ulcers of sin, and grow putrid with the tumour of
                  negligence, and we be thereby thrust into the abyss of torment; for we
                  learn from the divine <persName>Paul</persName> who said: <quote>There is great fear of falling into the
                     hands of the living God</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a34" target="#n34" n="34"/> What has been spoken is sufficient to stir up
                  the memory of the discreet.<!-- The translation has a close double bracket here that corresponds to the one above. I don't really understand either. -->
               </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-3">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-3.1" n="7">
                  The history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1320">John</persName> the perfect Nazirite is ended.
               </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 37, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Near Amida; see ch.58 (fol.131 r˚ b).</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 37, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>I Cor., VI, 13.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 37, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>James, V, 5</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 38, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I Cor., II, 9.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 39, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Acc. to P.-Smith <hi rend="singleQuotes">
                        <foreign xml:lang="la">anchusa tinctoria</foreign>
                    </hi>; but this seems to be a bush, 
               not a <hi rend="singleQuotes">large tree</hi>. Perh. the <hi rend="singleQuotes">
                        <foreign xml:lang="la">syagrus</foreign>
                    </hi> of Pliny, <title>N. H.</title>,
               XIII, 9 is meant; but, as the tree had given its name to the town of Singara (Shigra), the name must be presumed to be Syriac.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 39, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr" dir="rtl">ܝܠܦ</foreign>, like <foreign xml:lang="grc">πυνθάνομαι</foreign>, is often used in this sense, 
               though unknown to the lexicons; cf. ch.10 (fol.35 v˚ b) and ch. 54 (fol.124 r˚ b).</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 39, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>B <hi rend="singleQuotes">he should</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 39, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>B <hi rend="singleQuotes">boulder</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 40, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I. e. heal his head on the ground; cf. ch.13 (fol.49 r˚ b).</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 42, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>As the monks of Amida were expelled in 512 (see Introd.), we get 496 as the date of the beginning of his monastic life.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 42, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., X, 33.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 42, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Ibid., V, 10.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 43, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. the demons.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 44, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This would be in 533.</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 45, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I Cor., III, 13.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 45, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Hebr., X, 31.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 45, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. XXXVI, 7</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 45, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>This phrase, which occurs again below (p. 46, l. 6), perh. means <hi rend="singleQuotes">May it not be?</hi>
                    <hi rend="singleQuotes">What is the difficulty?</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 46, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., VII, 22, 23.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 46, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ibid., V, 3, 4.</note>
                <note xml:id="n21" target="#a21" n="21">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 46, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. LXXXIV, 11(?).</note>
                <note xml:id="n22" target="#a22" n="22">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 46, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>John, V, 24.</note>
                <note xml:id="n23" target="#a23" n="23">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 48, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Gen., XXII, 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n24" target="#a24" n="24">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 48, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Id., XXI, 12; XXII, 7.</note>
                <note xml:id="n25" target="#a25" n="25">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 50, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I Pet., III, 10, 11.</note>
                <note xml:id="n26" target="#a26" n="26">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 50, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., XXV, 46.</note>
                <note xml:id="n27" target="#a27" n="27">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 50, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Id., VII, 14.</note>
                <note xml:id="n28" target="#a28" n="28">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 50, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr. (B <hi rend="singleQuotes">and not</hi>).</note>
                <note xml:id="n29" target="#a29" n="29">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 50, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>Rom., VII, 24.</note>
                <note xml:id="n30" target="#a30" n="30">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 51, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n31" target="#a31" n="31">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 54, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>II Tim., II, 26.</note>
                <note xml:id="n32" target="#a32" n="32">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 54, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., VII, 12.</note>
                <note xml:id="n33" target="#a33" n="33">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 55, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Hebr., X, 31.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
