<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/796">Abraham and Maron</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/795"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/797"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/796.xml -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-4" n="4">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-4">
                    <head type="main">Next the Fourth History, of the Saints <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1546">Abraham</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885">Maro</persName> the Brothers.</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-4.1" n="1"> These [before] our time and in our time itself gained distinction upon a column
                  and seized the crown of victory through their marvellous ways of life; in whose
                  case also the words found in the Psalms of the Holy Spirit may also aptly be sung:
                     <quote>How good and how beautiful it is for brethren when they dwell
                     together</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> for to these
                  two holy brethren alike it is good and beautiful and marvellous that they dwell
                  together, as is written in the Psalmist. These two holy brothers were by birth
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from a village called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2804">Kalesh</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> in the territory of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2737">Amida</placeName>; and the elder whose name
                  was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1546">Abraham</persName> was first
                  moved by zeal, and he went and dwelt in a monastery called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1524">Arʿa Rabtha</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> in the territory of
                     <placeName>Ingila</placeName>. Now there was a high stone column to which men
                  used to come in order to stand upon it in that monastery; and <pb n="57"/>
                        <pb n="57"/>after he had broken himself for a space of ten years by great labours
                  he himself ascended the column. And, when his brother whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885">Maro</persName> had seen it, he also came
                  and entered upon the road from the first mile and began to walk soundly, while
                  those two brothers were thenceforward illustrious for mighty labours of
                  abstinence, until they received gifts of the Spirit also, the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1546">Abraham</persName> receiving even the
                  power of working healings and driving out demons, he being above, while his
                  brother the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885">Maro</persName>
                  shunned these things, saying: <quote>Sir, I will have nothing to do with things
                        that<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> gain very vain glory for
                     someone but deceive certain persons</quote>. And many would seek assistance<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> with these; but he when he saw these
                  persons coming to be healed would shut his door and remain silent. For from the
                  very beginning also he had made a great segment from a hollow tree and set himself
                  up inside it, having taken it inside the enclosure in a certain corner (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γωνία</foreign>); and he used to stand in it. And there was a
                  little door, and he would stoop and come out by it when he wanted; for this
                  monastery is situated on the top of a mountain, and there used to be heavy snow
                  there and violent winds; and so he would go out and remove the snow <pb n="58"/>
                        <pb n="58"/>and recite the service and stand, while his brother from above
                  used to chide him and say to him: <quote>Wherefore are you thus killing yourself?
                     What good is this to you? Why do you afflict yourself?</quote> But he would
                  weep and say: <quote>Woe is me, sir, forgive me, sir. Which, pray, is the keener,
                     this snow that afflicts for a little time, or the eternal torture that does not
                     end, or the smoky burning of bitter thirst? Lo! how bitter is the intensity of
                     the stress (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άνάγκη</foreign>) is made known by the
                     torment of that wretched rich man.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> And for this reason let this wretched body which has an end be tortured
                     here, and, be there sorrows or joys, they will soon come to an end, and it will
                     not last</quote>. When the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1546">Abraham</persName> heard in his soul and
                  in his thoughts how God's judgment was always depicted in his heart, and, because
                  he pitied him in that his colour was changing nature from the intensity of the
                  snow, used to urge him to go into his tree-segment, because the blessed man also
                  above found it difficult to repel the violence of the winds, he in order to carry
                  out his brother's order would comply, and would go inside weeping, and beat upon
                  his face and say: <quote>Woe is me woe is me the sinner; <pb n="59"/>
                            <pb n="59"/>who will entreat for me that I may escape from that torment?</quote> And so
                  these brothers were objects of marvel, their fame going as far as the country of
                  the Persians. And, when <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1546">Abraham</persName> [...] thirty-eight years [...] completed thirty eight<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> years on the column [...] deep and he
                  [...] in his days, [...] When a great clamour everywhere arose and a great number
                  of people in the villages and of the cities gathered together, they went up [...]
                  the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1546">Abraham</persName>. And
                  what was purposed in the heart of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885">Maro</persName> was not known to anyone;
                  but when a ladder had been set up he first went up; and, when he stood at the top
                  of the ladder, he found the holy old man bending down and sitting with his face to
                  the <placeName>east</placeName> with his head between his knees, and he bade him a
                  farewell; and so he took him up and carried him out weeping, and handed him
                  towards [...] below him<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/>[...] the
                  cast and for himself and prayed. And he entered and went [to] his brother's
                  [place]. And the multitude (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όχλος</foreign>) [was seized
                  with sorrow] and affliction on his account that was more than that in memory of
                  the holy blessed man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1546">Abraham</persName>, while they cried and said, <quote>Do us a kindness, our
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3625">father</persName>; and, if so
                     be you are thus purposed, [come down] and first comfort us [and] go up at once
                     in peace, because we shall all be made glad by this. And, if you do not come
                        <pb n="60"/>
                            <pb n="60"/>down, we will all go up there</quote>. And, being
                  from affliction and many sighs unable to speak to the people, he beckoned to them
                  with his hand to be silent and wait for him. And, when he had suppressed his own
                  tears for a short time and restrained his weeping, he then said to them:
                     <quote>Brethren, pray for me, and leave me alone. I for my part did not desire
                     this and my Lord knows, but, in order that my holy brother's place may not be
                     vacant, I hope by his prayers that, until you bring me down as he came down, I
                     shall henceforth not come down hence. But take the saint and wrap him up for
                     burial, and go; and pray for me, that I may not be deprived of my brother
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1546">Abraham</persName>'s portion
                     with all the saints. Now take away the ladder, and pray for me</quote>. When
                  this had been done and the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1546">Abraham</persName> had been wrapped up, the assembly dispersed, and each man
                  went to his place in peace, being amazed and glorifying God.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> But the blessed man would in great affliction cry night
                  and day to God, saying, <quote>My Lord, let not this stone be to me a conductor to
                     torment, but a conductor to life</quote>. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-4.2" n="2"> The first instance in which the power of the prayers of the saint was seen
                  happened in the case of me the wretched one the writer of these things. <pb n="61"/>
                        <pb n="61"/>My parents were acquainted with him, and every son who was born
                  to them used to die at the end of a year and a half or two years: and, when I
                  myself was born and came into this perturbed life, and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> on the same day as my brothers the stroke that had
                  slain them attacked me, as my parents used to tell me, they immediately repaired
                  to the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885">Maro</persName>,
                  carrying me and weeping with sobs, crying to him, <quote>Have mercy upon us, and
                     pray to God for this one who has remained to us. Perhaps God will hear your
                     prayers, and save him; since, if your prayers do not persuade God, this child,
                     to judge from the example (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σημείον</foreign>) of his
                     brothers, is already housed in the grave</quote>. Then the blessed man, seeking
                  to silence my parents' sobs, said to them: <quote>Be quiet, be quiet. <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John</persName> shall not die before
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885">Maro</persName>
                        </quote>.
                  Then, as they used to say to me, I was struck with silence as it were to death;
                  and my <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3624">mother</persName> wailed
                  with a loud voice, and said: <quote>Sir, he is dead</quote>. Thereupon what
                  happened? The blessed man (they said) in answer to the woman's vehement wailing
                  jested and said: <quote>Do not wail, woman. <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John</persName> shall not die before
                     me</quote>. And, guarding against the suspicion of pride like a wise merchant
                  who keeps his riches that they may not be seen and plundered, and <pb n="62"/>
                        <pb n="62"/>to make these persons think that it was not he who was the cause of the
                  deliverance, he said to my <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3624">mother</persName> laughing: <quote>Believe in our Lord and go, take yourself
                     into the refectory (?),<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> and ask
                     for some lentils from the servitors'? cauldron,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> and bring them to him, and he will at once live and
                     recover, and eat of them</quote>. And she, as thinking that he was jesting with
                  her in order to silence her, herself went on wailing more than before, saying,
                     <quote>Henceforth, sir, this child's lentils are ripening in the grave. This
                     child will now never again taste lentils here</quote>. The holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885">Maro</persName> says to her: <quote>See,
                     you do not believe that from these lentils of these brothers you will gain a
                     son, through the help of the prayers of the same brothers</quote>. Then he said
                  (they told me) to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3626">a certain
                     brother</persName> who was present: <quote>Brother, go in and fetch some
                     lentils in a cup, and drop them into that baby's mouth</quote>. That brother
                  also (they told me) says: <quote>Sir, for the baby, pray for him. This baby has
                     already passed to that world</quote>. And again (they said) he repeated to that
                  brother, <quote>Go do as I have told you</quote>. That brother, in order not to
                  oppose the intent of his command, went laughing and saying: <quote>I am going to
                     raise your son from the dead by the eating of lentils</quote>. And he <pb n="63"/>
                        <pb n="63"/>went in and fetched the lentils and came (they said) and
                  stood above me, and said to the blessed man: <quote>Sir, here are the lentils. You
                     will see one who is dead eating lentils</quote>. The saint says to him:
                     <quote>Take some with your finger, and insert them into his mouth three
                     times</quote>. And that brother (they said) took them and inserted them into my
                  mouth, saying: <quote>See! These things have been done to no purpose</quote>. And
                  at the third time (they said) I opened my eyes, and moved my tongue round, and
                  tasted and turned round and roused myself. And then they cried to the blessed man,
                     <quote>Sir, sir, pray; and perhaps our Lord will effect a deliverance by your
                     prayers, for the child has roused himself</quote>. But the blessed man did not
                  see them; because women used to stand and speak to him from one gate of the
                  enclosure as far behind him as a woman's voice will carry, and they were not
                  allowed to set foot inside, and he also never saw the face (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>) of a woman, but her speech<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> only. Then he said to my <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3624">mother</persName>: <quote>Give him lentils
                     to eat as much as he wants, and take him and go, rear him for two more years,
                     and bring him to me here; because this is my son, and there is no possibility
                     of his dying until his <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3625">father</persName> is buried</quote>. And so they took me and <pb n="64"/>
                        <pb n="64"/>went away; and, after two years, they gave me to the blessed man
                  my spiritual <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3625">father</persName>, by
                  whose prayers I was saved from death; and the power of his blessing was dissolved
                  and nullified through my evil deeds; for God used to work acts of great and
                  marvellous power through him in all the words that he spoke even when laughing.
                  And from that time the multitude (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όχλος</foreign>) began
                  to gather together to the saint in numbers many times as great as came to his
                  brother <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1546">Abraham</persName>;
                     which<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> was also very hateful to
                  him that anyone should come and bring him a sick person or one possessed with a
                  demon, but he would at once drive him out, saying these words: <quote>O wretched
                     men, what has misled you into leaving God's altar and his great power which
                     took up its dwelling in the saints who were slain for his name, and loved him
                     and did his will, and coming to me the wretched man and provoker of God? Indeed
                        (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρα</foreign>), if I were one who pleased and loved
                     God and did his will, you ought not to have come to me and neglected the
                     saints, let alone when I provoke and irritate God. And there is another thing
                     that you should know and understand, that it was because of my sins that I came
                     up here to ask mercy like every man, not because of my righteousness. To <pb n="65"/>
                            <pb n="65"/>myself the madman and man of evil life why do you
                     come?</quote> And so this wonderful man as if to drive arrogance from him and
                  avoid the vain praise of men, even though he was gentle and kind, would violently
                  and with anger those who came to him to gaze at him as a great and righteous man.
                  Yet again, if he were vexed with any particular persons, he would at last as if to
                  entreat and console say reproachfully and kindly these words: <quote>My sons, be
                     not vexed at what I am saying to you. You do not know the evil one's wiliness
                     and deceitfulness. If I give way to these matters of sick and possessed
                     persons, and allow them an opportunity of coming to me, lo! fiends will at once
                     go and seize women and girls and many persons, be it by means of a fever, or of
                     ulcers, or of affection of the eyes, or of affection of the head, or so as to
                     foam in them, and will work in them without their knowledge, as if one were to
                     say <quote>Go jeer in the face of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885">Maro</persName>
                            </quote>, for, as
                     soon as they bring them here, as if our own prayers were indeed powerful and
                     mighty and drove out fiends, the fiends who have brought about these diseases
                     will abandon them, and in their deceitfulness depart and withdraw, in order to
                     carry out the wiles of their deceitfulness, and cheat us into having <pb n="66"/>
                            <pb n="66"/>some such thought of ourselves as that we ourselves are indeed
                     righteous and expellers of demons and healers of diseases, so that by this
                     means we may be puffed up and be arrogant, so as to add disaster to disaster,
                     and receive blows upon blows, and cease and remit these constant petitions to
                     God for our sins, as if we were indeed righteous, and through the guilefulness
                     of the demons' deceitfulness cease the rapid running on the road of repentance
                     for our sins, and utterly sink in the stormy sea of sins, and there be
                     fulfilled against us the saying <quote>Their days were consumed in vanity, and
                        their years rapidly</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/>
                     which also happened to many, and they childishly yielded to the deceitfulness
                     of the demons, and thought that what was done to them through the deceits of
                     the fiends was true, and fell and were caught in the depths of evils, through
                     the vain suppositions that they were indeed casting out demons and healing
                     diseases, and do not understand that they are sitting in a dark house, and
                     their heart is feeding on ashes, and they are making their souls a
                     dwelling-place for demons, and filling parts of themselves with the stain of
                     sins, and the demons are mocking at them because they are indeed casting them
                     out without considering our Lord's <pb n="67"/>
                            <pb n="67"/>saying which he
                     uttered beforehand to these men, which shall be spoken to them, when they shall
                     say <quote>My Lord, my Lord, did we not in thy name prophesy, and in thy name
                        cast out fiends, and in thy name do many deeds of power?</quote>, then shall
                     the bridegroom answer and say to them, <quote>Verily I say unto you I know you
                        not, depart ye from me workers of iniquity, go to the fire prepared for the
                        devil and for his angels</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> Now, my sons, who will not tremble at the pronouncement of despair
                     addressed to those who yielded to the deceitfulness of the fiends'
                     guilefulness, who thought that they were casting them out, when he hears from
                     the good Lord <quote>I know thee not</quote>? As for my wretched and sinful
                     self, as I have probed the deceits of the demons, it is enough for me to drive
                     them out of my stained self only; for to me it seems that the saints who truly
                     possessed power and authority from God over these used to shrink from and shun
                     being made spoil of, let alone us who, while all the wickedness of the demons
                     is ambushed within us, and all their envy and their deceit and their desires,
                     think of ourselves that we are driving fiends out of one another. Would that I
                     were driving my own out</quote>
                    </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-4.3" n="3"> By saying these things every day to many the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885">Maro</persName> did not per<pb n="68"/>
                        <pb n="68"/>suade men not to come to him every day; and, being distressed, and it
                  not being open to him to act as he did in his brother's days by withdrawing when
                  he saw these, accordingly, in order to extinguish out of him the reputation of
                  gravity, he would speak to many with simple and ridiculous words, and like a fool,
                  saying, <quote>Why then (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρα</foreign>) come you to a
                     madman? Have you, pray, seen anyone fouler<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> than I am? Since I am bound to this stone like a
                     malefactor, or as a vicious dog is bound by a chain that he may not escape and
                     do hurt not that, if it were open to me to escape hence, I should like each one
                     of you have both made a house for myself and had a wife and children? or
                     understand you not that in my case also it is on account of my sins and my
                     spots and my crimes that God bound me to this stone, like a judge who puts a
                     criminal in bonds?</quote> But those who knew the blessed man's character and
                  way of life used to say when they heard these things: <quote>Yes, sir, we also are
                     come as to a criminal, and as to one who is bound; for a man goes and sees even
                     murderers when they are bound in prison</quote>. But those who were not
                  thoroughly acquainted with him, who saw the <pb n="69"/>
                        <pb n="69"/>blessed man
                  thus distressed by the multitude of people and crying that they hindered him from
                  holding intercourse with God, wondered greatly. Once <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3627">a certain layman</persName> came to him
                  whose <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3628">wife</persName> was barren
                  and bore no children; and he knew his disposition, and had gained the privilege of
                  free speech (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>) with him, and by chance
                  he came in and found him removing his nails, because his toe-nails were of
                  vigorous growth, so that they were a finger or two fingers long. And, having
                  prayed and sat down and begun to speak, he says to him: <quote>Sir, pray for your
                     bondmaid that she may have children, since I have no heir and hope of my
                     house.</quote> But he looked at him and wondered, and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/> he says to him: <quote>Then (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρα</foreign>), so-and-so, how is it do not consider the words that you are
                     speaking to the most wretched of all men? How is it that you say these things
                     to me? llave you not heard the blessed apostle saying, <quote>If a man hath not
                        been able to rule his own house aright, how will he be able to rule God's
                           church,?<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/>
                            </quote>
                            <!-- eb, There is an incorrect quote here.--> How will one who has
                     not been able to pray for his soul, which has become by its disposition barren
                     of the progeny of good deeds, and through his prayer made it fruitful in
                     spiritual progeny, be able to pray for women that they <pb n="70"/>
                            <pb n="70"/>may bear children?</quote> The man says to him: <quote>Sir, there is no
                     difficulty with God in making the former fruitful as well as the latter. And if
                     wish you will have mercy upon me. By God who chose you do not neglect
                     me</quote>. When he heard that he adjured him by God, he was moved by two
                  considerations, one that he did not wish to state of himself at all that he could
                  do any such thing, and another that he heard God's name and his heart trembled;
                  and he said to that man: <quote>Why did you adjure me by God about a matter that
                     is not my concern and is too hard for me? Accordingly take what I will give you
                     without men being aware it of, and go hang it on your wife, and you shall have
                     a son, and you shall call his name <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885">Maro</persName>, no man being aware of
                     it</quote>. And he took one of his toe-nails and wrapt it gave it him; and, in
                  order that he might not honour it as a martyr, he said to him: <quote>Observe that
                     it is not a martyr, nor is this bundle <foreign>hnana</foreign>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/> but it is a herb that I give you.
                     See that no one undo and see it; and next year you shall carry your son also
                     and bring this herb with him to me</quote>. Then that man took it and went; and
                  he hung it on his wife; and at once God gave to her and she received conception,
                  and she bare a son. When this happened, it seemed to everyone no ordinary wonder
                  that so-and-so the <pb n="71"/>
                        <pb n="71"/>
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3628">barren woman</persName> had received
                  conception; so that to many it presented itself as a matter of doubt that
                  so-and-so <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3628">the barren
                     woman</persName> had received conception, until her conception came to
                  delivery. And, many being amazed, they used to assemble before her and in great
                  wonder eagerly inquire, <quote>What is the cause from which this has been brought
                     about in you after so long a time?</quote> But she, fearing the saint's
                  injunction, and in order that the power of his prayer and the miracle wrought for
                  God's glory might not be concealed, announced to everyone: <quote>So-and-so the
                     blessed man sent me something, and I do not know what it is, and God gave me a
                     son</quote>. Then all men in amazement glorified God. And many are the things
                  that God wrought through these two holy brothers, things that even surpass written
                  records and the capacity of the ears; but the acts of the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1546">Abraham</persName> even far surpass those
                  of this man.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a21" target="#n21" n="21"/> But this is enough
                  that I have undertaken to shorten his history and run through it in simple
                  fashion, observing two things, one that miracles are from their character
                  dillicult to believe, and another that I have determined in my mind not to be a
                  witness with my <pb n="72"/>
                        <pb n="72"/>handwriting except only of things
                  confirmed by the sight of my eyes as well as the written record, and not to repeat
                  in writing what I have only heard,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a22" target="#n22" n="22"/>
                  but the things that I have both heard and also seen to these I bear witness; as in
                  the case of this saint also I bring to record the same deeds that I have seen and
                  know, those that are small and a litile inferior, because of the unbelief and
                  doubt of many, abstaining from mentioning marvels that are greater than the ears
                  can bear. Even the actual things that we have repeated we have repeated for the
                  glory of God, and that God's love towards those who love him and keep his
                  commandments may be known to us ordinary (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ιδιώτης</foreign>) and simple men, and how great freedom (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>) God gives to his bondmen before him. There
                  was again <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3629">a certain
                     magistrate</persName> in the same village in which this saint had his stand
                  (with whom I also was well acquainted) who was an abominable and impious man, an
                  oppressor of the poor, and one who caused orphans and widows to groan, and a
                  perpetrator of all wicked deeds of covetousness and of injustice and of rapine;
                  and he had much property and a great house, and bondmen and bondwomen. And that
                  man bore himself proudly in the world; and the orphans and widows and other poor
                  persons used always to flee from him and take refuge <pb n="73"/>
                        <pb n="73"/>with
                  the blessed man. Then the saint would send and fetch him and gently entreat him,
                  admonishing him and saying: <quote>My son, beware, and keep what God has given
                     you, for you are not in need. Wherefore do you oppress these broken-hearted
                     poor, not one of whom has daily bread in his house? Remember the scripture that
                     says, <quote>The orphans and the widows and them that turn to me ye shall not
                        overreach nor defraud</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a23" target="#n23" n="23"/> and again <quote>I am the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3625">father</persName> of the orphans and the judge of the
                        widows</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a24" target="#n24" n="24"/> and again,
                        <quote>By reason of the plundering of the poor and the groaning of the
                        needy, therefore will I arise, saith the Lord, and I will make deliverance
                        openly</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a25" target="#n25" n="25"/> But for my
                     part I pity you, my son; since, however much God's justice turns away, it is
                     impossible that it will not some time be roused against evil-doers</quote>; and
                  again, <quote>Neither yet think that this the saints before whom these poor people
                     come and groan is a void thing; lest it beroused against you, and you and your
                     house perish.</quote> But that wretched man stirred himself up arrogantly at
                  the instigation of his <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3625">father</persName> the devil, whose will he did according to what our Lord said
                  to the Jews, <quote>The will of your <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3625">father</persName> ye do</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a26" target="#n26" n="26"/> so<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a27" target="#n27" n="27"/> this man derided and scorned the man of God, <pb n="74"/>
                        <pb n="74"/>saying, <quote>Blessed man, sit on your stone, and mind
                     your own business. I will not neglect matters which I know to be proper for me.
                     Sit in your monastery and be quiet, and you have no concern with me, and I none
                     with you. Every man's sins or righteousness as the case may be falls to his
                     lot. Those who are going up to heaven will not entreat for me</quote>. When
                  that captive man whom the evil one had taken captive had said these things, he
                  turned his ace to go out from the blessed man's presence; but the blessed man was
                  distressed and wept, and, carried away by his feelings, called him with a loud
                  voice and said to him: <quote>Woe for you, my son! a pronouncement of wrath has
                     gone out against you from heaven (for think not that I the sinner have cursed
                     you; far be it from me). But repent and I with you will entreat God's justice
                     for you, and perhaps you will be delivered</quote>. But he became more
                  hardened, and said: <quote>Let justice do what it likes</quote>; and so he
                  departed; while the blessed man shed tears and said: <quote>I, my son, am innocent
                     of your sin. You know</quote>. But at midnight fire broke out from the four
                  corners (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γωνία</foreign>) of his house, while the blessed
                  man saw it descending and coming down from heaven to earth like a ball (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σφαίρα</foreign>); and so that flame immediately made itself
                  master of his house and his property, and seized all his furniture; <pb n="75"/>
                        <pb n="75"/>and the man with <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3633">his domestic slaves</persName> hardly escaped naked because God wished to make
                  his presumption known to him, while all the precious belongings and valuable
                  furniture and the rest of the property contained in the buildings (?) were all
                  burnt. But the blessed man, when he saw it, weeping called his own <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3630">presbyter</persName> who stood before him,
                  and said to him: <quote>Go my son to that wretched man and see what has happened
                     to him</quote>; telling him with great sorrow what had occurred. And the
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3630">presbyter</persName> with two
                  brothers went to the village by night, and they found all the buildings (?) of the
                  house levelled with the ground, and blazing so much that the stones themselves
                  looked like coals of flame, and were all dissolved into chalk within the fire. And
                  fever and dysentery at once attacked that man, and in ten days he died; and his
                  wife survived, a great and distinguished woman; and the rest of the property that
                  remained to him was ruined; and of the vineyards and the fields that were thick
                  with their trees and their fruits, and were regarded with awe (?) in the
                  neighbourhood, some sank to the ground in two years, and the rest were plundered
                  from the owners(?);<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a28" target="#n28" n="28"/> and of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3633">the slaves</persName> some died,
                  and some ran away; and the woman herself became blind; and so receiving the com:
                  mand (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έντολή</foreign>) the woman also died, and she
                  became a subject of gossip and <pb n="76"/>
                        <pb n="76"/>of lamentation; while the
                  blessed man, whenever the memory of them came into his mind, would say to us
                  mournfully with many sighs: <quote>See, my sons, how the fiends destroy God's
                     creation. How can we avoid shedding bitter tears for this poor man, when we
                     think how far the evil one puffed him up until he destroyed him, and even
                     blotted out his memory from the earth?</quote> But for many days, while we were
                  kneeling before him at the end of the service, because sometimes the service was
                  performed in his presence, he would with many tears speak to us these words of
                  admonition from the divine Scriptures: <quote>See, my sons, how we stand, and what
                     majesty we take upon our tongues. Take care, lest we stand before that awful
                     and mighty Being as corpses without sense, while our hidden man has been
                     secretly made captive by our deceitful adversary, lest we make a mockery of God
                     when we stand before him, lest we insult the honour of his glory, who does not
                     himself need our praise, but because of his gracious mercy called forth by the
                     praise of him draws us to himself</quote>. At another time again, that is
                  always when he was thinking with wonder of that <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3629">magistrate</persName> and remembering him
                  with tears, he would again turn the warning toward us by way of admonition, <pb n="77"/>
                        <pb n="77"/>saying, <quote>See, my sons, again how severe and awful and
                     rapid is the sentence of the fall of pride, and beware of it, observing how
                     many high and powerful men it has overthrown. And why repeat many instances,
                     when it cast down from heaven to earth and overthrew him who himself causes it
                     among men; even as he also to-day is again in the same fashion eager to
                     overthrow everyone as he was overthrown, just as that wretched <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3629">magistrate</persName> also was suddenly
                     consumed and destroyed by his pride and haughtiness? Let us fear, and tremble,
                     and entreat <persName>Christ</persName> our God to repel it from us by the
                     prayers of his saints</quote>. Concerning the rest of the admonition which
                  treated of every form of life in his discourse, and concerning his warning and his
                  exhortation addressed not to us only, but to laymen also as well, and even to
                  women and children and fathers and all classes, what is there to write and say? To
                  the brothers who were with him he would offer spiritual education and warnings and
                  exhortation to spiritual things, and to his own priests and those of the villages
                  and all who resorted to him he would give expositions of the solemnity of their
                  service and the magnitude of the penalty, and the greatness also of the glory, and
                  would incite and warn them to stand earnestly and with fear in their stations and
                  serve in their classes; laymen again and women <pb n="78"/>
                        <pb n="78"/>he would
                  restrain from oaths and blasphemies and adultery and the other evil things, and
                  exhort to good things, declaring to them also the awful sentence of justice,
                  besides the other things which in the gentleness of his mercifulness toward all
                  men he<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a29" target="#n29" n="29"/> disseminates. But after a
                  space of about twenty years during which this saint stood upon the column a
                  revelation was shown to him concerning the terrible hosts of barbarians, i. e.
                     Huns,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a30" target="#n30" n="30"/> who should come forth to
                  chastise men upon earth. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-4.4" n="4"> Then with mournful weeping he continued with a loud voice vehemently giving vent
                  to his sorrow in the middle of the night and wailing out of a mournful heart,
                  beating on his face and speaking to God thus: <quote>What, Lord, will happen to
                     thy churches and thy monasteries? What, my Lord, wilt thou do to thine altars
                     and thy service and thy sacred vessels, Lord<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a31" target="#n31" n="31"/> Woe to us whose sins have brought these things to
                     pass, and not thy gentleness. What will happen to thy priests and the people of
                     the believers, whose corpses are cast out as dung upon the face of the earth
                     with none to bury them? In mercy chastise me and not in anger, Lord</quote>.
                  And, when all of us heard the voice from above in the monastery within, having all
                  been awoken we were agitated; and, because it was a short time before ser<pb n="79"/>
                        <pb n="79"/>vice, we did not ourselves dare to go into his enclosure;
                  but the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3630">presbyter</persName> who
                  was next after him went in, and cried out and said to him, <quote>Sir, give your
                     blessing</quote>, three times. And then he ceased his sobbing, and the
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3630">presbyter</persName> said to
                  him, <quote>Why, sir, is your holiness distressed with weeping, and so above all
                     when speaking?</quote> But the saint said to him: <quote>My son, go, and wake
                     the brethren, and stand up to prayer; and grieve for my<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a32" target="#n32" n="32"/> latter end, for what times I have been preserved,
                     and what in my days my eyes see and my ears hear</quote>. And, when his sobs
                  came up more than ever, the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3630">presbyter</persName>, having been himself also seized with trembling,
                  continued crying to him and saying: <quote>What is the matter with you, sir? Tell
                     me what it is</quote>. Then he said to him: <quote>My son, go and pray; because
                     a sword has gone forth from the presence of the Lord, and slaughter has
                     prevailed among the believers, and also over the churches and monasteries,
                     because men have provoked God</quote>. And the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3630">presbyter</persName> said, <quote>If you
                        please,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a33" target="#n33" n="33"/> I entreat you to
                     inform me what you have seen</quote>. Then the blessed man was angry and said
                  to him: <quote>Remove yourself now, my son, from my presence. Have you not come to
                     pry? Please go and recite the service; or, if not, begone now from
                  here</quote>. And they went out and stood up in service and in prayer all the
                  night until <pb n="80"/>
                        <pb n="80"/>the morning. But after twenty days the hosts
                  of the Huns came forth, and they covered the land of the
                     <placeName>East</placeName>, and none so numerous as they had appeared in the
                  land of the <persName>Romans</persName>, nor had it ever been heard that any Huns
                  except these presumed to cross the <placeName>Euphrates</placeName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a34" target="#n34" n="34"/> indeed even among the blessed man's
                  companions also arose haste to flee to the fortress, while they said to him,
                     <quote>Sir, if you please we will carry you down, lest we leave you alone and
                     you suffer distress, or they burn the monastery or anything happen to you
                     yourself</quote>. But he in confidence in his Lord said to them, and again not
                  by way of boasting: <quote>I, my sons, am ready for suffering, and my life and
                     death are in God's hands. Go, and the Lord be with you, and pray for
                  me</quote>. When they saw it, three of them, trusting in the blessed man's
                  prayers, bravely remained, while he was unaware that they had remained, and the
                  rest fled to the fortress. But those who remained went in to him, and he saw them
                  and was astonished, saying: <quote>Have you not gone away, my sons?</quote>, and
                  they say to him: <quote>Either life or death is better for us with you, our
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3625">father</persName>
                        </quote>.
                  But he said to them: <quote>Pray, my sons, that we may not <pb n="81"/>
                            <pb n="81"/>die in sin; but, if not, men cannot kill us, because <quote>they who are with
                        us are more than they who are with them</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a35" target="#n35" n="35"/> But these things I did<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a36" target="#n36" n="36"/> not say to you before, in order that we ourselves
                     also may fulfil every man's lot; for if it were open to me I also would have
                     fled, in order that we may not seem to be in any thing better than the rest of
                     men</quote>. But the heart of those who had remained with him was agitated,
                  though they were encouraged by him, and they continued peering out on all sides,
                  and they liſted up their eyes and see, and lo! a host of horsemen appeared before
                  the monastery; and they themselves trembled and were disturbed; and they ran to
                  the blessed man and say: <quote>Sir, pray, because the evil has come. Sir, what
                     shall we do? Lo! they surround us</quote>. But the blessed man continued
                  beating on his face, saying, <quote>What, my sons, can I say? What? Am I myself
                     better than all those who are now being cut in pieces and cast out, and are
                     being eaten by beasts and by birds?</quote> But the host of the barbarians,
                  when they had reached a distance of half a mile from the monastery, overtook men
                  who were fleeing toward the blessed man's monastery, and with cries uttered in
                  their language they pursued them, and they advanced as far as the monastery fence;
                  and those who were fleeing before them escaped inside. And <pb n="82"/>
                        <pb n="82"/>these, like men who are driven along or whose eyes are blinded or whom a
                  deceiver carries along so that they do not see, passed round the monastery hall on
                  one side and half on the other, and, just as if those whom they were pursuing were
                  running before them, they passed by the gate of the monastery on this side and on
                  that, thinking that they were just overtaking and catching the fugitives. And this
                  their shouting indicated; since, while there was no one in front of them, they
                  themselves continued crying and running, and so they passed round the blessed
                  man's monastery, and not one of them entered within it; and so it is believed by
                  everyone that it was not even seen by them at all, because they passed by the side
                  of its walls and gates, and did not even lift up their eyes and look upon the site
                  of one of its sides, although it is seen even at a great distance, and the blessed
                  man's station moreover is seen above, being black. And so by the help of his
                  prayers neither was the monastery harmed, nor anyone who was in it or round it,
                  though in all the villages round it complete destruction was carried out, and even
                  in the village itself they were for a whole day, and, while the whole monastery
                  and the blessed man were seen by the village like a sun, their eyes were blinded,
                  and they did not see him. Many such things God used to perform <pb n="83"/>
                        <pb n="83"/>through the blessed man's prayers; though, if I had undertaken to tell
                  all the things that were performed in sick men through the outward word only
                  without his applving his touch to these, either in the case of demons who came
                  out, or in that of the other acts of healing, one by one, I should have wandered
                  into a greatly protracted series of stories; but these few out of many are enough
                  to stir up praise to God in those who are convinced by them. As to the time of his
                  standing he completed on the column in this trial of endurance (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) twenty-nine years and fifteen days, and in the
                  tree-segment in his brother's days he passed eleven years, so that for the time of
                  the trial of endurance (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) in which he
                  laboured there are made up forty years.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a37" target="#n37" n="37"/> Bat as to the rest of his labours and the painfulness of his standing
                  and the austerity of his habits I reckon it superfluous to write. But his
                  successor is his own <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3630">presbyter</persName>, his kinsman, a man who from the very earliest time, when
                  he himself was not standing on the column, himself also walked rightly and soundly
                  in his very footsteps. For, even while the saint was alive, all men used to
                  congratulate him, because such a man was standing before <pb n="84"/>
                        <pb n="84"/>him; and after him he bore all his burden and that also of the whole convent
                  with stainless purity without murmur and without complaint; while the fame of his
                  kindness and of his own habits also was everywhere spoken, through the charity to
                  the poor which he possessed, and the love towards his brethren, and the reception
                  of strangers, who used to carry his fame everywhere. But, after the blessed man's
                  decease, he made himself a hut and a station in the enclosure itself, and therein
                  carried out his labour and his abstinence; but he did not as yet mount the column.
                  But I removed myself thence because of the neighbourhood of bodily kin (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>), and joined myself to the communities of the
                     <persName>Amidenes</persName>, while they themselves were in the exile
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>) decreed by the heretics. </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-4">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-4.1" n="5"> The history of the saints, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1546">Abraham</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885">Maro</persName> the brothers, is finished.</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 56, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. CXXXIII, 1.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 56, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>A short distance W. of Ingila and S. of the Tigris (see map in Lynch's
                  <title>Travels and Studies in Armenia</title>, and Dyakonov, p.33, n. 3).</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 56, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>I.e. <hi rend="singleQuotes">great soil</hi>
                </note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 57, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 57, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Text corrupt; this is the sense required.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 58, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Luke, XVI, 23-28.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 59, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>We should perh. read <hi rend="singleQuotes">28</hi> and complete the
               sentence as <hi rend="singleQuotes">when A [had practised asceticism] 38 years [and]
                  completed 28</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 59, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>I can make nothing of the 2 words which follow in the copy.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 60, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Mark, II, 12.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 61, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Mss. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 62, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Lit. <hi rend="singleQuotes">house of weeks</hi> (servitors' office); perh.
                  <hi rend="singleQuotes">kitchen</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 62, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>
                    <foreign>Hebdomadarii</foreign>, the batch of monks to whom the duties of
               the kitchen etc. were allotted for the week.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 63, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 64, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 66, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. LXXVIII, 33.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 67, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., VII, 22, 23; XXV, 41. A similar notion appears in ch. 15.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 68, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. <hi rend="singleQuotes">fairer</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 69, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 69, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>I Tim., III, 5.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 70, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Lit. <hi rend="singleQuotes">grace</hi>; a martyr's dust mixed with oil and
               water; see Zach. Rh., VIII, 6 and P. Smith, s.v. <foreign xml:lang="syr" dir="rtl">ܚܢܢܐ</foreign>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n21" target="#a21" n="21">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 71, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>If the text is right, the meaning must be that M. performed fewer miracles
               because he shrank from performing them. V. D. and L. in translation state the
               opposite without emending the text.</note>
                <note xml:id="n22" target="#a22" n="22">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 72, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This perh. refers to miracles only; but see p. 3, n. 1.</note>
                <note xml:id="n23" target="#a23" n="23">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 73, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Zech., VII, 10.</note>
                <note xml:id="n24" target="#a24" n="24">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 73, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. LXVIII, 6.</note>
                <note xml:id="n25" target="#a25" n="25">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 73, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. XII, 6.</note>
                <note xml:id="n26" target="#a26" n="26">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 73, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>John, VIII, 44.</note>
                <note xml:id="n27" target="#a27" n="27">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 73, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n28" target="#a28" n="28">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 75, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This can hardly be right; we require rather <hi rend="singleQuotes">by
                  robbers</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n29" target="#a29" n="29">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 78, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. God.</note>
                <note xml:id="n30" target="#a30" n="30">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 78, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>515 (?); see p. 19, n. 2. The better known invasion of 531/2 (Zach. Rh., IX,
               6; Proc., <title>Bell</title>., XXI, 28; Chr. Edess., A. S. 843) was after M.'s
               death.</note>
                <note xml:id="n31" target="#a31" n="31">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 78, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Jer., X, 24.</note>
                <note xml:id="n32" target="#a32" n="32">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 79, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n33" target="#a33" n="33">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 79, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>This seems to be the meaning of <foreign xml:lang="syr" dir="rtl">ܐܢ ܦܩܕ
                  ܐܢܬ</foreign> here and below (p. 80, l. 5). The expression occurs several times in
               this work, but is unknown to the lexicons.</note>
                <note xml:id="n34" target="#a34" n="34">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 80, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">And these things happened in the reign of
                  Justinian, in his 8th year</hi>; but this is 534/5, long after J. had left the
               monastery, which he did not do till after M.'s death, and, even if we read <hi rend="singleQuotes">Justin</hi> and make the year 525/6, the difficulty remains.
               Probably therefore the words are a scribe's interpolation, as v. D. and L.
               suppose.</note>
                <note xml:id="n35" target="#a35" n="35">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 81, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>II Kings, VI, 16.</note>
                <note xml:id="n36" target="#a36" n="36">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 81, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">did I</hi>. I do not follow the argument.</note>
                <note xml:id="n37" target="#a37" n="37">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 83, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>If the Hun invasion was in 515, this would bring M.'s death lo 523/4: but,
               as J. seems to have left the monastery not later than 522/3 (see lntrod.), we may
               perh. place M.'s death in 522 and take 20 (p. 78) as a round number. This throws back
               Abraham's death to circ. 493, and the beginning of his ascetic life to circ.
               455.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
