<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/797">Simeon and Sergius</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/796"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/798"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/797.xml -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-5" n="5">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-5">
                    <head type="main">Next the Fifth History of the Holy and Divine Men <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2095">Simeon</persName>, The Recluse and
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3154">Sergius</persName> Also the
                  Recluse His Zealous Disciple.</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-5.1" n="1"> In the same village moreover from which the saints of the
                  column derived <pb n="85"/>
                        <pb n="85"/>their origin (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> a great and
                  holy old man who was called <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2095">Simeon</persName> had also been living as a recluse ever since the time when
                  the saints <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3184">Abraham</persName> and
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885">Maro</persName> the brothers
                  began their discipleship,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> a man
                  whose own storym also was not unworthy of great admiration; who also in his own
                  person carried out the words of the apostle which say, <quote>They crucified their
                     flesh with all its affections and its lusts</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> This man because of the great hospitality that existed
                  in him (and he was eager to carry out the ministration to the saints personally
                  with his own hands like the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3184">Abraham</persName> the patriarch) used not to shut himself up in a hut like
                  all the others, because indeed as I have said he would not endure to do so, since
                  he used to perform the ministration to the brothers who resorted to him. For the
                  love of the great <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3184">Abraham</persName> had been implanted in him toward all men, and on this
                  account he made himself some small huts, and a little enclosed court and garden
                  without a gate; and thus he was shut up within them with one disciple or <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3686">jew</persName> two; and at one place he
                  made for himself a way of ascending and descending the wall, on account of the
                  strange brothers who resorted to him; and thus therefore he fulfilled in himself
                  two purposes, both that of seclusion and <pb n="86"/>
                        <pb n="86"/>that of the
                  entertainment of strangers. Whenever any stranger wearing the habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) came to him, he would himself open the gate at
                  the top of the wall for him, and he would come up outside and come down to him;
                  and he would take hold of him and embrace him and kiss his hands; and he would
                  fall upon his face and forcibly take hold of him, and would kiss his feet and his
                  heels, leaping and crying and saying, <quote>I thank my Lord
                        <persName>Jesus</persName> that he has come to-day and visited the sinner,
                     and has thought me worthy to see him in his holy bondmen</quote>. And, as soon
                  as they had made the prayer and were sitting down, he would run to a vessel
                  containing wine, and would fill a certain gourd-cup that had been made by him and
                  a roll (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κολλύρα</foreign>),<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> and before anything else would fall on his face before
                  the man's feet whoever he might be, that he might take that cup; and the
                  hospitable man would invite him to eat that roll (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κολλύρα</foreign>) also, saying to him, <quote>You are weary; but for God's
                     sake be kind and take this first</quote>. And, while that man was receiving it,
                  he himself would run and prepare a footpan (<foreign xml:lang="grc">λεκάνη</foreign>) and bring water, and would prepare a towel and put it round
                  his loins, in the manner which our Lord also taught; and thus he would wash them
                  whether they were one <pb n="87"/>
                        <pb n="87"/>or many, not allowing them to speak
                  nor to refuse. And, alter he had washed them, he would hastily raise this water to
                  his own face and his arms, just as if he were desirous of washing; and, that no
                  one might understand what he was doing, he would withdraw to one side while these
                  men were occupied in conversation; and he would drink of it three times, and then
                  leave them; and he would go and pour out wine and oil and anoint them. And
                  immediately he would run to that garden, which measured about ten cubits one way,
                  and about twenty the other (and the heavenly blessing rested upon the place to
                  such an extent that what was sown in it was enough for forty men), and he would
                  bring something from it and cook a dish, and then he would entertain whoever might
                  be there, and he would make merry and joyfully eat and drink, so that anyone who
                  was not acquainted with the saint's love and his manner of life would think that
                  he enjoyed himself in this way every day. But he would say in cheerful exultation,
                     <quote>Blessed am I that I am to-day eating and drinking with my Lord
                        <persName>Jesus</persName>
                        </quote>. For, whenever there was a stranger with
                  him, he would thus joyfully eat and drink without reserve; and, as soon as there
                  was no stranger, he would go as <pb n="88"/>
                        <pb n="88"/>much as six and seven and
                  even ten days, and taste nothing, saying, <quote>For my part without King
                        <persName>Christ</persName> I cannot eat bread, unless he has thought me
                     worthy to sit at table with him in his bondmen</quote>. Many were deterred by
                  him from going in to him on account of his reverend character and on account of
                  his great humility in their presence; others again who were a little lazy like me
                  could not pass more than two nights or three at most with him, on account of his
                  great watching and protracted recitation of service; for there was no possibility
                  of his sleeping more than two hours of the night; but he would stand up in the
                  night and lift up the head of <persName>David</persName>, and, until the day
                  broke, where he began there he would end;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> and, if it happened that he had some time over, he would leave the
                  brothers resting, and would himself go and recite the gospel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">εύαγγέλιον</foreign>) in the hut, weeping, until daybreak, and
                  then he would go and rouse them to and rouse them to perform matins. And so this
                  wonderful man ended his days in this severe labour and abundant love and great
                  earnestness, showing fortitude all the days of his life, so that men were not able
                  to support and endure the burden of his great labours more than a short time,
                  except <pb n="89"/>
                        <pb n="89"/>
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3154">Sergius</persName> his disciple an earnest man like himself, who also imitated
                  him in everything, for for the space of twenty years he laboured with him in the
                  excellent life, and accordingly the saying of the Spirit that<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> was uttered in the prophet as from
                  the mouth of the Lord, <quote>This is my rest with which I will rest the
                     weary</quote>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> was fulfilled in
                  the splendid old man and his diligent son, insomuch that they made a guest-house
                  outside, and there used to entertain all who came with everything out of the
                  window, whether they were women or laymen, each as was proper for him. Again also,
                  since the task of performing anything in the way of manual work was not open to
                  them, and that they might not continue to eat the bread of idleness, and be
                  despised by themselves and by their conscience, the blessed men formed a plan and
                  chose for themselves to teach boys, and this they did out of the window, since a
                  seat was placed inside the window, and hours were appointed for the boys to come,
                  that is in the morning and in the evening; and, when they had taught one class
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχολή</foreign>) to read the psalms and the
                  Scriptures, and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> they bad withdrawn
                  after being strengthened, another came in of little infants, thirty or forty of
                  them, and they would learn and go to their homes, because <pb n="90"/>
                        <pb n="90"/>it was a populous village, and many people used to come out from it. And so the
                  old man continued doing until the time of his end; and accordingly the boy-pupils
                  supplied their needs. After a space of twenty years <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3154">Sergius</persName> his disciple asked the
                  saint that he also might shut himself up at a certain place close by the village.
                  And, seeing that he was eager for every good deed, he said to him: <quote>I, my
                     son, should not be at all satisfied at your leaving me. However, I will not as
                     it were stand in your way so as to prevent you from making progress in running
                     on the road of righteousness as far as you are able; but go and may our Lord
                     prosper you</quote>. Then, having received this permission, he went out and
                  went and shut himself up, not after his master's method, but straitly in a lonely
                  hut the size of his stature, yes and even smaller than his stature; and there
                  henceforth he performed the rest of his labours. But, before doing this, because
                  there were many <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3686">Jews</persName> in
                  that village, and they went about with great freedom (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>), he carried on a continuous contest against them, and
                  every day he used to contend against them as with slayers of God, being fervent in
                  the love of his Lord, and gnashing his teeth, and saying: <quote>These crucifiers
                     of the <pb n="91"/>
                            <pb n="91"/>Son of God should not be allowed to live at
                     all</quote>; and he used to upbraid Christians who had dealings with them in
                  the way of taking and giving. And one day he led about twenty of their disciples
                  by night, and took fire, and went and burnt their great synagogue-house, with
                  their books and their trumpets and all their furniture, saying, <quote>As for
                     those who crucified my Lord <persName>Jesus</persName>, I will never make peace
                     with them</quote>. But these men, when they saw that all their hope had been
                  cut off through the burning of their books and of all their furniture, lamented
                  bitterly; and, because they were settled in the territory<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> of the church of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2737">Amida</placeName>, and used to pay many
                  contributions (<foreign xml:lang="grc">συντελείας</foreign>) to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3687">the members of the church</persName>, out
                  of desire for the abundance of their gold all <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3687">the members of the church</persName>
                  became their supporters, threatening the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3154">Sergius</persName> and saying: <quote>This
                     man wishes to destroy the property of the church</quote>. But the zealous man,
                  when these men had gone into the church of the city to prefer an accusation, while
                  the fire was still in their synagogue, collected all his master's disciples with
                  him and all the others from the village, and they took water, and went and put out
                  that fire; and they cleared all the soil; and they collected stones, and within
                  three days built a small martyr's chapel in that place, in the name of the Blessed
                     <pb n="92"/>
                        <pb n="92"/>God-bearer; and, at the end of one week the whole of
                  the martyr's chapel was completed, while the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3686">Jews</persName> assembled and looked on
                  and lamented, not knowing what to do; and that synagogue remained a martyr's
                  chapel for ever. Then the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3686">Jews</persName> who had gone in to prefer accusation against them took courage
                  and came to fight with the blessed men; since the old man also did not hold aloof
                  from the fight with them,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> though he
                  did not take it to heart, that is, he was not moved with indignation. When they
                  saw that all hope for their place of worship was lost, and it had now received the
                  form of a church, and the name too of the Blessed one, and they were no longer
                  able to approach it, inasmuch as they had been reinforced by those in whose
                  territory they were settled, they also took fire by night and went and set fire to
                  the old man's huts, before his disciple separated from him, and burnt them; though
                  perhaps even this also was brought about provientially by the grace of God, in
                  order that the blessed man might have a little breathing-space in his huts,
                  because he was muchfi straitened in them. Then <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3154">Sergius</persName>, because he was an
                  agile and energetic man, rebuilt them firmly in a few days. And, when these men
                  began to build a synagogue, <pb n="93"/>
                        <pb n="93"/>he waited for them till they
                  were on the point of finishing, and he occupied one night in pulling it to pieces
                  stone by stone, and thus he engaged in this contest against the crucifiers before
                  shutting himself up; so that during the days of his life the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3686">Jews</persName> could not raise their head
                  there. But, when they saw that he had shut himself up, they thought that they were
                  rid of him; and for this reason they went on building confidently; and, when they
                  had completed and finished,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> he sent
                  his disciples by night, and they burnt it; and so they desisted from building all
                  the days of his life. But the old man went on adding to the course of his habitual
                  practices and to his love toward God and toward strangers every day, until he grew
                  old and became very infirm, after completing forty years in these huts and in
                  seclusion and labours; and at last he became emaciated and was not able to stand
                  unless they supported him; and so he was laid upon his rug and recited the service
                  night and day; and, as soon as he saw a stranger, he would twine his hands
                  together above his head, and weep with sighs, sobbing and weeping like a baby.
                  And, because I knew the power of the old man's prayers and of his blessings, I
                  always used to repair to him from all quarters to receive his blessings, so that
                  once I did not shrink from making the effort and coming <pb n="94"/>
                        <pb n="94"/>down even from <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> in order to gain his blessing before his departure
                  from the body; and the merciful God, who saw the desire of my feebleness,
                  preserved him in the body till he had made me heir to a small portion of his
                  goods, though I for my part turned out a squanderer of his property. I found that
                  for one year he had been laid up with disease of the liver and of the spleen and
                  of all the internal organs, insomuch that the breath which came up from inside him
                  used to cause his tongue to dry up, and cracks appeared on it, as on a barefooted
                  man's heel. When he heard that I had come in to him and saw me, he went on for an
                  hour embracing me and weeping, and unable to speak; and he beckoned and they
                  brought him water, and he took some on his finger and wetted his tongue; and he
                  took oil and smeared it on it while we both wept; and then he spoke and said,
                     <quote>Now that I have seen my son, let me die</quote>. After I had spent a few
                  days with him, some strangers came to him; and, when he saw them, he placed both
                  his hands on his head, and went on weeping. And I said to him: <quote>Wherefore do
                     you weep, our father?</quote>, and he looked at me; and his tears went on
                  flowing more than before; and in the midst of his sighs he said <pb n="95"/>
                        <pb n="95"/>to me these words: <quote>How, my son, can I do aught but weep for my
                     wretched self, since <persName>Christ</persName> comes to me on his own feet,
                     and I cannot rise and wash them and drink</quote>. But I, in order that he
                  might be comforted, was staying to him: <quote>Be not distressed at this, our
                     father. When <persName>Christ</persName> wished, you washed him as much as he
                     wished. And now his will be done. And your own will also he knows, and will not
                     do you wrong, weep not</quote>. But he said to me: <quote>He, my son, has not
                     done wrong and does not do wrong; but I am a doer of wrong and one who have
                     done him wrong, and who am doing him wrong. If I had served him as I ought to
                     have done, he would have allowed me to serve him all my life; but because I
                     provoked him and neglected the service of his bondmen, for this reason he cast
                     me down.</quote> And so, though he was already a dead man in the body, men
                  supporting him and setting him up, he insisted on their coming up before him and
                  on stretching out his hand, weeping, and dipping it in the water in which the
                  strangers had been washed, and taking it and smearing it on his body. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-5.2" n="2"> A short time before a persecution had been set on foot by
                  those who served the synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> and men who possessed the name only
                  of churchmen <pb n="96"/>
                        <pb n="96"/>expelled many by the use of barbarian troops,
                  and many they arrested and imprisoned, and many they drove to death by stripes
                  inflicted with rods, and many again they greedily and mercilessly plundered; and
                  others they reduced to submission by force, and, when men had eaten and drunk wine
                  and meat, they would open their mouths with lashing<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> hides (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σκύτος</foreign>) and
                  rods, and stuff their oblation into their mouths. When these things were being
                  done in the very village in which these blessed men lived (inasmuch as it was in
                  fact inhabited by real churchmen), at first they went straight to the blessed
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3154">Sergius</persName> the old man's
                  disciple; for of the saint himself they were afraid; for indeed some time before
                  also they had used blandishments with him under the cloak of persuasion and
                  affection, and they saw the vigour of his disposition, when they on their part
                  thought that they were deceiving him as a simple man; for he on his side went on
                  openly anathematizing them. Therefore they shrank from him; and for this reason
                  they bent the whole mass of their plans in the direction of his disciple. And,
                  when they went and began to speak craftily to him with coaxing words, while they
                  praised the head of their congregation, that is their <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3688">bishop</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> and wished to deceive and say, <quote>There <pb n="97"/>
                            <pb n="97"/>is nothing wrong, but agree and accept</quote>, while they on
                  their side said these things to him softly and gently, as is said in the psalmist,
                     <quote>Their words are softer than oil, and they are arrow-points</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> inasmuch as he was vigorous in his
                  speech and in his zeal, he cried from his own window to them, <quote>Stand up and
                     go away from here, evil wicked men. You are cursed with the deceitful doctrine
                     that you proclaim, since you advise me to accept a quaternity instead of the
                     Holy Trinity, in which I was sealed for my life's salvation</quote>. But these
                  men, when they heard the anathema upon them spoken boldly<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> without fear, on their part also began their own
                  methods, saying to him, <quote>Come, come out; since there is no possibility of
                     your staying here</quote>. But the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3154">Sergius</persName> said to them: <quote>I
                     will not come out of myself. But, if you turn me out, as our Lord
                        <persName>Jesus</persName> lives, <quote>whose I am and whom I
                        serve</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/> in the middle
                     of the church, while the whole city is assembled, before them and in the middle
                     of them I will go up to the chancel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">βήμα</foreign>),
                     and will curse you to your faces, you and the head of your
                  congregation</quote>. And his speech was thus keen and cutting, like a sword. But
                  these men were yet more agitated by his words, and they pulled down his <pb n="98"/>
                        <pb n="98"/>window, and dragged him out. But the blessed man did not neglect
                  to carry out his oaths upon them; but the same night he set out and went to the
                  holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885">Maro</persName> the stylite;
                  because this happened in his days, while he was still alive, even as he also
                  contended for twenty years in this struggle (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) against the heretics;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/> but the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3688">bishops</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/> were much
                  ashamed before him and feared to send, or anyone to presume<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a21" target="#n21" n="21"/> to enter his monastery; unless perhaps one of the
                  clergy (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κλήρος</foreign>) came in to him as it were by
                  chance, who had voluntarily numbered himself in the ranks of the heretics, and
                  being ashamed acknowledged the falsity of their<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a22" target="#n22" n="22"/> faith. And thus two <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3688">bishops</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a23" target="#n23" n="23"/> passed away and died one after the other, and none
                  molested the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885">Maro</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a24" target="#n24" n="24"/> But the
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3688">third</persName>third, in order
                  to gratify those who appointed him, was lifted up in his pride and presumed to go
                  to the blessed man, advising and admonishing and cajoling him, in order to bring
                  him into subjection to the evil impiety of the accursed synod of
                     <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>. And, because this was a great and celebrated
                  man, this man craftily sought means to catch him if only in speech, in order by
                  himb to deceive many, and say <quote>Lo! <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885">Maro</persName> of his column agrees
                     with us</quote>; and, <pb n="99"/>
                        <pb n="99"/>if this had really happened,
                  numberless persons would indeed have been deceived and brought to this.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a25" target="#n25" n="25"/> But the blessed man, as one that was
                  a valiant man and wise in God, did not yield to his blandishments, nor yet fear
                  his threats; but as a valiant man he in everything showed him to be a denier of
                  God and a deceiver, with all of his opinion, and that instead of the Holy Trinity,
                  which was delineated in the prophets and proclaimed in the holy church in the
                  apostles, those men were secretly introducing a quaternity, diluting their
                  blasphemies like a drug with honey to give them to the people of the believers to
                  drink. And so he was dismissed from his presence, humbled in his pride and with
                  his plans frustrated, since he had not effected his intention, and even
                     recoiling<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a26" target="#n26" n="26"/> from his presumption,
                  as he also soon received a castigation on this account and a humiliation of his
                  pride, which we decline even to describe because of its fearful nature and the
                  greatness of the subject. When therefore the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3154">Sergius</persName> came to the very same
                  holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1885">Maro</persName>, and he was
                  startled at his coming and shed bitter tears, on account of the distresses of the
                  believers and the cruelty of the renegades, and the ejection of the saints from
                  their places of close seclusion chosen for God's sake, he said to him, <quote>What
                     is it, my son? what has happened that <pb n="100"/>
                            <pb n="100"/>you have come
                     out of your seclusion? Why have you come hither? And what has befallen our holy
                     father your master? Has even he also come out?</quote> Then the zealous
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3154">Sergius</persName>, himself also
                  weeping, related to him everything that had been done, and that they had been
                  afraid of his master, and had not gone to him; and that he himself moreover had
                  bound himself by oaths to go and go in and curse them before the whole city inside
                  the church if they turned him out. When we all too being assembled heard these
                  things also, we too desired to learn about the ejection of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3154">Sergius</persName> the recluse; but our
                  father continued beating on his breast and weeping with sobs, saying, <quote>Alas
                     for my latter end and for my evil days, to what times I have been preserved. It
                     is in thy power, Lord, to take my soul from me, rather than that I should see
                     the buffetings and the distress of thy believers, and the persecution of thy
                     church which thou purchasedst with thy precious blood.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a27" target="#n27" n="27"/> Have mercy, Lord, and remember thy church which
                     thou purchasedst with thy passion and savedst with thy cross. <quote>Behold
                        from heaven</quote>, my Lord, <quote>and see; and visit this vine, and the
                        vine which thy right hand planted</quote>
                            <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a28" target="#n28" n="28"/>
                        </quote> While our holy father was saying these
                  things with feeling and with bitter sobs, at the sound of his pitiful sobs we all
                  wept with him. But, when he had been <pb n="101"/>
                        <pb n="101"/>silent for a little
                  time and longer (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μάλλον</foreign>), he gave orders that
                  the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3154">Sergius</persName>
                  should retire to rest, inasmuch as he was weary from the effort of the walk. After
                  a day and two days had passed, he was desirous of carrying out his oaths and
                  hurling anathemas at them, the men who were persecuting God's holy church. And,
                  when the blessed man tried to restrain him and said, <quote>My son, you are
                     throwing yourself into a struggle (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>), and
                     you are about to fall into the hand of cruel and merciless men, and you have a
                     trial to endure. Beware</quote>, the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3154">Sergius</persName> said to him: <quote>Our
                     father, pray for me for our Lord's sake; because I for my part am prepared for
                     suffering, and I will contend until death with the renegades who malign God,
                     and fire will not frighten me, nor sword, nor scourgings, nor rakes.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a29" target="#n29" n="29"/> But only pray for me</quote>.
                  But the blessed man, when he saw his firmness and readiness, blessed bim and sent
                  him away, saying, <quote>Our Lord strengthen you, my son. Go in peace</quote>. But
                  the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3154">Sergius</persName> set
                  out and reached the city on the holy first day of the week at daybreak. Then he
                  went straight to the church; and, while the whole city were sitting<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a30" target="#n30" n="30"/> after the morning lauds, among them
                  he also who enjoyed the name of the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3688">bishopric</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a31" target="#n31" n="31"/> and <pb n="102"/>
                        <pb n="102"/>listening to the preacher (because those who were
                  orthodox (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθόδοξος</foreign>) also used to be present in
                  the congregation during the hearing of the service and the lessons and the
                  preacher, only without communicating), then suddenly there was seen at the door of
                  the church a strange and outlandish sight; and everyone was startled when they saw
                  a form (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) that was not their own, an
                  anchorite coming in, clad in a patchwork of rags made of sackcloth, and carrying
                  his cross on his shoulder, (and he came straight in without asking a question
                  straight to the middle of the church, without speaking or turning this way and
                  that), and, while the preacher was standing and speaking, he paused, while
                  everyone was struck with astonishment, and they looked to see what the matter was.
                  But the blessed man, as soon he reached the chancel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">βήμα</foreign>), planted his cross on the step and made to mount. And, when he
                  had begun to mount one and two steps in silence, and everyone supposed that he was
                  going to say something either to the city or to the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3688">bishop</persName> or to make a request of
                  them, he on reaching the third step, where the preacher was standing, flung out
                  his hand and seized him by the neck and grasped him tightly, and said to him:
                     <quote>Evil wicked man, our Lord commands <quote>Give not that which is sacred
                        to the dogs, nor pearls,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a32" target="#n32" n="32"/>
                        before the swine</quote>
                            <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a33" target="#n33" n="33"/>
                     wherefore are you speaking the words of God before men who deny him?</quote>
                  And <pb n="103"/>
                        <pb n="103"/>he swung his hand round and gave him a buffet, and
                  distorted his mouth; and he seized him and shook him down. And he himself sprang
                  up and stood in his place at the top of the chancel-steps (<foreign xml:lang="grc">βήμα</foreign>), and said: <quote>Cursed are the renegades; cursed are the
                     persecutors; cursed is the synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, and
                     whosoever assents to it. Cursed is every soul that receives the oblation from
                     you and assents to your opinion unless he repents</quote>. When the blessed man
                  had cried these words in a loud voice, great turmoil and confusion prevailed among
                  the clergy (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κλήρος</foreign>) and the people and the
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3688">bishop</persName>, some
                  threatening, some expressing indignation, some crying, <quote>This man is a
                     teacher of error, let him be arrested</quote>, and some crying, <quote>Let no
                     man lay hands upon him and die</quote>. And so the whole city became one
                  intense volume of sound, the adversaries expressing indignation, and the believers
                  joy. Since they feared on account of the people to lay their hands upon the
                  blessed man, the man who was practised in pernicious wiles rose and quieted the
                  people by saying, <quote>Be so good<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a34" target="#n34" n="34"/> as to let the blessed man come into the vestry,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a35" target="#n35" n="35"/> and we will speak, and see what his business
                     is</quote>; and thus he succeeded by a trick in withdrawing him from the
                  people, and then accomplishing his will upon him. When the crowd (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όκλος</foreign>) had dispersed, <pb n="104"/>
                        <pb n="104"/>then
                  like ravening beasts who find a sheep in a field and all attack it, each of them
                  tearing his own portion (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μέρος</foreign>) from it, so they
                  all savagely attacked the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3154">Sergius</persName> from all sides, so that even his body could not supply each
                  of them with a place where he could exercise his cruel disposition and cause pain
                  by striking him. At last, when they had vented all the venom of their malice upon
                  him, they went on to shave off the hair that marked his ascetic profession<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a36" target="#n36" n="36"/> (since he as well as the blessed
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2095">Simeon</persName> his master
                  wore the honoured habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) of the
                  anchoritic life), and put irons upon him, and assigned men to him, and sent him to
                  a certain house of anchorites in <placeName>Armenia</placeName> that is called
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2867">ʿTryz</placeName>, and it would
                  be better for a Christian to be confined in the lowest dungeon in a prison than in
                  that <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2867">monastery</placeName>; for
                  anyone who was sent thither was thenceforth reduced to utter despair, on account
                  of the boundless severity of sufferings which<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a37" target="#n37" n="37"/> they used to inflict on the man who was sent to them;
                  since they were very zealous for the tenets of the heresy, and they used to reckon
                  it as an act of justice to torture believers; and accordingly they would stand
                  over them like executioners not one or two <pb n="105"/>
                        <pb n="105"/>or a hundred
                  only, but each one of them would pull him<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a38" target="#n38" n="38"/> from his side and torture him (for they were about three hundred); and
                  accordingly those who used to send to that place were confident that their purpose
                  would be accomplished. But the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3154">Sergius</persName>, being confined in the middle of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2867">monastery</placeName> on the third floor,
                  by God's help escaped from them on the third day, having even slipped out of his
                  irons, and a certain pitcher for water, which was the only thing that he had with
                  him, he also in the keenness of his ardour grasped in his hand, and he climbed up
                  to his window on the third floor, and he leaped with that pitcher also in his hand
                  and the irons with it,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a39" target="#n39" n="39"/> and he came
                  down and stood on his feet outside the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2867">monastery</placeName>. And so he escaped
                  from them, and came to his holy master; and he fell upon his face before him, and
                  said: <quote>Now, sir, I have learned that God loves you, and in truth hears you;
                     since, unless the mediation of your prayers helps, it would have been quite
                     impossible for me to see your face</quote>. When he had related everything to
                  him, he gave thanks to the merciful God, who cares for his own. But afterwards he
                  asked his master's permission to go and build a <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2837">monastery</placeName> in a certain
                  mountainous district belonging to a village <pb n="106"/>
                        <pb n="106"/>called
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2837">Qlwfyte</placeName>; and he gave
                  him permission and blessed him. And he took his cross and the saint's blessing,
                  and went and erected his cross there, and recites the service. And he kneels down
                  and prays for three days, night and day; and then some people saw him and gave
                  information in the village, and they came to him. And on his informing them of his
                  purpose they were pleased; and each one of them ran to his house to find something
                  to bestow upon the blessed man's prayer in proportion to his ability, while by the
                  common effort also a <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2837">monastery</placeName> was erected in that desolate mountainous region in a few
                  days, there being abundance of water there. When the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2837">monastery</placeName> was completely
                  finished, the adversaries heard the news, <quote>That audacious stubborn man is
                     building a <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2837">monastery</placeName>
                     in such-and-such a place</quote>; and men were at once appointed to go out and
                  pull the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2837">monastery</placeName> down
                  to its foundations, <quote>and signify to him also besides that you desire to
                     arrest and bring him to us;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a40" target="#n40" n="40"/> and
                     if you see that he is ready and willing to come, leave him alone, and do not
                     bring him upon us</quote>. Then these men set out, having first declared and
                  professed <quote>Why! perhaps he will be afraid, and run away from us</quote>.
                  And, when they came, they found the blessed man standing and reciting the service;
                  and, when they saw him, they said to him: <quote>Since you have built a <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2837">monastery</placeName> without an order,
                     we <pb n="107"/>
                            <pb n="107"/>have been ordered to pull your <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2837">monastery</placeName> down, and conduct
                     you to the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3688">bishop</persName>
                        </quote>. But the blessed man in the fervour of his zeal said
                  to them with oaths: <quote>If you are in truth ordered to pull down and desire to
                     do so, I myself will lay the first ax to it; and, if it is your desire, I will
                     go in before you to him who sent you</quote>. When those men saw that he was
                  ready, they were afraid of him; and they say to him: <quote>We are truly ordered
                     to pull it down and are prepared to do so; but we do not desire you to come in
                     to the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3688">bishop</persName>
                        </quote>. Then the blessed man was the first to run and take his
                  ax, and he fixed it in the wall and said to them: <quote>Come, here is glory to
                     our Lord</quote>. And they, because they were many, pulled the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2837">monastery</placeName> down to the ground in
                  one day; and he himself was assisting them to do the work of demolition. But, when
                  they had finished their task, and he was himself urging them to drag away the wood
                  and stones and throw them outside, he said to them: <quote>Listen now, evil wicked
                     men. In truth I say to you that, if renegades against grace deserved it, I
                     would thank you greatly for labouring with me here. God without your being
                     aware of what you have done constrained you to subvert these huts, as to which
                     I was truly exercised in my mind in consequence of the fact that they were
                     built in haste; and now I trust in our Lord <persName>Jesus</persName> that I
                     shall now build a <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2837">monastery</placeName> indeed here</quote>. <pb n="108"/>
                        <pb n="108"/>They
                  say to him: <quote>If you rebuild, we will pull it down again</quote>. He on his
                  side says to them: <quote>Take what I say to you. By him who built the house of
                     all this world and was called the carpenter's son, if so be you pull it down as
                     many as thirty times, I will make it more spacious and I will make it stronger
                     than before all my life, if you pull it down</quote>. Then they departed
                  thence, wondering at the fervour and the vigour of the man. But the blessed man
                  dug and delved deep and laid the foundations on a spacious basis; and he built a
                  substantial <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2837">monastery</placeName>
                  and made it strong; and he planted a plantation, and made an enclosure round, and
                  made a very desirable place.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a41" target="#n41" n="41"/> And,
                  after a short time, he went to be blessed by the holy old man his master; and the
                  summons followed him, and he ended his life with him there, bearing good
                  testimony; and he was laid out<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a42" target="#n42" n="42"/> and
                  buried by his spiritual father, who was still in good health. But the holy
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2095">Simeon</persName> after living
                  brilliantly in his seclusion forty-seven years<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a43" target="#n43" n="43"/> ended his days, and himself also fell asleep in
                  peace; by whose prayers, with those of all the saints his companions, may all
                  wretched men gain merey in the day of judgment. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-5.3" n="3"> The tale of the healings and deeds of power and cures
                  that God wrought <pb n="109"/>
                        <pb n="109"/>for his glory by the hand of this holy
                  old man the time is too short for me to relate; and for this reason, wishing to
                  avoid a lengthy narrative, I have recorded these things only, thereby falling far
                  short of the splendid glories of this man; to which it is not only I who was a
                  witness, but all who knew him; so that another great and holy man and seer of
                  spiritual visions also who lived in the south in the inner desert bore testimony
                  about the old man, since, when some men from the territory (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χώρα</foreign>) of the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2737">Amida</placeName> were going down for the
                  harvest (because men are in the habit of going down to the southern country for
                  the harvest), they heard of that saint, and were eager to go and be blessed by
                  him; and, when they had gone and had come to him and been blessed by him, he asked
                  them, <quote>Whence are you, my sons?</quote>; and they said, <quote>From the
                     north of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2737">Amida</placeName>
                        </quote>. The blessed man said to them: <quote>But what, my
                     sons, do I for my part really know? and wherefore did you come to my wretched
                     self? If you are from the north of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2737">Amida</placeName>, wherefore did you not
                     go to the pillar of light which stands in the northern country, who to-day has
                     been serving God in his saints for forty years, and has not grown tired or
                     weary, nor is yet satiated with so <pb n="110"/>
                            <pb n="110"/>doing? Wherefore,
                     my sons, did you not go to this man, who has refreshed God in the persons of
                     the weary, who has also caused the savour of his practices and of his purpose
                     that is good and acceptable<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a44" target="#n44" n="44"/> at
                     all times to reach to the heavens of heavens?</quote> But these men on hearing
                  these things from the saint fell on their faces and continued entreating him and
                  saying: <quote>Who, sir, is he of whom you have said these things to us?</quote>
                  But the blessed man, in accordance with what our Lord also taught in his
                  preaching, <quote>A city built upon a mountain cannot be lid</quote>, and again
                     <quote>So let your light shine before men, that they may see your good works
                     and glorify your Father that is in the heavens</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a45" target="#n45" n="45"/> says to these men: <quote>This is <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2095">Simeon</persName> the recluse who is
                     living in seclusion on the top of a hill in the village of
                        <placeName>Kalesh</placeName>. But go to him, and greet him from me and say
                     to him, <quote>An idle sinful man settled in the desert entreats you, <quote>As
                           I know you to be always fervent in your love towards God, perform an act
                           of love, and pray for me</quote>
                            </quote>
                        </quote> But these men, as the
                  blessed man enjoined them, came and informed the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2095">Simeon</persName> of these things; and
                  they said to him as he said to them, seven years before his departure from the
                  body, <pb n="111"/>
                        <pb n="111"/>repeating all these words which that saint said.
                  And all continued giving thanks to God. </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-5">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-5.1" n="4"> The history of the holy and divine men <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2095">Simeon</persName> the recluse and
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3154">Sergius</persName> the recluse
                  his zealous disciple is ended. </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 85, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Kalesh;see p.56.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 85, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>M. began 1' years after A. (p. 57); but, even if we reckon from the time
               when M. ascended the columan (p. 59), we get 483 as the date of the beginning of
               Simeon's seclusion, which is inconsistent with later statements; see p. 94, n.
               1.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 85, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Gal., V, 24.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 86, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 88, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I.e. he repeated the whole psalter.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 89, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 89, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Is.,XXVIII,12.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 91, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>is a literal rendering of <foreign xml:lang="grc">παροικία</foreign> and
               means ecclesiastical jurisdiction, not property. Hence the <foreign xml:lang="grc">συντέλειαι</foreign> were not rent, but a kind of blackmail paid to secure
               protection against attacks of this kind.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 92, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>It can hardly be meant that he left his cell, but only that he encouraged
               his disciples to go.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 93, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I.e. the synagogue; the object has perh. fallen out.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 94, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This cannot be earlier than 540 (see Introd.) and therefore, if we reckon 40
               years from 483 (p.85, n. 2), we must suppose that S. lived 17 years in the descrepit
               state described above. Moreover 47 years is given below as the full time of his
               seclusion, which therefore did bot begin before 493.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 95, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>As Maro was still living (p. 98), this must be the persecution or 521, and
               the <hi rend="singleQuotes">short time</hi> must be at least 19 years.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 96, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Litt. <hi rend="singleQuotes">of <foreign xml:lang="grc">φραγέλλια</foreign>
                    </hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 96, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Abraham of Amida (Assem., B. O., II, p. 51; Zach. Rh., X.2; Mich., p.
               272).</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 97, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. LV,22.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 97, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>With <foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρήσσια</foreign>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 97, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Acts, XXVII, 27.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 98, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>It is hard to understand to what this alludes.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 98, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. of Ingila; see p. 56.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 98, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n21" target="#a21" n="21">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 98, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>As this must have been between 519 and 522, the succession or bishops at
               Ingila must have been rapid. In 519 a Monophysite held the see (Zach. Rh., VIII,
               5).</note>
                <note xml:id="n22" target="#a22" n="22">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 99, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. the synod.</note>
                <note xml:id="n23" target="#a23" n="23">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 99, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">he (Maro) had not done his will and even
                  recoiled</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n24" target="#a24" n="24">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 100, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Acts, XX, 28.</note>
                <note xml:id="n25" target="#a25" n="25">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 100, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. LXXX,15,16.</note>
                <note xml:id="n26" target="#a26" n="26">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 101, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Instruments of torture.</note>
                <note xml:id="n27" target="#a27" n="27">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 101, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>This seems to show that at that time Eastern congregations sat (no doubt on
               the floor) during the sermon.</note>
                <note xml:id="n28" target="#a28" n="28">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 101, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Abraham of Amida.</note>
                <note xml:id="n29" target="#a29" n="29">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 102, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n30" target="#a30" n="30">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 102, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Matth. VII, 6.</note>
                <note xml:id="n31" target="#a31" n="31">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 103, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See p.79.</note>
                <note xml:id="n32" target="#a32" n="32">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 103, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>House of the <foreign xml:lang="grc">διαχονικόν</foreign>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n33" target="#a33" n="33">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 104, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This appy. means thal they shaved off the hair that remained after the
               monastic tonsure, leaving him bald.</note>
                <note xml:id="n34" target="#a34" n="34">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 104, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ms om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n35" target="#a35" n="35">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 105, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n36" target="#a36" n="36">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 105, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>What was the use of the irons? If it is meant that they were still on him,
               the statement is inconsistent with what precedes.</note>
                <note xml:id="n37" target="#a37" n="37">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 106, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n38" target="#a38" n="38">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 108, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Perh. our Sergius should be identified with 'S. who has now rebuilt (Zach.
               Rh., VIII,5).</note>
                <note xml:id="n39" target="#a39" n="39">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 108, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>is not elsewhere found in this sense.</note>
                <note xml:id="n40" target="#a40" n="40">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 108, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 94, n.</note>
                <note xml:id="n41" target="#a41" n="41">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 110, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Rom. XII,2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n42" target="#a42" n="42">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 110, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., V,14,16.</note>
                <note xml:id="n43" target="#a43" n="43">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 111, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
