<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/798">Paul the Mourner</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/797"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/799"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/798.xml -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-6" n="6">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-6">
               <head type="main">Next the Sixth History, of the Great Man of God <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1980">Paul</persName> The Humble
                  Anchorite,</head>
               <ab xml:id="section-6.1" n="1"> There was again a blessed man beloved of God and
                  laborious and humble and a perfect Nazirite, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1980">Paul</persName> the anchorite, who was
                  from the district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/493">Sophanene</placeName>. This man therefore, when he had been for many years
                  practising heavy and severe labours of asceticism and great abstinence, heard some
                  men saying that there was a certain large cave in the side of a certain high rock
                  on the banks of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/202">Tigris</placeName> at a place called Surtha,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> which is some distance from the cultivated land, but
                  near the road, and malignant fiends lived in it, so that men passed along that
                  road with trembling, though it <pb n="112"/>
                  <pb n="112"/>was very necessary that
                  men should pass along it, because it led into the fortress called
                  <placeName>Ziyat</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/>
                  But this blessed man, when he heard the report of that cave, reflected,
                  <quote>Because those who pass along that road are frightened, and again in
                     order that the powers of the enemy may be expelled by the name of human beings
                     and the presence of a human habitation, it is a duty to go, and to erect the
                     emblem of the cross there</quote>. </ab>
               <ab xml:id="section-6.2" n="2"> Then this blessed man, like a mighty man who mocks at the
                  feeble and sick men who wish to fight with him, confidently armed himself with the
                  power of God and confidence in him, and directed his steps to the place. And he
                  went and arrived at the cave, and near it at about half a furrow's length<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> he erected the cross; and he fetched
                  stones, and traced the plan of a small oratory and knelt there in prayer, and
                  passed the night in the place. And during the night shapes of basilisks and
                  fearful shapes of every kind (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) gathered
                  together against him;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> and, the more
                  constancy he on bis side showed, the more the gruff voices and grievous
                  exhalations increased, just as if great serpents had arrived and were coming, and
                  just as if their <pb n="113"/>
                  <pb n="113"/>breath were striking against the
                  blessed man's clothes in order to drive him away. But he was thus constant in
                  prayer all that night, and all the day, and again another night also. And next lo!
                  a sound of boulders being uprooted just above the blessed man, and they were
                  indeed uprooted and came down from the rock above, and they came, and reached him,
                  and thus they would pass by while he was kneeling at his prayer, not having power
                  to touch him. And so he passed seven days and nights in that place in such
                  conflicts. And, when these demons practised many different kinds of contrivances
                  against him in order to shake him or frighten him or drive him away, he like a
                  mighty man girt in the true breastplate of his Lord was not shaken, nor reckoned
                  their wiles and their foul shapes as anything, but also after he had, like a
                  mighty man who trusts in his Lord, after the pattern of the holy
                  <persName>David</persName>, chosen for himself the sound pebbles of prayers
                  from the river of grace, and had taken the staff of the cross, and lifted the
                  sling of heavenly trust, then he next looked upon the camp of the
                  <persName>Philistine tyrants</persName>, to pull down their prowess and to
                  scatter their camp. And so on the eighth <pb n="114"/>
                  <pb n="114"/>day he planted
                  his cross in the midst of that cave, and, hung up a bag of saints<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> at the east end of it, and knelt in
                  it to pray a prayer. And, while he was kneeling, frequent sounds of loud and
                  violent howling were suddenly heard in the cave itself, such that many thousands
                  of men if they joined together would not be able to howl so loud, so much so that
                  the blessed man used to say, <quote>If help from God had not reached me, I should
                     have gone out of my mind; so that I was indeed already dazed, and my head
                     became dizzy, and my ears rang from the violence of that sound. And thus I
                     remained constant in trust on God; and at last I heard a voice outside the
                     door, saying, <quote>Alack! the cross has laid us low; otherwise you with the
                        dirty hood would not have laughed at us; and it is not you who would have
                        ejected us from our place, and come in and settled in it yourself.</quote>
                     Then, when I saw that they had gone outside the mouth of the cave and were
                     crying to me from outside, I rejoiced; and I also was strengthened, and I said
                     to them: <quote>I also am contending with you and expelling you by the cross
                        itself, not by my own strength</quote>. And from that time I remained
                     settled in the cave, while they used to display before me foul visions and many
                     fearful shapes strange to the sight <pb n="115"/>
                     <pb n="115"/>of men, and
                     thereupon they would hold speech with me as men, and further they would even
                     take the shapes of men, and would come and pretend to entreat me to come out
                     and go with them to their houses, for the purpose (as they said) of visiting
                     their sick. And again they would often come and cry <quote>Flee, flee. Lo! the
                        land is full of <persName>Huns</persName>
                     </quote>. And
                     <persName>Huns</persName> appeared to me in various fearful shapes, riding
                     on horses and with swords drawn and flashing. And lo! they came up to the gate
                     crying in barbaric language, and in an excited state, and with arrows fitted to
                     their bows. And I on my part would say to them, <quote>This is my grave, and my
                        place for ever. Until the coming of <persName>Christ</persName> in his
                        glory, and the resurrection from the abode of the dead this is my place. I
                        do not care; and, if you are in truth barbarians and you have received power
                        to kill, I do not fear death; and, if you are fiends and can kill me or take
                        me away and eject me from this place, lo! I am before you; but my own will
                        shall not be your assistant and eject me hence; and not only in my life but
                        not even in my death</quote>. While I was saying these words, all the hosts
                     of the <persName>Huns</persName> would cry and go up upon these rocks thus:
                     <quote>Henceforth the cross has protected this man against us. This man has
                        con<pb n="116"/>
                        <pb n="116"/>quered</quote>.</quote>. These things the
                  holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1980">Paul</persName> used to repeat
                  to me, because many times when I went to him I used to inquire of him, <quote>How,
                     father, did you carry on the conflict with the strange powers who haunted this
                     place and overcome them?</quote> But he, in order to expel and repress pride,
                  would say to me: <quote>We, my son, should not have overcome nor should we be
                     victorious, unless the cross had overcome. And, as we see, if we have
                     understanding, that the hosts of Satan have been expelled and hurled down by
                     the same cross not only from one small and insignificant place like this, but
                     also from all quarters, in that it has deprived them of the worship paid to
                     them, and caused their worshippers to turn to the cross, and closed their
                     mouths, and whelmed them in the lowest abysses, so also from this place too
                     these malignant spirits have been expelled by the power of the cross, and it
                     has strengthened me for its glory</quote>. These few words he himself would
                  repeat to me. But at last, when his fame had been spread about, many men used to
                  resort to him, and he also gained about <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3657">ten disciples</persName> there, while even
                  still the sights that were seen in the place were fearful, and, when men came to
                  him, whether to reside or to stay for a time, he would arm them beforehand,
                  saying: <quote>If so be you see anything or hear any sound whatsoever, <pb n="117"/>
                     <pb n="117"/>be not agitated, but make the sign of the cross upon you and
                     be silent; and, even if I myself call you or anyone else, do not come
                     out</quote> (because the fiends often deceived men there). And again to those
                  who came to him to receive instruction from him he would say the same words and he
                  would caution them, since at night they slept inside, and he outside by the gate;
                  because fiends used to appear in his likeness, and used to terrify the brother,
                  and entice him out; because under the cave there was a great hole. And so the
                  blessed man used to lie awake to guard the place in which he lived, from the time
                  when he directed his steps to that cave, and he made an altar and set it up in it,
                  and he made it a chapel. And thenceforth the brotherhood used to sleep confidently
                  in it; and his monastery extended to twenty men. And so all the men of that
                  district used to run to receive the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1980">Paul</persName>'s blessing, and to gain
                  the privilege of seeing him, and to hear his gentle words;. for God gave also into
                  his hand a great gift of healing. But his asceticism and his labours and his
                  humility no man can succeed in describing;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> since he was so humble and retiring that, if a man were to sit with him
                  and converse for three days, he would not raise his face (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>) nor <pb n="118"/>
                  <pb n="118"/>would men see the inside of
                  his eye, but he would thus converse with emotion with his head bent and his looks
                  fixed downwards. When he had been in that cave for a space of about twenty-five
                  years, and a monastery had been built, and the brotherhood had reached the number
                  of thirty men, the blessed man finished his course<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/>, and departed from the body; and he was buried on the
                  spot in accordance with his promise. And, on account of his love toward God and
                  his humility, even after his death miracles were everywhere wrought through his
                  holy bones, men taking his skull and going round the districts, and, wheresoever
                  locusts came, or hail or a scorching wind or bubonic plague, and his right hand or
                  his head went, God would straightway make deliverance. By his prayers, with those
                  of all the saints, may all we sinners have mercy in the day of judgment. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-6">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-6.1" n="3"> The history of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1980">Paul</persName> the blessed and holy
                  anchorite is ended. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 111, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sc.<hi rend="singleQuotes">the image</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 112, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>See Amm. Marcell., XIX, VI, 1, and <hi rend="singleQuotes">Dion.</hi> ap Nau
               in Rev. de l'Or. II o. 61.It seems to have lain between the Tigris and the Zab
               (Dyakonov, p. 46, n. 110)</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 112, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Circ. 50 yards - 43 metres.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 112, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>Perh. stalactites. Dyakanov (p. 39, n. 236) quotes an interesting parallel
               from Taylor's <title>Travels in Kurdistan</title> (<title>Journal of the R. Geogr.
                  Soc.</title>, XXXV, p 42). But, if so, it must have happened after he entered the
               cave.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 114, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sc. relics (v. D, and L.)</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 117, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">comprehend and describe</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 118, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>II Tim., IV, 7.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
