<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/799">Abraham the Recluse</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/798"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/800"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/799.xml -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-7" n="7">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-7">
               <head type="main">Next the Seventh History of the Old Man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1555">Abraham</persName> the Layman, the
                  Recluse.</head>
               <ab xml:id="section-7.1" n="1"> We wish next to place on record the history of the old
                  man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1555">Abraham</persName> also, <pb n="119"/>
                  <pb n="119"/>who was called <hi rend="singleQuotes">the
                     consecrated</hi>, and had reached old age being about sixty years old. This man
                  one day, when the gospel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έυαγγέλιον</foreign>) was being
                  read, heard that our Lord said, <quote>Whoever shall leave wife or children etc.
                     for my sake and for the sake of my preaching shall receive thirty fold and
                     sixtyfold and an hundredfold in this age, and in the future age shall inherit
                     eternal life</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> and again
                  <quote>Whoever doth not take up his cross and follow me is not worthy of
                     me</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> When this old man
                  heard these words, sorrow entered into his mind, and he thought within himself,
                  and said: <quote>Wherefore am I for my part alive and called a Christian, if I do
                     not do now that God's will? If it is pleasing to God that I should leave wife
                     and children, even my days have been completed and the sentence has reached me
                     that I shall leave them against my will, why do I not that which God wishes?
                     What have I gained either from children or from wife, or from the whole world,
                     except that I have consumed my life in it in vanity, and idly wasted my
                     moments, and passed my days evilly?, and lo! I have come to the gate of the
                     grave. Who will shelter me there in that judgment? or who will rescue <pb n="120"/>
                     <pb n="120"/>me from my sins? But now even for this little
                     remainder of my life that remains to me I will go and repent of my sins, and
                     then I will die, having hope in that parable of the labourers which our Lord
                     spake, that, even after the day had declined and one hour only was left for
                     those who came, they were thought worthy to receive the pay with the first.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> So I too also hope that God will
                     not shut the door of his mercy in the face of my repentance</quote>. And
                  thereafter the old man would think, <quote>What shall I do? If I go to a
                     monastery, I cannot work; and they will say, <quote>This old man has come upon
                        us in order to get a present out of us</quote>
                  </quote>. Then the old man
                  left everything, and went to a certain monastery and said to them, weeping:
                  <quote>Rise make the prayer for me, and give me the tonsure, and take the hair
                     of my secular life from me, since I desire to repent for a short time for my
                     sins before I die</quote>. But the blessed men did not frustrate his wish and
                  stand in his way, when they heard the announcement of repentance from him, but
                  they encouraged him and they say to him: <quote>You are doing right, our father,
                     if you are turning in repentance toward God; since he is merciful and will
                     receive you</quote>. After they had held much conversation with him, because
                  they supposed that he intended to live with <pb n="121"/>
                  <pb n="121"/>them, they
                  said to him: <quote>After you are tonsured, where do you intend to live?</quote>
                  But he said to them: <quote>Rise give me the blessing and take my hair, and where
                     God wishes I will live</quote>. They say to him: <quote>We seek to learn
                        whether you intend to remain with us or elsewhere; and then, if you remain with
                        us, we will ourselves give you the tonsure, and, if elsewhere, why will you be
                        tonsured away from the place where you are going to live?</quote> The old man
                  said to them: <quote>I came to you that you might make the prayer for me and give
                     me the blessing and the tonsure, not that you might argue with me. If you are
                     willing, well; and, if not, pray for me.</quote> The blessed men, when they saw
                  the old man's own intention and purpose, made the prayer and gave him the tonsure,
                  and he rose and left the place, and he directed his steps to a certain oratory at
                  the boundary of his village, which had been formerly built and roofed and in which
                  a man had lived; and he went in and repaired it and closed its doors, and took up
                  his abode in it, after requesting a man to bring him his little food every first
                  day of the week. And so he would stand and recite a service and pray constantly
                  and weep, while everyone was struck with astonishment at him, and some mockers
                  would <pb n="122"/>
                  <pb n="122"/>say, <quote>Come let us go and be blessed by
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1555">Abraham</persName> the
                     consecrated recluse</quote>, and others, uttering words that came from the evil
                  one, would say, <quote>If he had shut up his wife with him, he would be doing
                     rightly</quote>. But the old man despised everything and set one object only
                  before his eyes, since he would ask repentance for his sins and healing from the
                  merciful Physician, not ceasing from prayer and recitation of service, either by
                  night or by day. And his service was as follows: <quote>Glory to the Father and to
                     the Son and to the Holy Spirit Halleluyah!</quote>; and again as follows:
                  <quote>and from eternity to eternity Amen and Amen! Halleluyah!</quote> And
                  thus he spent the hours of the night and of the day in these words of praise with
                  prayer and supplication and thanksgiving, while he gave orders that none of his
                  kin (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) should appear in his presence; and
                  before the first day of the week he did not speak to anyone, but wept continuously
                  for his sins; and so men used to go by stealth, and listen to the sound of his
                  sobs, and they were astonished at him. And the old man persevered in his
                  repentance for eight years. And in the eighth year, when he was near his end,
                  there used to be hail in these villages <pb n="123"/>
                  <pb n="123"/>every year<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> and they were smitten, and their
                  crops also were utterly ruined. And, when the time arrived and that terrible cloud
                  had come up according to its custom, on the first day of the week, when some
                  persons were present at his lodging, they began to weep, because the cloud was
                  terrible and very trick, and something like fire was blazing and roaring within
                  it, and it came and settled over the boundaries of that village, after the fire
                  had burnt up all those round it. But the old man looked out from the window and
                  saw it; and he turned his eyes toward heaven, and said: <quote>My Lord, if thou
                     hast been pleased with the sinner's repentance, and thy mercy has declared of
                     me that I shall not perish, let not this cloud come within the boundaries of
                     this village</quote>. Then that cloud took in the middle of it as it were the
                  likeness of serene air (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άήρ</foreign>) inside all that
                  darkness; and, while it all divided this way and that, and passed by the
                  boundaries of that village, the signal of light remained until that cloud had
                  passed. And so through the power of the old man's prayers that village was
                  delivered and escape from that terrible rod of chastisement, which injured not one
                  leaf within its boundaries; and, <pb n="124"/>
                  <pb n="124"/>outside all its
                  boundaries all round, not even the leaves remained upon the trees.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> Then the boundaries of that village
                  exulted, while they themselves made proclamation concerning the power of the
                  prayers of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1555">Abraham</persName>, everyone being astonished and giving thanks to God. And
                  the old man also rejoiced, and he gives thanks to God who had shown him that he
                  accepted his repentance. And, at the end of the eighth year, he departed from the
                  world in the good ending of repentance. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-7">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-7.1" n="2"> The history of the old man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1555">Abraham</persName> the layman, the
                  recluse, is ended. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 119, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Mark, X, 29, 30 (a loose citation).</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 119, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Matth., X, 38.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 120, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Matth., XX, 9-16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 123, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sic syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 124, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Cf. p. 12, where a similar story is told.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
