<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/800">Addai the Chorepiscopus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/799"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/801"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/800.xml -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-8" n="8">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-8">
                    <head type="main">Next the Eighth History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1116">Addai</persName> the
                     <foreign>Chorepiscopus</foreign>
                    </head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-8.1" n="1"> It is patent to everyone that salt does not itself need a
                  condiment, because by its own nature it is a condiment, and, to put it
                  differently, not a condiment only, but salted by its nature; and accordingly it
                  does not need itself or make use of itself, but all other insipid ſoods need to
                  use it as a condiment. But so also fair sketches which show the admirable form of
                  the likenesses of the saints are not adapted for repetition to them, nor do they
                  themselves need <pb n="125"/>
                        <pb n="125"/>these, but for us ourselves who are more
                  insipid than food<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> the condiment of
                  the stories of the saints is required. This blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1116">Addai</persName> then was
                     <foreign>chorepiscopus</foreign> in a monastery in a village called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2776">Fardaisa</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> at the approach to the Armenian frontier in the
                  district called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Anzetene</placeName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> and he
                  had fittingly wielded the authority of the chorepiscopate for a considerable time
                  with all religious conduct without blame, visiting the poor, and caring for the
                  orphans, and providing for the widows, and admonishing the clerical staff in the
                  churches and the monastic convents, going about and warning and teaching each man
                  to devote himself sincerely to his ministry without stain in the sight of men,
                  while his words to every man were always these: <quote>My sons, let us not despise
                     the expressions of the great and divine <persName>Paul</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> Let us hear from him that he
                     cries to us as with a trumpet and says, <quote>My children, it is the last
                        time. And from this we understand that it is the last time, from the false
                           <persName>Christs</persName> who have come in among us</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> and again he says, <quote>The end
                        of all things hath come near</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> and again, <quote>The end of the times hath come near upon
                        us</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> And for this
                     reason, as men who read these things and meditate upon them always, let us
                     conduct ourselves in the time of our <pb n="126"/>
                            <pb n="126"/>sojourning with
                        fear;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> because <quote>the day
                        of the Lord so cometh as a thief in the night</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/>, and the day of vengeance has come near<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> and the day of requital that
                     requites every man according to his deeds<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> is at hand; and for this reason <quote>wake
                        yourselves righteously, and sin not</quote>
                            <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> Keep the purity of your persons and of your souls,
                     as well as that of your bodies; and wake and devote yourselves to the service
                     of him who called you and by his grace brought you to his holy order, and
                     appointed you to praise him, because he will cause you to live at his coming;
                     not because he himself needs our praise, but this is the will of his gracious
                     mercy, through the praise of him to give glory to us</quote>. When therefore
                  the rest of this blessed man's days he had<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> spent in such warnings and in such earnest care toward every man,
                  suddenly the smoke of the heretical persecution that had been exhaled over the
                  whole empire reached him, and those who had been made fervent labourers for the
                  impiety of the synod of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/622">Chalcedon</placeName> directed their steps to him as a chief and leader and
                  man of eminence, requiring him to go to the man who held the authority in his
                     metropolis,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> and make concord
                  with him, and accept communion in his apostasy; and, if on the other hand he did
                  not do so, to be <pb n="127"/>
                        <pb n="127"/>driven into exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>). But the saint on hearing these things
                  rejoiced; and he answered them, saying: <quote>Who then (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρα</foreign>) is there, pray, who will not take upon himself as you
                     suppose (everyone who has sense in him) exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>) with <persName>Christ</persName>? Now that
                        <persName>Christ</persName> is being driven into exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>) by you, would that we also may be banished
                     by you rather than by becoming renegades with you be banished by him</quote>.
                  When therefore the men who had been sent to him heard these things from him, they
                  went on uttering great menaces against him in great wrath, threatening and saying,
                     <quote>Prepare yourself to meet a fate that is in accord with your assertion;
                     since you shall not live here longer, unless you make concord and signify
                     acceptance according to the king's order</quote>. But he, when he heard these
                  words, laughed at them, and said: <quote>If, pray, there had liappened to be a
                     king who ordered me to sacrifice like the holy martyrs, would you on account of
                     his order have urged me to obey him because he was king, and sacrifice to
                     idols?</quote> Then the blessed man arose before them and gathered the inmates
                  of his convent together, and spoke many words with them, saying, <quote>Let every
                     man beware</quote>. And he took his staff and went out, saying: <quote>Think
                     not to yourselves that, if I possessed the whole world, it would be more to me
                        <pb n="128"/>
                            <pb n="128"/>than the true faith in
                     <persName>Christ</persName>. Lo! I have not taken even bread for the day now
                     that I am expelled from all this course of life in which I have run and
                     laboured and gathered<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> from my
                     youth. It is better for me to die than that anyone should make my boast in our
                     Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> vain<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/>
                        </quote>. And so he departed and went up to the
                  rugged towering mountains that are in the east of that district, in which nothing
                  except great beasts is to be found on account of their inaccessibility; and he was
                  there for a considerable time supporting himself on roots, and passing the nights
                  in caves, and going about and praying, and weeping for the sheep of
                     <persName>Christ</persName>'s innocent flock, how they had fallen into the
                  hands of malignant apostate wolves. And, after a considerable time, the blessed
                  man was seen by certain men, and news of him was heard; and the inmates of his
                  monastery also sought for him carefully, and they discovered him; and he learned
                  from them what had happened; because, after those who were conducting the
                  persecution had seen that he himself had departed, they did not trouble themselves
                  much about his monastery, but took all the plunder that they could from it, and
                  left it. And, when he learned these things, he continued enjoining them to provide
                  for the poor and the orphans and the widow's out of the remnant that had been left
                  to them. But he, on account of the ruggedness of the mountains and <pb n="129"/>
                        <pb n="129"/>the unbounded amount of snow that covered them, went down to the
                  neighbourhood of a certain hamlet that was situated among these same mountains,
                  and made a cell for himself, and there he used to pass the winter. But after five
                  years during which he had lived in this manner, busying himself about providing
                  for the poor, his monastery was brought to indigence; and, when he knew that it
                  had been plundered more than ten times, and no longer contained provision for the
                  needy as before, and the blessed man was grieved and distressed on account of the
                  starving and distressed persons for whom there was no method of providing, and
                  further the inmates of his monastery also were pressed by want, then he considered
                     <quote>There is no longer any quarter from which it is possible for me to
                     provide for my brethren, except that the blessed men should come and make a
                     vineyard in these mountains, and it will be a provision for them and for the
                     needy</quote>. And this he did not delay to carry out; but when they came to
                  him he spoke to them, and this suggestion pleased them. And they brought men and
                  dug; and there in the first year they put in about twenty thousand,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> and a like number also in the
                  second, and the third; and the vineyard reached a great size on the mountains. And
                  the news went out everywhere <quote>Such-and-such a monastery has covered the
                     mountains with vineyards</quote>; and hence within five or six years so much
                  wine was produced that they could not find vessels <pb n="130"/>
                        <pb n="130"/>to
                  contain it. And, since the region of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2763">Cappadocia</placeName> was close at hand,
                  and these men<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/> used to go out as far
                  as Syria and buy wine, they became aware of the place that was close to them, and
                  from that time it became their habit to go out thither in companies and buy; and
                  thenceforth the anxieties of the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1116">Addai</persName> that had been troubling
                  him because he had nothing in his possession wherewith to provide for the poor
                  were much relieved, since he would send from forty and fifty
                     <foreign>denarii</foreign>, and as many as came in from<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/> that vineyard, and buy clothes and distribute them to
                  the needy, and similarly also corn and oil, and many articles; so that, except
                  what was needed for the cultivation of the vineyard itself, he left nothing
                  whatever that he did not liberally bestow upon the distressed persons. And thus he
                  completed twenty-five years in this occupation, while he did not go into the
                  cultivated territory or neglect this business, nor did men see him casually, but
                  he would carry his staff the whole day, and go about among the gullies and ravines
                  and among the trees, and would kneel and pray and weep, taking care that no one
                  should pass behind him and surprise him; and so at evening-time he would betake
                  himself to a certain place that he had secretly <pb n="131"/>
                        <pb n="131"/>made,
                  and the man who attended him would meet him, and inform him in case anyone had
                  come out to look for him. And thus he would do even in snow and frost, in order
                  that he might not be seen by men; but he had given orders that everyone who came
                  should be received and refreshed and go; so that in fact on one and two occasions
                  I went up to these mountains to see the blessed man, and I did not see him with
                  his consent. But on one occasion, because I knew the hour of his arrival, I took
                  one of the brethren with me, and at eventide we betook ourselves to that place;
                  and, as there was a thicket of many trees there, I said to the brother who was
                  with me: <quote>Let us sit down among these trees, and lie in wait for the old
                     man; since perhaps he will come and we shall catch him, and obtain his
                     blessing</quote>. And, while we on our part were sitting down, lo! there comes
                  the sound of his feet and of his breath as he was coming down from the mountain;
                  and, when we saw him in the distance, we kept ourselves hidden all the more, lest
                  he should see us and turn back; as in fact happened. When he had approached to
                  about half a furrow's length<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/> from
                  us, though neither the sight of us nor the perception of our presence reached him,
                  as if he scented the smell of us, he checked himself and halted, waiting a long
                  time, while we on our side did not stand up and were not seen by him; and, as if
                  he had become <pb n="132"/>
                        <pb n="132"/>aware of us in his spirit, he thereupon
                  like a wild beast turned aside, and set his face to go down the mountain-side at a
                  run. When I saw that the old man was running, I cried out: <quote>Forgive us,
                     father, and pray for us</quote>. And, in order not to vex and annoy him, we did
                  not pursue after him; and so we went in and passed the night, and we did not
                  obtain a sight of the saint. But again, inasmuch as my mind was ardently bent on
                  running and labouring after the good and precious merchandise of the old man's
                  blessing at all costs, even so I was not remiss in the matter, but also after a
                  time again I directed my steps to these mountains, having determined, <quote>If I
                     am here as much as two months, I will not depart from these mountains until I
                     am blessed by the bondman of God</quote>, entreating our Lord to grant me this
                  gift. And at noontide in the middle of the day we saw the old man passing over a
                  certain clear space some distance off, and coming down from peak to peak, because
                  there was a gap between; and we kept ourselves close lest he should see us and run
                  away. And, because intense noonday heat prevailed, he stood and prayed, and next
                  he knelt down, and he stood up and stretched out his hands to heaven, expanding
                  himself in the form of a cross; and he continued for a long time until about the
                  ninth hour,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a21" target="#n21" n="21"/> and then he sat down
                     <pb n="133"/>
                        <pb n="133"/>to rest for a short time. But we, when we saw that he
                  had sat down to rest, came down by a certain deep gully, and went on until we
                  arrived opposite the blessed man; and thus we suddenly came up and caught him. But
                  when he saw us he was thunderstruck, as a man is frightened by the sudden sight of
                  some lion; and, after he had looked this way and that and seen that there was no
                  escape, he stood up and received us, and made a prayer. And he stood and asked,
                  saying, <quote>Whence have you come hither, blessed men, on this mountain?</quote>
                  We continued entreating him to sit down for a little time; but he did not consent
                  to sit down, in order that he might not be involved in a long conversation with
                  human beings; but he continued saying to us, a <quote>Go to the monastery and rest
                     there, and lo! I will myself come at once</quote>. And, after we had begun many
                  sentences, he continued urging this upon us, to go to the monastery, in order (as
                  he professed) to rest, which was only that he might escape from us. But I,
                  inasmuch as I divined his purpose, said to him: <quote>Why, our father, do you run
                     away from us? Sit down and speak, and console us with your aſſectionate
                        words,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a22" target="#n22" n="22"/> and sow good seed in
                     our ears, even if<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a23" target="#n23" n="23"/> our own soil
                     is ungrateful, and barren and unculti<pb n="134"/>
                            <pb n="134"/>vated</quote>.
                  But he looked at me, and said: <quote>Do we then (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρα</foreign>), pray, seek another greater than <persName>Jesus</persName>
                     to speak with us or to admonish us? and, if we do not obey him, if a man rise
                     from the dead and speak, how shall we obey him?<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a24" target="#n24" n="24"/> Now go and rest, and I will come, and we will
                     talk</quote>. But I inasmuch as I knew his purpose reflected that on account of
                  the blessed man's pleasure we had been afraid of annoying him; and so we fell down
                  before him and entreated him to bless us and to endow us with his holy prayers.
                  But he when he dismissed us said to us: <quote>Do you pray for me the ungrateful.
                     As for yourselves your earnestness signifies the direction of your will, that
                     God may mingle his will with your will, and make your will his will. Pray for
                     me</quote>. And thus we parted, and we did not see the blessed man again; but
                  sufficient for our consolation and for thanksgiving to God to be ever rendered by
                  us was this one occasion on which we were not deprived of the benefit of the sight
                  of this divine man. After a period of twenty-five years, while spending his time
                  in this way, he ended this life of troubles, and departed to the rest of his Lord,
                  having committed the place of provision for the needy to the inmates of his
                  convent, and enjoined <pb n="135"/>
                        <pb n="135"/>them to make provision from it for
                  the needy, as during his life, for ever. </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-8">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-8.1" n="2">The history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1116">Addai</persName> the
                  <foreign>chorepiscopus</foreign> is ended.</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 125, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Or
                  <hi rend="singleQuotes">insipid of taste</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 125, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sc.
                  <hi rend="singleQuotes">paradise</hi>
                </note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 125, n.
               3</orig>
                    </choice>Syr. <hi rend="singleQuotes">Ilanzit</hi>
                </note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 125, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Sic
               syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 125, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>I
               John, II, 18 (loose citation)</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 125, n. 6</orig>
                    </choice>I
               Pet., IV, 7.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 125, n. 7</orig>
                    </choice>I
               Cor., X, 11 (?).</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 126, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I
               Pet., I, 17.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 126, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>I
               Thess., V, 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 126, n.
               3</orig>
                    </choice>Is., LXIII, 4 (?).</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 126, n.
               4</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., XVI, 27.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 126, n.
               5</orig>
                    </choice>I Cor., XV, 34.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 126, n.
               6</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 126, n.
               7</orig>
                    </choice>Abraham of Amida.</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 128, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Spiritual profit?</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 128, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>II Cor., IX, 3.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 129, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. vines.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 130, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. the Cappadocians.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 130, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 131, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 112, n. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n21" target="#a21" n="21">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 132, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>This must appy. be 3 P.M., but in other places the hours seem to be
               reckoned from midnight and noon; see p. note on ch. 13.</note>
                <note xml:id="n22" target="#a22" n="22">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 133, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Or take as a title, and render <hi rend="singleQuotes">the words of
                  your afflection</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n23" target="#a23" n="23">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 133, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n24" target="#a24" n="24">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 134, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Luke, XVI, 31.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
