<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/802">Simeon the bishop</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/801"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/803"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/802.xml -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-10" n="10">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-10">
                    <head type="main">Next the Tenth History, of the Brave Warrior on Behalf of The True Faith, Mar
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> the Bishop,
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">the Persian
                  Debater</persName>.</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-10.1" n="1"> When I approach the task of relating the history of this
                  holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> the bishop, I
                  do not do this in simplicity and without fear; because his character does not
                  shine out in one beauty of righteousness only, that one might presume to depict
                  his virtue as one portrait, but in many beauties, the objectsm of great and
                  inexpressible amazement, be they labours of righteousness, or humility exceeding
                  the standard of those who live in these times, or zeal on
                     <persName>Christ</persName>'s behalf, or the war which all his life until death
                  he carried on against the fraudulent disciples of the school of Nestorius, or
                  again his labour in all <pb n="138"/>
                        <pb n="138"/>countries in which the preaching
                  of <persName>Christ</persName> had travelled; for whom, I think, it would not have
                  been improper to speak with boldness (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>)
                  like the holy <persName>Paul</persName> and say: <quote>I have toiled more than
                     all</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> and to say further
                  this also, that he had travelled not only from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/104">Jerusalem</placeName> and as far as
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2797">Illyricum</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> but also in all countries in which
                  the preaching of <persName>Christ</persName> had travelled, except only the
                  territories of <placeName>Rome</placeName>; and thither also he was ready and had
                  started to go, when God saw his venerable character and his old age and his
                  labour, and ordered him to finish his course in the royal city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/586">Constantinople</placeName>. This holy
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> then even before
                  the period of his episcopacy, besides the fervent zeal and enthusiasm for the true
                  faith unto death which he possessed, was deeply versed in the Scriptures, and he
                  was also ardent in practising debate, beyond (in my opinion) any other man, even
                  the ancient fathers; because besides the gift of God this other fact too summoned
                  him to it, because he was also a <persName>Persian</persName>, and he lived in
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/526">Persia</placeName>, and it is in
                  that country especially that the teaching of the school of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/780">Theodore</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/655">Nestorius</persName> is very wide-spread,
                  so that believing bishops and their dioceses are few there, and further besides
                  this teaching that of the school of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/608">Mani</persName> and <pb n="139"/>
                        <pb n="139"/>
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/616">Marcion</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3">Bar Daisan</persName> also had from this
                  cause been much disseminated there, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/608">Mani</persName> travelled much there in the
                  same country, and there also they flayed him alive, and he died there; and
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3">Bar Daisan</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/616">Marcion</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> because there was once a school (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχολή</foreign>) of <persName>Persians</persName> at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2605">Edessa</placeName>, and the
                     <persName>Persians</persName> are in general keen inquirers, they were trained
                  in the tenets of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3">Bar Daisan</persName>
                  and of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/616">Marcion</persName> and became
                  immersed in them; and they carried this evil plant down and planted it in that
                  country; even as <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/534">Hibam</persName>
                  the blasphemer who was once ruler there (of the church of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2605">Edessa</placeName>) made himself a promoter
                  of that same school (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχολή</foreign>); because this man
                  not only blasphemed like Nestorius, but even surpassed him in wickedness. Whendai
                  this bitter plant was spreading in the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2605">Edessa</placeName>, the holy bishop
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2253">Cyrus</persName> discovered it,
                  and tore it out from its roots, and did not allow the school (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχολή</foreign>) of the <persName>Persians</persName> to be
                  mentioned there again, as had been the case before;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> and this school was from that time established in the
                  city of Nisibis, from which all that country drink dregs of gall, so that even in
                  this our country, the country of the <persName>Romans</persName>, some men taste
                  of it.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> Against these therefore the
                  blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> was always
                  strongly armed <pb n="140"/>
                        <pb n="140"/>and ceaselessly contending; and wherever
                  he came victory was given him by God, and he was made a closer of the mouth to all
                  heretics (<foreign xml:lang="grc">αίρεσιώται</foreign>), until their chiefs or
                  doctors dreaded to open their mouth and speak in a district in which his presence
                  had been reported; because in a district in which a debate was being originated by
                  the Nestorians against the believers who were in it, if he were five or ten days'
                  journey (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μανσίων</foreign>) away, as if God had made him
                  ready and as if the earth had vomited him up, he would suddenly spring up and be
                  present there,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> since from the
                  greatness of his zeal and the fervour of his will he did not rest and sit still in
                  one district, saying, <quote>I must not sit still and rest, when I know that
                        <persName>Christ</persName>'s sheep are being scattered among ravening and
                     destructive wolves, who will not spare to destroy them and tear them in
                        pieces<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/>
                        </quote>. And for this
                  reason he was sedulous in going out among the countries, as far as <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2792">the camp<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> of the Saracens</placeName> of the tribe of Nuʿman,
                  which he often visited; so that he gained a large number of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2792">Saracens</placeName> in it, and he induced
                  the magnates who were converted by his words to build a Christian church in it.
                  And again he would depart and go down to the very gate of the kingdom,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> and <pb n="141"/>
                        <pb n="141"/>would
                  turn many to God not only among the heretics (<foreign xml:lang="grc">αίρεσιώται</foreign>!), but also among the <persName>Magians</persName>; so
                  that he once even converted <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3618">three
                     great and distinguished men among the Magians</persName> and baptized them.
                  And, when their companions heard that they had turned away from Magism and become
                  Christians, they informed the king about them; and they received an order that, if
                  they had really turned away and would not deny Christianity, they should die. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-10.2" n="2"> But these men, who showed themselves worthy of a crown of
                  life, when they saw the threat and the king's sword, were not afraid nor dismayed,
                  while the blessed man also armed them with the enthusiasm of martyrdom for the
                  sake of eternal life, and they resisted the order and the sword that had gone out
                  against them; and they say, <quote>Far be it from us to deny the living God who
                     made heaven and earth, and his Son the Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>,
                     who called us and brought us near to him by his grace, that we should deny him
                     again and worship instead of him the things that he created</quote>. Then ten
                  days after their spiritual birth these blessed men departed to God by the quick
                  death of the sword, bearing good testimony. But this blessed man continued to go
                  out among the countries without ceasing, and to warn and make disciples and
                  convert. And accordingly his fame went out over the whole land, and not only that
                  of the <persName>Persians</persName> but that of the <persName>Romans</persName>
                  also; <pb n="142"/>
                        <pb n="142"/>and he extended his travels to the royal city of
                  the <persName>Romans</persName> for the first time for a reason like this. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-10.3" n="3"> On one occasion <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3619">the Nestorian bishops</persName> of the
                  chief cities met together and gave information to the king of the
                     <persName>Persians</persName> about the believers in that country, saying,
                     <quote>These men are traitors to your majesty, as it is in your power to learn,
                     since their faith also and their rites agree with those of the
                        <persName>Romans</persName>
                        </quote>; and the <persName>Magian</persName>
                  believed them, and he ordered a persecution against the orthodox (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθόδοξοι</foreign>) in the whole of his kingdom. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-10.4" n="4"> But the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> in the fervour of his zeal
                  formed the plan of going up and informing the believing <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2265">Anastasius</persName>, king of the
                     <persName>Romans</persName>, of these things, that he might do this favour to
                  the church of the believers in the country of the <persName>Persians</persName>,
                  saying, <quote>Who will be able to intercede with the king for us if I do not do
                     these things? and that believing king will ask of him peace for the believers
                     in the country of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/526">Persia</placeName>
                        </quote>. Then he quickly arrived before king <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2265">Anastasius</persName>, and informed him of
                  these things. And this God-loving king, because he was a believer and a friend of
                  the believers, did not delay to carry out his request which he asked of him; and,
                  because there was peace between them, and they were sending embassies to one <pb n="143"/>
                        <pb n="143"/>another,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/>
                  and royal presents and gifts, king <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2265">Anastasius</persName> then wrote earnestly to the
                  <persName>Persian</persName>, saying: <quote>You will do well if you order that
                     peace shall reign in your empire in your days; and in this matter you will
                     gratify and please us, if your order keeps the Christian peoples in your empire
                     unmolested, when you order that they shall not harm one another by reason of
                     occasions of enmity, nor any of your people molest them</quote>. These words
                  then that are in the king's letter together with others we have found that the
                  holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> himself asked
                  from him, and he gave him a copy (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ίσον</foreign>) of
                     them.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/>
                    </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-10.5" n="5"> And, when the envoy came down, he presented the request
                  of the believing <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2265">Anastasius</persName> to the king; and he consented and gave orders that none
                  of the Christians should hurt his neighbour; and thenceforth the machinations of
                  the heretics were rendered of no effect, and the party of the believers enjoyed
                  freedom (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>). And the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> was more incited against
                  the heretics, and was warmed with zeal for debating against their leaders <pb n="144"/>
                        <pb n="144"/>and doctors, insomuch that, wherever they asked him to
                  debate, he would debate with them before an audience and would set up umpires to
                  hear the discussion between them, and so he would debate and would refute them and
                  put them to shame, so that on no single occasion was he defeated by them in
                  debate. And therefore, if it happened that one of their bishops wished to
                  originate a debate with any of the believers, he would first inquire<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> from travellers, or from anyone who
                  came in his way where <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> was, and then would speak, saying, <quote>Inquire<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> and see as to the man whom they
                     used also to call the invincible <persName>Satan</persName>
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> the debater
                     where he is</quote>; so that once they were asking him himself,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> about him<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> because everywhere he was inflicting shame upon them,
                  defeating and refuting them, and causing even the <persName>Magians</persName> to
                  laugh at them, since he would often set up the <persName>Magians</persName>
                  themselves as judges, and thus before them as judges plead the cause of the faith,
                  and they themselves would adjudge the victory to him, and laugh at these men. And
                  therefore many were threatening to kill him, in order to rid themselves of him;
                  and above all those who did not know him by sight and were accustomed to hear
                  about him used to threaten him; and for this reason <pb n="145"/>
                        <pb n="145"/>he
                  had left his hair and also his beard like that of a layman; because in the country
                  of the <persName>Persians</persName> they allow the beards of laymen to grow and
                  increase as much as they can; and for this reason no one knew that he was not a
                  layman, unless it were someone who was very well acquainted with him. And, when he
                  was, as he used to tell us, on the point of entering a certain city, he found some
                  clergymen (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κληρικοί</foreign>) sitting at the gate; and
                  they asked him as a stranger coming from a distance, <quote>Whence do you
                     come?</quote> And he said to them, <quote>I am a stranger</quote>. They say to
                  him: <quote>Where have you heard that that <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> the debater is?</quote>
                  And he turned round and looked at them; and, that they might not know that he was
                  the man, he on his part said: <quote>Woe for those same men</quote>, and passed
                  on, hearing them say, <quote>This man is one of ours, and he has heard him crying
                     out against us, and for this reason he cries <quote>Woe for
                  him</quote>
                        </quote>; and thus he passed on and went away, while they asked him
                  about himself, and they did not recognise him; and so the Nestorians dreaded him
                  everywhere. Once again he set out and went to visit the believers in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/219">Hirthad Nuʿman</placeName>; and the great
                     <foreign xml:lang="la">catholicus</foreign> of <persName>Arzun</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> having sent and learned that he had
                  gone to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/219">Hirtha</placeName>, sent to
                  the believing <pb n="146"/>
                        <pb n="146"/>bishops, and said to them: <quote>Assemble
                     together, and come let us debate about the faith</quote>. And the bishops on
                  hearing it were alarmed; and they write to him saying, <quote>Wait for us</quote>;
                  but he knew that they desired to send about the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName>, and he continued pressing
                  them more, thinking, <quote>Lest they send and inform him and he come, and again
                     we shall not be able to speak a word</quote>. But they on their part wrote a
                  letter and horsemen,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> and sent after
                  him. And, when he heard it, he rose promptly and took two Arab mares,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/> and quickly arrived among them. And,
                  when they saw him, they rejoiced greatly, and gave thanks to God; and they rose
                  and went to the man who had written to them, while he had no notion that <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> was in the land of the
                     <persName>Persians</persName>, but supposed that he was in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2792">Saracen territory</placeName>. The blessed
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> says to the
                  believing bishops, who were five: <quote>Lo!, as soon as the Nestorians see me,
                     they will be amazed; and, because they will not know what to say, they will end
                     by saying this, <quote>We will not permit this man to join in the discussion
                        with us, since he is a disturber</quote>. But do you say to them: <quote>If
                        you are not willing that all of us should join in the discuss<pb n="147"/>
                                <pb n="147"/>ion, then neither will we ourselves hold discussion with
                        you</quote>
                        </quote>. Then at the sight of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> these men were astounded
                  and disturbed; and they were also caught and did not know what to do. To decline
                  the debate would bring ridicule upon them, since it was they who had originated
                  the debate; and again to speak and be defeated would bring disgrace upon them. The
                  blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> again says
                  to them: <quote>If you desire to debate with us, we need umpires and an audience
                     to hear the discussion between us, lest we fall into empty talk. But let us in
                     the presence of an upright audience speak a few words that will refute and be
                     refuted</quote>. They say to him: <quote>If you want an audience, we on our
                     side will ask the king's <foreign>
                                <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3236">marzban</persName>
                            </foreign> who is
                     here</quote>. He on his side says to them: <quote>Neither will we refuse to
                     accept the <foreign>
                                <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3236">marzban</persName>
                            </foreign>'s decision</quote>. Then all together were
                  going to a <persName>Magian</persName> to argue about the faith; even as this too
                  was brought about by divine dispensation, that even through the heathen the true
                  mystery of the right faith might be proclaimed. And, when they had taken their
                  seats opposite one another and begun to discuss, the great <foreign xml:lang="la">catholicus</foreign>, whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/969">Babai</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/> inasmuch as he took precedence over all, first said:
                     <quote>My lord, we inform your high excellency that these men are the king's
                     enemies, and their faith <pb n="148"/>
                            <pb n="148"/>agrees with that of the
                        <persName>Romans</persName>, and they convey the secrets of the kingdom to
                     the <placeName>Roman dominions</placeName>
                        </quote>. But this wretched <foreign xml:lang="la">catholicus</foreign>, because he knew that if he opened his mouth
                  on the subject of the faith he would be put to shame, began to make accusation,
                  not knowing that God would put him to shame; and, because he did not know what to
                  do, had recourse to accusation. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-10.6" n="6"> But that governor as if inspired by the grace of God
                  answered him, saying: <quote>These are our affairs, not yours. If we learn that as
                     a matter of fact these things are so, we will attend to them. You on account of
                     the enmity that you have toward one another say these things to us; but we for
                     our part will not receive these statements from you</quote>. Then an expression
                  of thanks was offered to the <persName>Magian</persName> by the believers, who
                  said, <quote>Your judgment is just and upright</quote>. The governor says to the
                     <foreign xml:lang="la">catholicus</foreign>: <quote>If you have anything else
                     to say, about your faith, say on</quote>. <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/969">Babai</persName> the <foreign xml:lang="la">catholicus</foreign> says to him<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/>: <quote>My lord, as to our faith we have to speak about a certain man like us,
                     who was born from a woman as we were, and upon whom the Word<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a21" target="#n21" n="21"/> of God came down on account of
                     his uprightness and his righteousness; and, just as the king of kings might
                     find a beggar's son in a dungheap <pb n="149"/>
                            <pb n="149"/>girt with rags, and
                     give orders about him that they should raise him from the dungheap, and strip
                     the rags with which he was girt off him and clothe him in royal raiment, and
                     the king might issue an order <quote>Let everyone name this man my son</quote>,
                     and, because that poor man found grace in the king's eyes, he also conferred
                     upon him the honour of being called his son, so God was pleased to name this
                     man to whom the contention between us relates his Son by grace, when he is not
                     so by nature</quote>. And he came to an end. The governor says: <quote>What do
                     you say?</quote>
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> says: <quote>We
                     know that your wisdom will not go astray. Therefore we entreat you by the great
                     God (may he prolong your days) out of all the statements which the <foreign xml:lang="la">catholicus</foreign> has made to investigate two, and examine
                     and judge fairly</quote>. He says to him: <quote>Tell me which</quote>. He says
                  to him: <quote>Since the <foreign xml:lang="la">catholicus</foreign> stated in the
                     presence of your highness that an ordinary man like us was born of a woman, let
                     your wisdom put this question to him. Whereas we are born of a woman from the
                     seed of a man, inquire<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a22" target="#n22" n="22"/> from him
                     as to the man who he told you was born of a woman like us, was he from the seed
                     of <pb n="150"/>
                            <pb n="150"/>a man like us, or whence was he</quote>. The
                  governor says to the <foreign xml:lang="la">catholicus</foreign>: <quote>What say
                     you about these things? Was the man of whom you spoke to me from the seed of a
                     man, or whence was he?</quote> But he was struck with shame, and he could not
                  say that he came from seed. He says to him: <quote>He did not come from
                     seed</quote>. He says to him, <quote>And whence is his conception?</quote> He
                  says to him: <quote>It is written that it is from the Holy Spirit</quote>. He says
                  to them: <quote>Lo! therefore you lied when you said that he is an ordinary man
                     Lo! therefore his conception and birth are not like us, but above us; for we
                     for our part never heard that a man was born without seed. And, if in the case
                     of this man whom you accuse you have yourself on the other hand testified that
                     he was born without copulation and without seed, he is not an ordinary man like
                     us; and by your own testimony you have been condemned, and these men speak
                     truth rather than you</quote>. While the party [of] the believers were
                  proceeding to extol the governor with praises, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> says to the
                        <foreign>
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3236">marzban</persName>
                        </foreign>: <quote>My lord, let them confess one more point
                     in the presence of your wisdom, and let us dispense with lengthy
                  speech</quote>. He says to him, <quote>What?</quote>
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> says to him:
                     <quote>Since the <foreign xml:lang="la">catholicus</foreign> said to your
                     highness that the king of kings takes a poor man's son from a dung<pb n="151"/>
                            <pb n="151"/>heap and clothes him in royal raiment, and orders him to be
                     called his son, and therefore by grace everyone calls him the king's son while
                     he is not his son by nature, let your highness put the question to him:
                        <quote>Has that poor man's son (though the king takes him and names him his
                        son while he is not so according to his own very statement<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a23" target="#n23" n="23"/>) a natural father? Or whence
                        was he born?</quote> Inquire<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a24" target="#n24" n="24"/>
                     from him who is the father of the man also of whom he speaks. Has he a natural
                     father? and if not let him show in your presence whence he was born and who his
                     father is</quote>. When the <foreign xml:lang="la">catholicus</foreign>
                  received the questions put by the <foreign>
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3236">marzban</persName>
                        </foreign>, with the
                  whole assembly of his bishops, they closed their lips and hung their heads, and
                  could not utter a word; and when the judge sharply insisted on their declaring the
                  father of him of whom they were speak, they confessed that he was born from God
                  and without copulation. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-10.7" n="7"> The governor says: <quote>Therefore if God was his father
                     his son also is God. And, if again a man was his father and he came from the
                     seed of copulation like us, he himself also was a man as you said before. But
                     by the words that you have spoken you have refuted and condemned yourself; and
                     men who are fewer than you hold the true and sound logical position, and the
                     thing is as they say by your own testimony</quote> Then the believing <pb n="152"/>
                        <pb n="152"/>bishops continued giving vent to exclamations (<foreign xml:lang="grc">φωνάς</foreign>), saying, <quote>God preserve your wisdom and
                     your uprightness many years. God multiply your greatness many times, and grant
                     you a good life</quote>. And so they separated, the Nestorians having been put
                  to shame. This was also the occasion of this saint's episcopate; because they
                  often pressed him to accept ordination to the episcopate, and he would not
                  consent; but, after he had come out victorious, they seized him by force and made
                  him bishop for a place called Beth Arsham,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a25" target="#n25" n="25"/> and thereforward he bore the title of metropolitan bishop of Beth
                  Arsham . And so he would go about in the interior countries beyond the
                     <persName>Persians</persName> and make disciples, and convert men from paganism
                  and Magism, and return again to the same country, and strenuously meet those who
                  held the impious doctrine of Nestorius in the same contests; and these were again
                  inflamed with hatred against him. And some moreover of the most eminent among them
                  made cruel accusations against him and all the believers as well before <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2286">the Persian king</persName>. Then he
                  issued an order that all the believing bishops should be arrested, and all the
                  chief archimandrites, and <pb n="153"/>
                        <pb n="153"/>committed to prison at
                  Nisibis; and thus they were arrested and imprisoned in bitter confinement (as is
                  the custom of the <persName>Persians</persName> who imprison without mercy) for
                  seven years, being subjected to great distress and severe trial (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>), so that the mouth is too small for us to
                  describe that distress. And then, after their own lives had wasted away, and they
                  were all already knocking at the gate of death, from the distress and also from
                  the length of time, an account of these things was written to the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3191">king of Aethiopia</persName>; and, since
                  he also was a believer, he made this request though his <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3622">ambassadors</persName> of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2286">the Persian king</persName>, and he
                  released them from that distress. But after a time much accusation was again made
                  against them before the king by the Nestorian bishops, who said: <quote>Our people
                     hold the faith among all Christians and in all kingdoms</quote>. When the
                  blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> learned
                  these things, he came to the king's court, and strenuously contended in the
                  refutation of this falsehood. But the Magians, being much worried by them, since
                  they did not know how to judge and decide between them, issued an order in these
                  terms: <quote>Whoever of you wishes it, permission is given to him to go out <pb n="154"/>
                            <pb n="154"/>and go round among the kings of the Christian peoples,
                     and among the chief bishops and authorities, and bring us their faith and their
                     seals, that we may know which party among you speaks well and shows great
                     correctness</quote>. But this earnest blessed man, when he heard these words,
                  rejoiced with great joy; and from the ardour of his zeal, since he had thus set
                  his face to the task, the labour of going<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a26" target="#n26" n="26"/> from peoples to peoples, and from kingdoms to kingdoms was not reckoned
                  by him as anything at all, but he undertook this with joy as something light and
                  easy and of no moment.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a27" target="#n27" n="27"/> And he set
                  out at once without delay in his zeal, in order to traverse the frontiers of the
                  peoples and the kingdoms, not being hindered or frightened by fear of anything,
                  not of the great length of the intervening space, nor the dangerous character of
                  the countries on account of robbers, nor the crossings of the rivers, nor the long
                  distances to be covered, and, what is greater than all, not even the burden of his
                  old age; but thus, in confidence on God and the ardour of his burning zeal, he
                  made light of everything, and <pb n="155"/>
                        <pb n="155"/>set out and travelled in
                  all countries in which the preaching of <persName>Christ</persName> had set foot,
                  eastern and northern and southern, wherever there were peoples and kingdoms to
                  whom the preaching of the gospel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">εύαγγελιον</foreign>)
                  had penetrated, in the east and the north and the south; but toward the west he
                  came only as far as the royal city, and he ended his course there, the third time
                  that he came up,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a28" target="#n28" n="28"/> while we were
                  present there. The good and mereiful God therefore, who does not fail to reward
                  zeal for his name, on seeing the man's purpose of mind and his zeal, and that he
                  underwent weariness no less than that of the apostles without shrinking, himself
                  also bestowed upon him in no less degree than upon them his gift that was given to
                  the apostles, of speaking with new tongues. For, whatever people's country he
                  entered, on the third day that came he would speak with them in their own tongue,
                  thanking God who had visited him. And so also he even delivered an exposition in
                  the chancel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">βήμα</foreign>) in the churches of all the
                  peoples to whom he went; and on this account he would declare and say to us with
                  tears, <quote>In this matter I recognised clearly that God had visited me and
                     strengthened me, and that he had not withheld his grace and his merey from
                     me</quote>. But <pb n="156"/>
                        <pb n="156"/>he reflected, <quote>What parchments
                        (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χάρτης</foreign>) and what rolls are capable of
                     going through all this wear of long and protracted journeys through the
                     countries without being torn to pieces?</quote> And for this reason, and in
                  order that the certainty of the writing might remain without suspicion of
                  alteration, he made great linen cloths and medicated them, so that they might take
                  writing, which also will, I think, be preserved by the believers in the land of
                  the <persName>Persians</persName> for ever; and on them he would accordingly write
                  the belief of every people in their own language from their archbishops, and above
                  the belief he affixed the seals of the king of that people and of the bishops of
                  the same and of their chief men in lead upon these cloths, and thus confirmed it,
                  acting thus among all peoples and all tongues among the believers,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a29" target="#n29" n="29"/> going about and taking their belief
                  and the seals of their soverans and of their highpriests. And thus he collected
                  the belief of many peoples and of many tongues on these cloths. And he turned back
                  after seven years and went away (?);<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a30" target="#n30" n="30"/> and, while he was on his way back, the king in whose days he had started
                     died,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a31" target="#n31" n="31"/> and the magnates who had
                  been umpires, and his son succeeded <pb n="157"/>
                        <pb n="157"/>him; and he
                  proceeded to stir up war in the territories of the
                     <persName>Romans</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a32" target="#n32" n="32"/> and
                  his appearance before the authorities was not carried out. But it became known to
                  all men living in the country of the <persName>Persians</persName> that the evil
                  doctrine of Nestorius flourished there only, while all peoples and tongues
                  abhorred it; and this glorious old man was yet more emboldened against them. In
                  this same zeal then some occasion called him to go up to the queen of the
                     <persName>Romans</persName>, to ask her for a letter to the chief queen of the
                     <persName>Persians</persName> about the affairs of the believers, and, if it
                  were possible, to go up in the same zeal to the territories of
                     <placeName>Rome</placeName>. And she gladly consented, because she had in fact
                  been well acquainted with his earnestness and his zeal for some time; and she
                  detained him there for the space of one year, holding him in great honour. And God
                  saw the saint's labour, and that he had grown old and very feeble, and his signal
                  gave command and he fell asleep there, in our presence; so that his presbyter who
                  himself also was devout and virtuous, whose name was <persName>Paul</persName>,
                  lived with us in the domicile of the glorious patrician <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3246">Probus</persName> for two years,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a33" target="#n33" n="33"/> while at all seasons we meditated
                  together upon the eloquence <pb n="158"/>
                        <pb n="158"/>of the holy old man
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> and on his
                  treatises and his proceedings against the heretics (<foreign xml:lang="grc">αίρεσιώται</foreign>), Nestorians and Manichees, and followers of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3">Bar Daisan</persName> and Eutychianists;
                  since he also composed a work of instruction and books of objections against the
                  heretics, and he write many letters on the faith to many believers everywhere,
                  some of which in the saint's own handwriting we inherited in order to supplement
                  his blessing. But at last that presbyter also as well fell asleep in the same
                  city, bearing the testimony of a devout manner of life. </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-10">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-10.1" n="8"> The history of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Simeon</persName> the bishop <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">the Persian debater</persName> is ended.
               </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 138, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I Cor., XV, 10.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 138, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Rom., XV, 19.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 139, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>The sentence is left unfinished, and the sense completed in another
               way.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 139, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>489 (<title>Chron</title>. Edess., A. S. foo).</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 139, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Cf. Simeon's own account in Assem., B. O., I, p. 350-354, from which John
               probably took this.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 140, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 140, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Acts, XX, 29.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 140, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Syr <hi rend="singleQuotes">Hirtha</hi> (d Nu'man) = Arab. <hi rend="singleQuotes">Al Hira</hi>; see p. 145.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 140, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. Ctesiphon</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 143, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Hypatius was sent on a embassy to Persia in 517 (P. O., VII, p, 661); but an
               earlier occasion seems to be here meant, for the 7 years' imprisonment (p.153) must
               have begun some years later, and S. afterwards travelled for 7 years and returned in
               531 (p. 156), and he was certainly at liberty in 524 (Assem., B. O., I, p. 364;
               'Zach. Rh.',VIII, 3). Moreover, if the narrative is in chronological order, this
               mission to Constantinople preceded the dispute with the Nestorians, which was between
               499 and 504 (p. 147).</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 143, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>This was meant perh. among the documents which came into the acuthor's
               possession (p. 158), and, if so, he no doubt quotes from it.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 144, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>like <foreign xml:lang="grc">πυνθάνομαι</foreign>, is often used in this
               sense; see p. 39, n. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 144, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Lit. <hi rend="singleQuotes">his own person (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>)</hi>
                </note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 144, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>See below (p. 145). The same story is told of James (ch. 49).</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 145, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Arzanene. From p. 147, l. 16, it is clear that the only Nestorian
                  <foreign>catholicus</foreign>, the bishop of Seleucia, is meant.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 146, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 146, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">riding-animals</hi>, perhaps dromedaries
               (P.-Smith, s. V. ).</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 147, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>499-504.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 148, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>As John was no theologian, the argument here advanced must be ascribed to
               Simeon; but that Babai and the marzban used the words put into their mouths <hi rend="singleQuotes">credat Judaeus</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 148, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>As the verb is fem., we should perhaps write <hi rend="singleQuotes">word</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n21" target="#a21" n="21">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 149, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 39, n. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n22" target="#a22" n="22">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 151, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">proper character</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n23" target="#a23" n="23">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 151, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 39, n. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n24" target="#a24" n="24">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 152, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Near Seleucia (Bar., H. E., ed. Abbeloos and Lamy, III, p. 85).</note>
                <note xml:id="n25" target="#a25" n="25">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 154, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n26" target="#a26" n="26">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 154, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>The reason for the journey can hardly have been as here stated, since the
               Persians would have no object in making the inquiry and knew well that the Nestorians
               differed from the Christians of the empire and therefore favoured them. Moreover it
               was to the interest of the Nestorians to lay stress upon the difference, not to deny
               it; cf. p. 142, 147. Barh. (l.c.) says that S. obtained an order from the king to
               encourage the Monophysites to hold their services freely and to defend them against
               the Nestorians, adding that he received certificates from Greeks, Armenians, and
               Syrians, saying that they differed from the Nestorians.</note>
                <note xml:id="n27" target="#a27" n="27">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 155, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>The second occasion is not mentioned, unless two visits are here intended,
               the third being that recorded below (p. 157, 1. 6).</note>
                <note xml:id="n28" target="#a28" n="28">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 156, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I.e. the Monophysites. Therefore he went only to those who agreed with him.
               What kings besides the king of Abyssinia and an Arab shaikh or two are meant is not
               easy to see.</note>
                <note xml:id="n29" target="#a29" n="29">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 156, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>This word has perh. crept in from below.</note>
                <note xml:id="n30" target="#a30" n="30">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 156, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Kawad, who d. Sept. 531.</note>
                <note xml:id="n31" target="#a31" n="31">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 157, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Not till 538. His first act was to make peace (532; <title>Chr.
                  Edess.</title>, A. S. 843; 'Zach. Rh.', IX, 7).</note>
                <note xml:id="n32" target="#a32" n="32">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 157, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Probably 540-542; see Introd. and Dyakonov, p. 50. Simeon's stay in
               Constantinople wil then have been 539-540.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
