<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/803">Ḥarphat</title>
            <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/802"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/804"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/803.xml -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-11" n="11">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-11">
               <head type="main">Next the Eleventh History, of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1771">Harfat</persName> the Chorepiscopus From the Country of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Anzetene</placeName>
                  <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>
               </head>
               <ab xml:id="section-11.1" n="1"> This blessed man belonged to a distinguished, great, and
                  rich family (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>); and, when all the members
                  of his family (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>), his parents included, had
                  died, the whole household and the wealth were left in this man's hands, <pb type="vol" n="159"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="159"/>and also in the hands of another kinsman older than he;
                  and he practised deceit and was a man of artful tricks and a dogjoh like
                  <persName>Nabal</persName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> and
                  he was moreover engaged in the affairs of the <foreign>praetoriani</foreign>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> But this virtuous <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1771">Harfat</persName> lived in pure and simple
                  fashion and spent a guileless life within the house like
                  <persName>Jacob</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/>
                  having committed the whole management of it to that kinsman of his; and he himself
                  as far as he could gave his attention to the needy and to the salvation of his
                  soul, while his soul was indeed vexed and he was distressed at the multitude of
                  male and female slaves, and hired servants and outsiders, and the other luxuries
                  of the household; and he would think in himself, and say: <quote>Wherefore do I
                     need all this parade, while debtors go on bringing interest and bonds continue
                     to be exacted every day?</quote>; but the blessed man was occupied with
                  thoughts that were adverse to these things. After a little time the bishop of a
                  place called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2744">Arsamosata</placeName>
                  died, and they came to make the blessed man bishop, that is in the Chalcedonian
                  communion;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> but he shrank from
                  this. When they saw that this man had absolutely refused, under the inducement of
                  riches and high position they <pb type="vol" n="160"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="160"/>seized <rs ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3764">his kinsman</rs>, a layman, and made him
                  bishop; and, when he had become bishop, the blessed man continually required of
                  him to divide the estate; in order that he himself might distribute his share
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μέρος</foreign>) among the needy, and he would not
                  agree, saying, <quote>While I live, it shall not be divided</quote>. Now they had
                  about five thousand <foreign>denarii</foreign>, besides all the rest of the
                  estate, and, when that man had gone to his see, the blessed man distributed as
                  much as he could among the needy, and committed the rest to our Lord, saying,
                  <quote>Lord, thou knowest the readiness of my mind, and the fact moreover that
                     neither hast thou commanded me to continue in contention and strife.
                     llenceforth, Lord, dispose thou my wretched soul to live before thee according
                     to thy will</quote>. </ab>
               <ab xml:id="section-11.2" n="2"> Then the blessed man left the house and the office of the
                  chorepiscopate which he had held for some years, and withdrew to a convent of the
                  solitary life. And, because he was very simple, and thought that this was the
                  consummation of perfection, he went and made great heavy irons and put them upon
                  himself, that is on his neck and on his hands and on his feet, <pb type="vol" n="161"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="161"/>two on each. And he went and settled on a certain mountain about three
                  miles from the cultivated land, and he did not take or receive any part whatever
                  of his property, but he would sit thus on that mountain, mourning and weeping and
                  groaning for the rest of life which had been spent and had passed from him in
                  vain. But, when he had stayed a considerable time in these mountains, in
                  consequence of the quantity of snow and the severity of the cold the blessed man
                  suffered great distress and was brought to the point of death. Then a certain
                  believing lady made a hut for him, and in it he would sit and weep night and day,
                  though many said to him, <quote>What is the cause of this weeping of yours that is
                     thus incessant and not for a limited season? The man who weeps out of sorrow
                     for his sins has seasons. Why do you thus weep like a baby over your eating and
                     your sitting down and your rising up?</quote> But, when he heard these words,
                  the blessed man's sobs would rose all the more, and his very speech to the man who
                  was addressing him was mingled with weeping, while he expressed himself saying,
                  <quote>Who, my sons, will not weep, when he sees a decayed and putrid <pb type="vol" n="162"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="162"/>corpse thrown down in his house? Who will not mourn
                     for the sons of youth fair to behold and of attractive age, when he sees that
                     death has corrupted their features, and they have become mire and putrescence
                     and loathsome worms in place of the attractive beauty of childhood? And, if men
                     weep for these with sobs, how shall I not now wail bitterly for my wretched
                     soul that was fashioned in the likeness of angels with all beauties, and lo! is
                     dead in sin and decayed through evil deeds and cast down in the house of the
                     body, and in which corrupt and abominable thoughts creep about like worms? How
                     shall I not weep for my moments that have been spent by me in vain without my
                     perceiving it? How shall I not mourn for my days that I have uselessly wasted
                     one by one without knowing it? And now lo! the terrible sentence of torment is
                     prepared for me, which the workers of iniquity deserve.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> For this reason I ought not only to weep, but also
                     to mourn and wail like a jackal, and increase mourning as of a jackal's whelp
                     for my life that has been spent, for my moments that have been consumed, for my
                     years that have been lost, for my time that has been wasted, for my <pb type="vol" n="163"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="163"/>soul that is dead in sin, for my body that has been made a
                     grave during my life, for my soul that is dead in evil deeds, for the judgment
                     that has arrived, for the end of life that has overtaken me, for the terrible
                     sentence of justice, for the moment when the command will go forth, <quote>He
                        who hath not wedding-garments, let his hands and his feet be bound and let
                        him be cast into outer darkness</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> And for what reasons, pray, O men, do you advise me
                     to cease crying woe upon my life at all moments?</quote> And thus this man used
                  to cause all men to marvel and be amazed, until the report of his mortification
                  and of his affliction penetrated to every place. And, when we heard these things,
                  we made it our object to obtain a sight of this blessed man. And, having done
                  this, we went and entered his presence; and so we found him in the same state,
                  sitting in dejection, and in great infirmity on account of the labour and the
                  abstinence, as well as from the weight of these irons. And, when we had enjoyed
                  his society for a day and two days, and had gained freedom (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>) of speech in his presence, and continued
                  saying to him <quote>Wherefore, O our father, have you burdened your body with the
                     weight of all this iron?</quote>, he said to us, <quote>On account of my
                        sins</quote>. And, when <pb type="vol" n="164"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="164"/>we were on another occasion
                  conversing with, him, we again said to him: <quote>What regulation commands this
                     matter of the irons to be carried out?</quote>, and, <quote>If we seek to
                        humble our body to the earth by labours of asceticism, cannot we humble it
                        without irons?</quote>. After we had addressed many words to the blessed man,
                  he continued to weep and sigh; and at last he said to us: <quote>And now, sir,
                     what do you wish done?</quote>. And I, joking a little with him, said to him:
                  <quote>We wish you to throw off these irons which are a useless burden, and
                     lade yourself instead of them with the burden of labours performed with
                     knowledge; and thus you will please God</quote>. But tbe blessed man was much
                  annoyed at these words, saying, <quote>It were better for me that my head were
                     removed and not these irons</quote>. And I turned upon him with the words:
                  <quote>For what reason?</quote> But he in his simplicity said, <quote>On
                     account of my sins, and on account of the stumbling-block put in men's
                     way</quote>. But we, since we pitied the infirmity of his body, and wished to
                  remove these irons from him, said to him: <quote>Lo! therefore see, our father,
                     that the matter <pb type="vol" n="165"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="165"/>of the irons is addressed only to
                     men, but there is nothing in them that brings near to God; but I even fear lest
                     they lead away from life; since God gave no commandment about irons. But, if we
                     seek to conduct ourselves according to knowledge and fulfil God's commandments,
                     we shall hear from him what he said, <quote>Learn of me for I am mild and lowly
                        in my heart</quote>, and, <quote>Whoever smiteth thee upon thy
                           cheek</quote>; and first <quote>Thou shalt love the Lord thy God</quote>; and
                     again <quote>Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself</quote>; and again
                     <quote>Whoever will take thy cloak</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> besides the other things which the Lord taught and
                     commanded us in his preaching. If, our father, you wish to please the Lord, it
                     is by these things and by the others that are like them that you will please;
                     but by irons God will never be pleased; but they even become sources of
                     detriment to the soul. For now, as you said, you are a sinner; and we or others
                     who see you with irons hanging on you think to ourselves that you are a great
                     and holy man, and a worker of miracles. If you are so, you do well in hanging
                     irons on yourself</quote>. When the blessed man heard all these things, his
                  heart trembled and he said: <quote>If it is so, and <pb type="vol" n="166"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="166"/>they
                     tend to cause loss, I do not desire to suffer loss; for as for me it is my
                     earnest endeavour to amass gain, and not loss</quote>. And so he committed
                  himself to our Lord, and to us; and by the aid of many strong men we took these
                  irons off him; and thenceforth he subjugated himself by double labours in their
                  place, insomuch that after seven years we returned to him, and we found him thus
                  living a hard life, and thus he ended his days with great glory. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-11">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-11.1" n="3"> The history of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1771">Harfat</persName> the chorepiscopus is
                  ended. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 158, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Syr. <hi rend="singleQuotes">Hanzit</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 159, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>I Sam., XXV, 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 159, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Sc. the civil servants in the governor's office.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 159, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>Gen., XXV, 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 159, n. 4</orig>
               </choice>This would be not earlier than 519, and we find in fact a Monophysite bp. of
               Arsamosata at that time ('Zach. Rh',VIII, 5).</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 162, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Luke, XIII, 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 163, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Matth., XXII, 31.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 165, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Id., XI, 29; V, 39; XXII, 37, 39; V, 40.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
