<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/805">Thomas, Stephen, and Zota</title>
                <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/804"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/806"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/805.xml -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-13" n="13">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-13">
                    <head type="main">Next the Thirteenth History, of Certain Saints and Servants of God, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3010">Stephen</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3011">Zwṭʾ</persName> the Notaries (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νοτάριος</foreign>) and <foreign>syncelli</foreign> of the Holy
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/48">Mare</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> Metropolitan of the City of
                  Amida</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-13.1" n="1"> After the decease of the believing king <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2265">Anastasius</persName> who is among the
                  saints, when <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2268">Justin</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> was set over the kingdom, he was
                  making a beginning of divisions and contentions in the church of God by
                  introducing the impious synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>; and from that
                  time forward by order of the same schismatic king everyone who did not assent to
                  the reception and introduction of the synod lived under persecution and expulsion,
                  and certain members of the church were accordingly banished to various places of
                  exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορίας</foreign>). The beginning of these things
                  occurred in the year eight hundred and thirty of
                     <persName>Alexander</persName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/>
                  and from this time forward were clearly seen in every man's case the love that was
                  in him and the foundation of his heart and the <pb type="vol" n="188"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="188"/>firmness
                  of his will, those who had<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> the love
                  of God, and those again who had<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> the
                  love of the world and desire for positions of power and inclination toward the
                  renegades. These things therefore quickly reached <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1452">Mesopotamia</placeName>, and overtook the
                  holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/48">Mare</persName> bishop of
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>; and he took upon
                  himself to suffer persecution and expulsion with <persName>Christ</persName>,
                  rather than to depart from <persName>Christ</persName> and occupy the temple and
                  the throne of temporal honour<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> This
                  saint therefore, with <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3257">Sergius</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3010">Stephen</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName> his notaries (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νοτάριος</foreign>)
                  and <foreign>syncelli</foreign>, were<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> sent to a hard and distant place of exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορίας</foreign>) at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/157">Petra</placeName>; and they accepted it and departed and went; and they were
                  there in great distress exceeding their power of endurance, until their lives were
                  near disappearing. By reason of this distress therefore the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/48">Mare</persName> was constrained to send the
                  virtuous zealous <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3010">Stephen</persName>
                  his deacon and notary (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νοτάριος</foreign>) to the royal
                  city, in the hope that he might perhaps by the intercession of anyone whom <pb type="vol" n="189"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="189"/>God might put in his way be able to have that place
                  altered for them. But, when he went up, the good God, who, as the divine apostle
                  also says, <quote>is faithful and just, who will not permit you to be tried more
                     than ye are able to be tried</quote>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> directed the virtuous <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3010">Stephen</persName> to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">Theodora</persName> who came from the brothel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πορνείον</foreign>), who was at that time a patrician, but eventually became
                  queen also with <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2268">King
                     Justinian</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> She
                  therefore, when she learned of that distress, as if by divine instigation, because
                  she saw that saint's distress, made her mercy manifest, and made entreaty to
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2268">Justinian</persName> her
                  husband, who was master of the soldiers (<foreign xml:lang="grc">στρτατηλάτης</foreign>) and also a patrician and the king's nephew,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> that he would inform his uncle, and
                  he might order relief to be given to these distressed men, making this entreaty
                  even with tears. And, through the grace which cares for every man's life, it was
                  done and an order went out to them to come to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>. And <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3010">Stephen</persName> the deacon took this
                  order, and brought it down, both to them and to the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2545">Isidore</persName> another bishop, of
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/162">Kenneshrin</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> who also was exiled there with them;
                  and according<pb type="vol" n="190"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="190"/>ly a great relief and deliverance was
                  effected for these blessed men, because at that time this city became a habitation
                  of men driven by persecution from all quarters, and a place of reception for men
                  expelled from every place; and from that time the blessed men were quietly settled
                  in the same city. But, after a short time, some cause called them to be in need of
                  a utensil (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σκευάριον</foreign>) such as they make out of
                  the leaves of the date-palm for household use; and, as it were by the dispensation
                  of God, an old man was found selling them who lived in a certain desert in the
                  region of Libya belonging to a village called Mendis,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> which lies twenty-four miles above <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>, and this old man had
                  also had also come into this desert from <placeName>Palestine</placeName> under
                  persecution, with other blessed men as well as virtuous blessed women also who
                  were living in quietude in that place, in a certain tower which had been set up
                  for defence against barbarians.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/>
                  Since therefore this man came from the territory (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χώρα</foreign>) of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, and the blessed men who accompanied the holy bishop
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/48">Mare</persName> saw that he was an
                  educated man and spoke their language, <pb type="vol" n="191"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="191"/>they brought him,
                  and received his <foreign>mzyqn</foreign>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> from him, and conversed with him; and they inquired also further where
                  he lived. And, when he had told them all his affairs, the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3010">Stephen</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName> the deacons conceived
                  the desire of going out to that place; and he conducted them, and they went out
                  with him; and they saw the blessed men driven out by persecution who were with him
                  and the blessed women, and the quietude of the place also attracted them. And they
                  also told them about a certain large pit that lay near the place in the desert at
                  a distance of two miles, in which someone had once lived;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> and they went and saw it. And from that time the
                  blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName>, with
                  whom the chief part of the story and the course of the narrative are concerned,
                  formed the plan of going down and living in that pit; a luxurious and dainty man,
                  who from his childhood had been brought up like a king's son, who was also a
                  descendant (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3215">Ishakuni Bar Brʿy</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> who was a patrician; who was mighty
                  and great and eminent above all who were in <placeName>the East</placeName>; and
                  the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName>
                  moreover possessed an estate (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ούσία</foreign>) and male
                  and female slaves, and great riches; and he was so luxurious <pb type="vol" n="192"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="192"/>and dainty that he used to clean his face and his hands with water
                  more than ten times a day. This saint then, who lived under these conditions, now
                  in opposition to these things formed the resolution of acquiring ascetic habits.
                  But, when his object became known, that he wished to do these things, then
                  everyone who heard it would as it were laugh at his purpose, saying, <quote>All
                     that delicacy and luxury wants to dwell in the waste uninhabited
                  desert</quote>. And, though the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3010">Stephen</persName> had the intention of
                  doing spiritual service, yet, because he was feeble and sickly of body, he
                  refrained from doing these things, saying, <quote>For ourselves this is too great
                     a thing to live in the desert on account of our feebleness; but, my brother,
                     let us look after our soul, and gain a desert by our manner of life and our
                     heart, and always entreat the Lord to cause his grace to shine upon us</quote>.
                  When they had returned to the city, the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName> provided for the
                  concerns of his cell, doing everything in secret, and he gave his key (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κλείδα</foreign>) to the bishop's cellarer (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κελλαρίτης</foreign>), and for some reason was blessed by the
                  saint without his knowing of it;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/>
                  and he departed and returned to the place, and went straight <pb type="vol" n="193"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="193"/>to that pit, bravely applying himself thenceforward to asceticism and
                  vigil and protracted recitation of services. But he used to go down into that pit
                  and come up again, that he might not put force upon his body all at once and faint
                  and be overcome, while the blessed men who were the occasion of his going out to
                  that place supplied his necessary requirements. And so in that pit he laid great
                  and grievious labours upon himself, and was without ceasing continuously occupied
                  in weeping and sorrow and mourning for his sins, and these blessed men (since
                  these also were very perfect in their manner of life) used to relate to me,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/>
                        <quote>Whenever we see the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName>, we find him beating his face, and saying, <quote>Woe to
                        me, my brethren, since I have consumed my days in vanity. Woe to me, since
                        my moments have melted away in evil deeds. Woe to me since my life has been
                        squandered in works of darkness. The world has deceived me. The demons have
                        mocked me. My mind has been lost in the vanity of the affairs of this lying
                        world. Pray for me, my brethren, that the merciful God may receive me in
                        repentance, and not turn his face away from my hatefulness. Pray for me that
                        the door of mercy at which I am knocking may be opened to me, and I <pb type="vol" n="194"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="194"/>may find the life of my wretched soul which was
                        lost. All the carefulness of life I for my part expended on these
                        corruptible concerns of this body of dust; and life has passed away and
                        death has come near, and corruption is at hand, and judgment has overtaken
                        me. And what shall I do, my brethren? Woe to me woe to me, the erring one.
                        Where, pray, was my darkened mind, that it did not think of these things
                        till to-day?</quote>. As often as he saw us</quote> (these blessed men used
                  to say to me), <quote>by reason of the sound of his sobs and his weeping and
                     mourning for his soul he would make us also weep</quote>. When he had been in
                  that pit six years, because attacks of bodily infirmity and the influence of damp
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νοτία</foreign>) had greatly affected him, and he had
                  become infirm by reason of the severity of the labours which he had laid upon
                  himself, they with great force lifted him out of it. After a space of eight years
                  the holy bishop <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/48">Mare</persName>
                  departed from the body in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/> while
                  his two sisters<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/> also who were
                  deaconesses were there in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>, women who are themselves also in truth among the
                  saints by reason of the greatness of their mode of life. And, after the decease of
                  the blessed bishop <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/48">Mare</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a21" target="#n21" n="21"/>
                        <pb type="vol" n="195"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="195"/>his sisters with the rest of the company (<foreign xml:lang="grc">συνδία</foreign>) that was with them prepared to carry his bones
                  down to his own country; and they sent the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3010">Stephen</persName> the deacon to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">Theodora</persName>, who had before
                  interested herself in procuring their release from exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>), who also at the time had become queen;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a22" target="#n22" n="22"/> and she thereupon issued an order
                  that the blessed man should be carried down. And, when the order came, they
                  thereupon continued constraining this blessed man who loved the wilderness to show
                  his gratitude to his holy bishop, and consent to go down with them with his bones
                  to his country. But the blessed man utterly refused to do this, saying, <quote>It
                     cannot be</quote>. And, when they had made many attempts to induce him to
                  consent to go down, and if he wished, return, saying to him, <quote>If you wish
                     this, it would not be right for you to leave your estate (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ούσία</foreign>) and your affairs to chance, but you ought to
                     go down and arrange matters as you wish between yourself and your sister, and
                     come back</quote>, and, when they had urged him, he considered this to be the
                  right course, since he came to this conclusion, that it was not in accordance with
                  right that his affairs should remain <pb type="vol" n="196"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="196"/>without provision;
                  and he accepted and went down with them in silence, and with his head covered, and
                  his tears always flowing. And, when they saw that he was constantly weeping night
                  and day, then these holy women also who saw that his tears ran down upon his food,
                  and on the road also while he was travelling again the same, and similarly also at
                  his lodging-place, being much astonished at his sorrow, would say to him:
                     <quote>What is the matter with you, father, that you thus constantly
                     weep?</quote> But the devout and holy man would say to them: <quote>I weep
                     because I am sick; but pray for me</quote>. But they, as they used to relate,
                     <quote>as if to jest a little with him said to him: <quote>And what of it? Does
                        a man who is sick thus constantly weep?</quote>
                        </quote> But he said to us:
                     <quote>A man who is seriously ill, if he feels that his complaints are giving
                     him pain, weeps even if he does not wish it'</quote>. And so we would praise
                  God, who had thought him worthy of such sorrow and weeping and humility, and had
                  given him repentance that he might know his blemishes. But, when they had gone
                  down and reached the city, and the magnates and their kinsmen and the whole city
                  had come out to receive them, and the bones of the blessed bishop had <pb type="vol" n="197"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="197"/>been laid in his martyrs' chapel which he had built, called that
                  of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2757">Beth Shurla</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a23" target="#n23" n="23"/> they proceeded to enter the city;
                  but the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName>
                  directed his steps to a monastic convent on the north of the city which is called
                  that of the house of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John</persName>, of which I also was an inmate for about 19 years from the
                  time of the departure of the holy <persName>Maro</persName> my spiritual
                     father.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a24" target="#n24" n="24"/>, both when it was
                  suffering persecution and when it was at peace<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a25" target="#n25" n="25"/> To this monastery then this saint came; and he went in
                  and prayed, and he asked for a lodging, and it was given him. And, when his
                  sister, whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3202">Cosmo</persName>, who also was a woman of virtuous habits of life, and the
                  other persons of high position urged him to go into his house and that of his
                  people, he did not yield to them, saying, <quote>Learn, my brethren, from the
                     divine psalmist who says, <quote>One day in thine habitation is better than a
                        thousand</quote>
                            <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a26" target="#n26" n="26"/>
                        </quote>.
                  And, when the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3010">Stephen</persName> the deacon saw that he had taken up his lodging outside,
                  because they loved one another, and also imitated one another in the matter of
                  virtuous practices, he also <pb type="vol" n="198"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="198"/>asked to lodge outside in
                  the monastery. And thus they did, while both of them were detained, because they
                  intended to return to the desert together. And they were delayed for two years;
                  though, if their thoughts had not been completely set upon God, it would have been
                  decided that they should remain for good.' The blessed men thenceforward together
                  with <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3011">Zwṭʾ</persName> the deacon,
                  who also was a clergyman (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κληρικός</foreign>) of the
                  church under the same holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/48">Mare</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a27" target="#n27" n="27"/> himself also
                  devoted himself to death or life with the blessed men, who himself also astonished
                  those who knew him by the manner of life which he finally adopted, while it would
                  never have entered any one's mind that that man would ever place upon his nock the
                  great yoke of monasticism. And the three of them thenceforth lived with one
                  virtuous purpose, while to see to what humiliation the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName> had come from what
                  splendour and greatness astonished and saddened everyone; and so many used to
                  spurn and despise everything in him. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-13.2" n="2"> This space of two years then he occupied in making an
                  equal division between himself and his sister, saying, <quote>She is in the world,
                     and needs her <pb type="vol" n="199"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="199"/>share. I am not required to dispose of
                     anything except my own</quote>. When they had completed everything, and he was
                  thenceforth desirous of returning to the desert, being every day vexed and annoyed
                  and distressed at his detention from that country, I, inasmuch as I was close at
                  hand and had been in constant intercourse with him because I had seen his manner
                  of life, and had also gained freedom of speech (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>) before him, would say to him as if jesting with him,
                     <quote>Why, pray, are you vexed, father? Lo! are you not in a monastery? (for
                     are you in the world?), lo! it lies before you to fast and to pray, and
                     practise asceticism as much as you wish. Wherefore are you distressed? You had
                     a cell in the desert, and lo! here too is a cell. Do in it as you wish</quote>.
                  But the blessed man, while I on my part was sayi these things to him, kept his
                  hand resting upon his cheek, and looked at me in astonishment; and at last he
                  sighed and said to me: <quote>Can a slave then (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρα</foreign>) serve two masters?<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a28" target="#n28" n="28"/> or again can a man be in intercourse with God and <pb type="vol" n="200"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="200"/>with men and can one see any of one's relatives and bodily kin
                        (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) and approach spiritual things?
                     accept my statement, sir, that for me a foreign land is much better, and it
                     preserves me from many impediments. Or know you not that hour after hour and
                     moment after moment privily steal and snatch away part of our life like wolves
                     and flee from us, so that, since, if all our lifetime we run after one moment
                     of our life, we shall not overtake it, how, father, shall we not weep and
                     lament for one day only that passes idly from us, without bearing the fruits of
                     our praises and presenting them to God, and again that also our petitions and
                     prayers and requests may on it be<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a29" target="#n29" n="29"/> depicted and made visible before God? Know you not that man's days and his
                     years are themselves like volumes full of letters, and every day and hour on
                     which a man does good or evil, or performs praise or prayer, that hour or day
                     records them upon itself, and presents them before God, and, since God is
                     omniscient, in order that the man may be judged or applauded according to his
                     conduct in life, and that everything that has been done by him <pb type="vol" n="201"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="201"/>may be known to him, therefore his own moments approach in order
                     and pass before God, each one of them carrying that which that man did in it,
                     whether it be what is good or what is evil, and showing it to God. And, if
                     again a day which has passed of our life is one of abstention from good deeds
                     and from evil, the place in the life of the man whoever he be is in it
                     similarly void and torpid and useless, and it stands up and accuses him, since
                     that day carries the fruits of the saints, and the confession of the
                     confessors, and the praises of those who give praise, and the prayers of those
                     who pray, and the alms of the givers, and the forgiveness of those who forgive,
                     and shows them to God, every man's own actions which he performed in it being
                     depicted on it. And now, O father, when these things are so, how shall we
                     neglect one hour and not tremble to let it pass from us void without carrying
                     the fruits of our repentance, and without the words of our praises being
                     written upon it? How, our brother, shall we be caught by the deceit of this
                     lying world, and not understand and consider that from this hour in which we
                     now stand we were equally distant from the time of our birth down to the
                     present day, and, since we began to speak, it has been quickly fleeing from us
                     and departing, and, if we run after it for a thousand years, <pb type="vol" n="202"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="202"/>we should not be able to overtake it again or to see it for ever
                     and ever? And for this reason it is much better for me to go and sit in some
                     corner (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γωνία</foreign>), and weep for my life and for
                     my empty moments and for my profitless years, and for my hours that have melted
                     and passed from me empty and void, where neither acquaintances nor relatives
                     will harass me; because in the moment when the sentence goes forth upon me no
                     friends, or loved ones, or kin (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>), or
                     members of the family, will give me any pleasure</quote>, As for me, while I
                  was listening to all these things from this saint, great marvel fell upon me that
                  he so effectually controlled his thoughts and collected his mind, directing it
                  toward God, and did not allow even if it were one idle hour or moment of his life
                  to be lost without praise and prayer and repentance, and thus shunned and dreaded
                  and feared the waste of one hour only. Then I marvelling in my mind thought,
                     <quote>Pray, what sounds and songs of lamentations will suffice to make lament
                     for my own sell, and for the rest of those who are like me? since I have wasted
                     some of my moments, that is even the whole of my life, in wantonness (<foreign xml:lang="grc">στρηνία</foreign>); and not only has <pb type="vol" n="203"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="203"/>one hour not been treated by me as of any account, but not even a whole year
                     of days also</quote>. And marvelling I went out from the presence of the
                  blessed man, and used to repeat all these things to my brethren with trembling.
                  Now the blessed man's manner of life while he was in the monastery was as follows,
                  fasting from one evening to the next, and scanty food; and indeed with the freedom
                  of speech (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>) that I had acquired with
                  him I used to say to him, <quote>In truth I wonder how you live</quote>; but he
                  would answer me, saying: <quote>What have I gained by feeding my body as if for
                     sacrifice down to the present time? Or ought I not to know that food belongs to
                     the creeping thing and the worms? Wherefore must I take fire and scorch my
                     eyelids? When the body receives foods and is nourished and grows fat, the fire
                     of passions and lusts is kindled in it, and it scorches and burns the eyes of
                     the soul so that they do not see and restrain it from sinning. And now, instead
                     of it hanging to the soul so that it is brought down and, wallows in the mire
                     of the body's lusts, let the soul hang upon it, that the body may rise out of
                     its mire and share in the soul's purity and lightness. Those who concern
                     themselves with the nourishment of their bodies, thinking that it is a good
                     thing, are weaving a rope of pigskin and <pb type="vol" n="204"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="204"/>throwing it
                     round their own necks, and giving the end of it to Satan to drag them to
                     torment</quote>. But, while he was delighting us with such words, he would
                  abstain even from the scanty quantity of food that he was in the habit of taking.
                  But his recitation of service was one which lasted without ceasing from the first
                  hour in the night<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a30" target="#n30" n="30"/> until morning,
                  while during every <foreign rend="italics">marmitha</foreign>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a31" target="#n31" n="31"/> he would make thirty Egyptian
                  genuflexions which are called prayers, until he accomplished five hundred during
                  the night with the service of matins; and these I myself on many nights secretly
                  counted without his discovering me; because I too also occupied a cell behind his
                  cell, and there was only a partition between me and him, while we were some
                  distance from the common chapel of the brotherhood, together with the virtuous men
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3010">Stephen</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3011">Zwṭʾ</persName>, and we alone lived in
                  cells. The first time that I heard the sound of his <foreign xml:lang="grc">μετάνοιαι</foreign>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a32" target="#n32" n="32"/> behind my
                  cell, since he used to <pb type="vol" n="205"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="205"/>make three knocks in quick
                  succession, the sound would come to me just as if three men were striking together
                  upon a smith's anvil with hammers, the sounds following one another till morning,
                  since his hands first struck the ground, and after them his knees, and lastly his
                  head; and so he would suddenly sink down, until I thought that the sound was
                  coming up from beneath me, while I even crossed myself and said, <quote>Perhaps
                     Satan is mocking me, and is making me hear this sound in order to deceive
                     me</quote>; and I would go outside by night, and would hear the sound; and I
                  would come in again, and there was the same sound. And, because the blessed man
                  showed great care and earnestness in charging and entreating everyone, <quote>Let
                     not a man approach the door of my cell till the morning, because I am a very
                     bad sleeper, and, if I am aware that any one is passing round the place where I
                     am sleeping, it is quite impossible for me to sleep again, and I am tormented
                     the whole night</quote>
                        <!-- missing in translation -->, on account of this
                  charge therefore no one approached his cell, lest he should annoy him, since we
                  thought that it was as he said; but he wished to act by stealth and not be
                  discovered by stealth. </ab>
                    <pb type="vol" n="206"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="206"/>
                    <ab xml:id="section-13.3" n="3"> I therefore, keeping the charge, and being for many
                  nights annoyed by the sound, from the first hour of the night till morning,
                  wondered greatly. But one day, not having suflicient resolution to endure that
                  sound which had lasted many days and take no notice, I went outside and stood
                  still, listening to the sound; and I softly approached the door, and found that it
                  was he, who was pressed down under all this labour, panting as if he were running
                  before a horse; and I was greatly amazed at this man's labour. But his bed was
                  magnificently laid, and raised high by the number of its rugs, and he had wrapt
                  himself in a little piece of hair-matting fitted to his stature as iſ under his
                  feet (?), and on it he rested so far as he slept at all, while to us he presented
                  the appearance of really sleeping on his bed. And from that time I like an idle
                  man would often keep count of the industrious man's prayers, both those of the
                  night and those of the day. And thenceforward the virtuous men <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3010">Stephen</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3011">Zwṭʾ</persName>' the deacons made it
                  their endeavour to imitate him in everything, and they themselves also underwent
                  great labours. When then they had thereafter made preparations to set <pb type="vol" n="207"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="207"/>forth to the land of Egypt, and to live there as before, queen
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">Theodora</persName>, who had been
                  in intercourse with the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3010">Stephen</persName> the deacon both before she became queen and after she had
                  become queen, sent magistrians<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a33" target="#n33" n="33"/>
                  after him and a letter, earnestly inviting him to come up to the capital in order
                  to be with her in the palace (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>), because
                  of his eloquence and his conversation and his wisdom, and moreover because he also
                  lived a pure life and after the manner of a solitary; and this further hastened
                  them in making their departure. Then they left the district of <placeName>the
                     East</placeName>, and I also with them in intercourse with them, as far as
                     <placeName>Antioch</placeName>. And there <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3010">Stephen</persName> thenceforth continued
                  to entreat <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName>,
                  saying, <quote>My brethren, let us on no account. part from one another; but, in
                     order that this woman's will may not be disappointed, let us go up together to
                     the royal city, and return and go down together by sea to the desert</quote>.
                  But he, declining to do this, continued entreating him and saying: <quote>Pray for
                     me, my brother, since <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName> will not see anyone from this kingdom here</quote>. And
                  so with weeping and many <pb type="vol" n="208"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="208"/>sobs they parted from one
                  another, while the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3010">Stephen</persName> was entreating him and saying: <quote>Pray for me, my
                     brother, that I may sobs be dismissed from that city and come down to you, and
                     we may end our lives together in the convent of solitaries<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a34" target="#n34" n="34"/>
                        </quote>. But the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName>, shedding tears and
                  sobbing, said to him: <quote>Beware, my brother, and take care of your soul; and
                     day by day, as far as in you lies, entreat God in penitence for your sins. Let
                     not your thoughts mock you and say to you, <quote>You shall go out to the
                        desert and pray to God</quote>; because you shall never see the desert
                     again; but neither indeed shall we meet one another in the body any more; and
                     you will live in the royal city till the end of your life. Accordingly pray for
                     me</quote>. And they prayed, and they set out at the same time, while the
                  blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName> said,
                     <quote>As, when we left our country, we enjoined upon our kinsmen (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) and everyone to suppose that they were thus
                     following us to the grave, so, my brother, in this hour also do you think that
                     you are following me to the grave and you</quote>. And, while we were all
                  listening to these things, the tears of us all burst forth with sobs. And thus
                  they for their <pb type="vol" n="209"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="209"/>part separated, each of them to his own
                  quarter; and I returned again to the convent, intending by making petition to
                  obtain leave, and betake myself soon to the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName>. And after my return I
                  was a petitioner for two years; and, on account of the great love that the blessed
                  men bore towards me, scarcely with difficulty did they allow me to go.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a35" target="#n35" n="35"/> On reaching the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName> we learned about the
                  life of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName>, and about his marvellous habits; and we went out to him to
                  the desert called that of Mendis, twelve miles above the habitation of the holy
                  Mar <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2819">Menas</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a36" target="#n36" n="36"/> But, when we arrived and I saw the
                  blessed man, I scarcely recognised him, while I looked at him and was in doubt if
                  it was really he, since his whole body was black and burnt by the sun, and all his
                  hair was scorched and standing on end, and he was clad in one old garment of rags,
                  and one ugly little hood was bound round his face. And, when he saw me, he was
                  astounded, and fell on his face; and he came up and gripped us; and we greeted one
                  another, while I was still not sure that it was he, until at last I fixed my gaze
                  on him; <pb type="vol" n="210"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="210"/>and I was seized with astonishment to think to
                  what all that luxury had come. And, while he was exuberant with joy and was asking
                  me, <quote>What have you to say, father? what has brought you to the
                     sinners?</quote>, I was looking at him in astonishment, saying to him,
                     <quote>What has happened to you that your body is thus burnt, our
                     father?</quote> But he after these things bent his looks downward and shed
                  tears; and he said to me; <quote>Would, our brother, that my outward body might be
                     burnt, and not my soul that is stained with the evil deeds that I have done
                     from my childhood and down to the present time.</quote> After we had remained a
                  short time, about three months, occasion called us on our side to return again to
                  Syria; and so we received the blessing of the saint, together with all the rest of
                  the saints in the whole of the desert in which he was living, together with that
                  of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3011">Zwṭʾ</persName> the
                  deacon; and we left them, and returned, promising them that we would return again
                  to them. And thus we parted, we to our vain occupation, and they to their
                  spiritual employment. And, when twenty six years<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a37" target="#n37" n="37"/> had been completed <pb type="vol" n="211"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="211"/>by the
                  holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName> in such
                  great labours, in order that the conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>)
                  against his distresses which he displayed by means of his endurance might be
                  further increased, he fell for about eight months under the chastisement of an
                  illness; and then the blessed man finished his conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>); and he departed carrying the great and honoured burden of his
                  triumphs; and we were not again granted the privilege of seeing his face in the
                  body. But he left in his place after him the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3011">Zwṭʾ</persName> the deacon; who also
                  passed out of this disturbing and deceiving world in the same desert with great
                  labours and noble triumphs in the third year after the passing of the blessed
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName>. And so, after
                  we parted from them and down to the passing of each one of them, both they and we
                  were day by day in hope that we should be coming back to them; and so our sins
                  brought it about for us that we did not come to the place where they lived till a
                  year after the death of both. But we, after we had gone down to
                     <placeName>Syria</placeName>, went up again to the royal city; and we also
                  found the blessed virtuous <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3010">Stephen</persName> too;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a38" target="#n38" n="38"/> who
                  also did not fail to obtain the glory that is gained by great labours of
                  asceticism and of abstinence; and who was moreover a great harbour (<foreign xml:lang="grc">λιμήν</foreign>) of rest for all the <pb type="vol" n="212"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="212"/>afflicted who used to repair to him from all quarters, and a comforter of all
                  the distressed, and a noble example to all men; so that even the king and queen
                  themselves stood in awe of his venerable mode of life, and they executed his
                  orders in everything; and thus his cell had in consequence become a house of rest
                  for strangers. And, while half a <foreign>denarius</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ήμίσεον</foreign>) a day was allotted to his table, besides the
                  cost (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άναλώματα</foreign>) of his bondservants in addition
                  to other matters, so this was not large enough for the expenditure on the
                  strangers and the needy who used to come to him; and not only so, but to the
                  senators (<foreign xml:lang="grc">συγκλητιχοί</foreign>) themselves he was a great
                  comfort and support; and he was very well-known all over the city, but especially
                  in the palace (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>). And when the sentence
                  of pestilence went forth upon the world from God,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a39" target="#n39" n="39"/> he also too was carried off in it by the command; and
                  in his cell as the property of a man who might be supposed to have more than five
                  hundred pounds' weight (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κεντηνάριον</foreign>) of gold<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a40" target="#n40" n="40"/> nothing whatever was found after his
                  death except a <foreign>denarius</foreign> and a half. And, while men supposed
                  that he had money and the coins had been taken by others, there was found a <pb type="vol" n="213"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="213"/>tablet (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πιττάκιον</foreign>)
                  inscribed in his hand as follows: <quote>Lest anyone suspect me or accuse anyone
                     else in any matter, I write these things with my hand, that I am prepared to
                     give account to God on the day of judgment that neither at a distance nor close
                     at hand do I possess anything in the world except this
                        <foreign>denarius</foreign> and a half; and let this go to the poor</quote>.
                  And thus everyone was seized with astonishment, insomuch that some time afterwards
                  everyone used to speak of these things with wonder. </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-13">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-13.1" n="4"> The history of the saints <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2127">Thomas</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3010">Stephen</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3011">Zwṭʾ</persName>, the
                  <foreign>syncelli</foreign> and notaries (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νοτάριος</foreign>) of the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/48">Mare</persName> metropolitan of the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, is ended. </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 187, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This name is frequently thus pointed out in mss., and I therefore write it
               so rather than <hi rend="singleQuotes">Maria</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 187, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Mss. <hi rend="singleQuotes">Justinian</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 187, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>519.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 188, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>The verb is not in the syr., and the sentence in ungrammatical.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 188, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>The verb is not in the syr., and the sentence in ungrammatical.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 188, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>In 519, Thomas was bp. of Amida, but died, after the order for his
               expulsion, and his successor, Nonnus, lived only 3 months, after which Mare was
               appointed ('Zach. Rh.', VIII, 5; Assem., B.O., II, 349). His expulsion was probably
               in 521..</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 188, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Sic. syr. From the sequel it is clear that M. only was banished, and the
               others accompanied him voluntarily. Sergius is not again mentioned, and from the
               return to Amida we find Zwt' in his place.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 189, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I Cor., X, 13.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 189, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>See Proc., Hist. Arc., IX, Justinian's marriage followed upon <title>Cod.
                  Just.</title>, V, IV, 23, which, being addressed <hi rend="singleQuotes">Demostheni pp.</hi>, must be dated 520-524..</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 189, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Syr. <hi rend="singleQuotes">sister's son</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 189, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Chalcis. For I. see Severus, <title>Selected Letters</title>, p. 58, 66,
               153, 166, 369.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 190, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>W. of the Nile, now Mendishe (Yakut, <title>Geogr, Wörterb.</title>, ed.
               Wüstenfeld, IV, p. 661).</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 190, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Cf. ch. 27.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 191, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This must be the name of the utensil which they required. It probably
               represents some Greek word.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 191, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>The same is stated in Susan's case (ch. 27), and it is perh. the same cave,
               though one would have expected Susan to be mentioned as the last occupant.</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 191, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Cf. 'Zach. Rh.', VII, 4. Nöldeke's conjecture <hi rend="singleQuotes">Arsacids</hi> (Arshakuni), hesitatingly adopted by V. D. and L., is quite out of
               place.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 192, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I. e. without Mare knowing his purpose (?).</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 193, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This must have been in 534 (p. 209); but the words though given in the
               present, appear as spoken at the beginning of his ascetic life.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 194, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>If 8 years after his deprivation is meant, the date is probably 529. In this
               case, as Th. was in the pit 6 years, the removal to Egypt was not later than
               523.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 194, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Cf. 'Zach. Rh.' VIII, .</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 194, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>In B thename has the vowel points; see p. 187, n. 1.</note>
                <note xml:id="n21" target="#a21" n="21">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 195, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>1 Apr., 527.</note>
                <note xml:id="n22" target="#a22" n="22">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 197, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. <hi rend="singleQuotes">house of eye-film (?)</hi>. L. wrongly reads <hi rend="singleQuotes">Beth Shur'a</hi> (house of ruin). The reading of both mss. is
               clear.</note>
                <note xml:id="n23" target="#a23" n="23">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 197, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>522-540 (?). John's figures are not always quite accurate; see
               Introd.</note>
                <note xml:id="n24" target="#a24" n="24">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 197, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>As the monks were in exile till the end of 530 (see Introd.), the arrival of
               Amida cannot be earlier than that time.</note>
                <note xml:id="n25" target="#a25" n="25">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 197, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>s. LXXXIV, 11. The word for <hi rend="singleQuotes">habitation</hi> is the
               same as that for <hi rend="singleQuotes">monestary</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n26" target="#a26" n="26">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 198, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>The sentence is finished in a different way.</note>
                <note xml:id="n27" target="#a27" n="27">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 199, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Luke, XVI, 13.</note>
                <note xml:id="n28" target="#a28" n="28">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 200, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr. Perh. ins. a negative , and render <hi rend="singleQuotes">on which
                  our... requests are not</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n29" target="#a29" n="29">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 204, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>The hours seem to be reckoned from midnight. He could hardly begin at 7
               P.M., and, if he did, he would get no sleep at all. Cf. p. 215, n. 1.</note>
                <note xml:id="n30" target="#a30" n="30">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 204, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>A division of the Psalms (gr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">στάσις</foreign>). Of
               these were usually 15, so that we should probably understand that he made 50
               genuflexions during matins</note>
                <note xml:id="n31" target="#a31" n="31">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 204, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Prostrations in token of penitence.</note>
                <note xml:id="n32" target="#a32" n="32">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 207, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Officials of the staff of the <foreign>magister officorum</foreign>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n33" target="#a33" n="33">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 208, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">solitary life</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n34" target="#a34" n="34">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 209, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Since Th. stayed at least 2 years in Amida, we may probably place this visit
               in 534; see Introd. and Dyakanov, p. 47.</note>
                <note xml:id="n35" target="#a35" n="35">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 209, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>The celebrated monastery; see <title>Journ. As.</title>, ser. V, tom. XII
               (1858), p. 414. PATR. OR. - T. XVII. - F.1.</note>
                <note xml:id="n36" target="#a36" n="36">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 210, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>His ascetic life began at least 6 years before Mare's death (p. 194), and
               therefore probably between 521 and 523, which brings his death to 548-550 and J.'s
               visit to 551-554. J. however was in Alexandria in 541 (ch. 25. see Introd. and
               Dyakonov, p. 63), and there is no evidence that he was there later; and we may
               therefore take 26 as an error for '16', and place Th.'s death in 537-8.</note>
                <note xml:id="n37" target="#a37" n="37">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 211, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>J. probably here returns to the narrative on p. 210 and refers to his first
               visit to CP. in 535 (see Introd.).</note>
                <note xml:id="n38" target="#a38" n="38">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 212, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>The plague of 542.</note>
                <note xml:id="n39" target="#a39" n="39">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 212, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>(£ circ. 22.500 = Fr. 562.600.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
