<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/806">Abi</title>
            <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/805"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/807"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/806.xml -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-14" n="14">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-14">
               <head type="main">Next the Fourteenth History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1536">Abbi the Man of Abnegation and
                     Nazirite</persName>.</head>
               <ab xml:id="section-14.1" n="1"> This blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1536">Abbi</persName> lived in a certain convent
                  in great abnegation and abstinence, and severe labours. And, when the persecution
                  on account of the synod of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/622">Chalcedon</placeName> arose, the inmates of his convent were under the <pb type="vol" n="214"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="214"/>compulsion of the persecutors united to their communion;
                  but in the case of the holy old man, as they were unable to bring down his high
                  purpose that was set on <persName>Christ</persName>, they gave him a charge,
                  saying, <quote>If you will not yield, since you have been made an example to many,
                     withdraw yourself hence whither you please</quote>. Then the old man, weeping
                  for the time of error that had got possession of men, set forth and came to the
                  community of us <persName>the men of Amida</persName>, which was living in the
                  district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2858">Ṭyšf</placeName>, in a
                  village called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2796">Ḥzyn</placeName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> which was in
                  number seven hundred and fifty men. And, because this blessed man was acquainted
                  with the convent in which I was at that time,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> he came direct to us; and thus he attached himself to
                  the same monastery, having one tunic and one cape made of pieces of rag fastened
                  together, and a small text of the gospel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">εύαγγελιον</foreign>); and he would not consent to read in any other book
                  except that gospel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">εύαγγελιον</foreign>). And he chose
                  for himself a certain corner (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γωνία</foreign>) among the
                  brotherhood, where not much light pene<pb type="vol" n="215"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="215"/>trated; and at the
                  end of the service, when the brotherhood was scattered over a large number of
                  chambers for the purpose of reading as well as for the purpose of repeating the
                  service, he would sit in the great common (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κοινόν</foreign>) chapel and cover his head with his book on his knees, while
                  even the book also was covered, and except a small surface only for the purpose of
                  admitting light no part whatever of it was exposed. And thereupon he would open
                  the book and gaze at it, and at once his tears would burst forth, falling down
                  upon his breast; and thus he would sit from morning till the sixth hour,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> with his face covered, and weeping;
                  and he would not turn over a leaf, but generally had the book open at the
                  beatitudes, or the parable of the virgins, or that of the talents, or that of the
                  banquet, or that of the rich man, or any place where the subject was that of
                  threats and judgment; and thenceforth not even if a man was actually speaking to
                  him would be raise his eyes and look upon men outside that book; but men did not
                  see his face (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>) until the bellman
                  sounded the bell,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> nay not even then
                  also; for <pb type="vol" n="216"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="216"/>even during service too he would again stand
                  in this way in the same corner (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γωνία</foreign>) with his
                  head bowed and covered, and after every sentence that came out of his mouth he
                  would utter an expression of praise with ecstasy. And he used to keep silence the
                  whole day, not speaking to men at all, no not even if anyone spoke to him. But, if
                  any kind of occasion called him to speak, he would weep while speaking; and, even
                  if one of the seniors came up to him and said to him, <quote>Wherefore, our
                     father, are you exceedingly mournful, and do not speak and enjoy yourself a
                     little?</quote>, he on his side would thus answer: <quote>Why do you desire a
                        dead man who is dead in his sins and buried in his body to speak? For me whom
                        you see my body is a grave; for, like a rotting corpse in a grave, thus my soul
                        is rotting within it in sin; and henceforth over the dead man there is mourning
                        only and weeping</quote>. And even these words he would say with many sobs. And
                  in the same way his food also which he took at table did not go down <pb type="vol" n="217"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="217"/>into his belly unless mixed with tears; and at night again the
                  same. And so this blessed man used in truth to sorrow disconsolately, like a woman
                  girt in sackcloth for the husband of her tender age in the first days of her
                  mourning. When the time came round when he received clothes, all the blessed men
                  would entreat him to change that old garment of his, and he would not agree; but,
                  when he was forced by the quantity of vermin, for two or three days, while he was
                  seething it in hot water and it was drying, he would consent to put on another;
                  and again, when he was forced by the cold, he would for a few days cover himself
                  with a cloak supplied out of kindness, and would return it to its owner with an
                  apology. And thus he spent his life in this practice of great mourning. And,
                  because he used to see in my case that my soul loved and clave to anyone in whom I
                  saw anything of this kind, and I for my part had not yet subdued the wild impulse
                  of youth, then he would each time take me apart, and open that book, and with
                  tears warn me out of it, saying, <quote>Come, hear, my son, how many secret
                     blessings and promises are guaranteed to the pure and the virgins and the pure
                     in heart, and to boys like you who draw near to the <pb type="vol" n="218"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="218"/>Lord;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> and guard your
                     purity, and keep virginity, which beyond all things has magnified and glorified
                     its possessors; and see moreover what a threat and sentence of weeping and
                     gnashing of teeth, and an immortal worm and unsleeping fire and darkness are
                     threatened against the wicked and the presumptuous and the doers of sin; and
                     fear, and be wary</quote>. And these words again he would speak to me with a
                  flood of tears. But one day I presumed to say to him: <quote>Why, sir, do you tell
                     me to perform acts of righteousness? If I go to do anything, lo! you seniors
                     laugh at us, and say: <quote>If you see a boy going up to heaven, catch hold of
                        his foot</quote>. And what therefore can we do?</quote> But the saint,
                  looking at me and shaking his head, said to me: <quote>Know, my son, that a lion
                     who does not tear the prey in his second year will not afterwards quickly tear
                     it. And know this further, that childhood, like tender wax which receives the
                     impress of that which falls from the ring upon it, so itself also from the
                     beginning receives the impress <pb type="vol" n="219"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="219"/>and the picture of
                     that which is impressed upon it, be it of good things or of evil</quote>. And
                  after these words I said to him: <quote>What, my father, do you command me to do?
                     What will be for my good?</quote> The old man says to me: <quote>Lo!, my son,
                        <persName>Jesus</persName> your Lord tells you here and shows you what is
                        the great and first commandment: <quote>Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with
                           all thine heart, and with all thy strength, and with all thy mind</quote>;
                        and the second which is like it, <quote>Thou shalt love thy neighbour as
                           thyself</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> He has again
                        in his own person shown you humility, and commanded you: <quote>Whoever shall
                           smite thee on thy cheek, turn to him the other also</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> together with the other
                        commandments. These things, O my son, which God himself your Creator taught
                        you, keep and you shall live<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/>
                     </quote>. And thus he would warn me with many words every day; and I, when I
                  should have used the saying of the psalmist against evil, here on the contrary
                  drew it to me, and <quote>as a deaf man heard not</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> The blessed man from the time when he came to us
                  completed nine years in this employment; and so he will receive his Lord <pb type="vol" n="220"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="220"/>with a load of joy, in order that the text may be
                  fulfilled, <quote>They who sow in tears shall reap in joy</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> so that from the time when I myself
                  came to know this old man of abnegation down to his passing away not one moment
                  passed in which he was not sowing the tears of sorrow. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-14">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-14.1" n="2"> The history of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1536">Abbi</persName> the man of abnegation is
                  ended. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 214, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>See ch. 18 and 35.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 214, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>The monastery of John Urtaya (ch. 58). The date must be 522-526 (see
               Introd.)</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 215, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Perhaps 6 P.M.; see p. 204, n. 1., and cf, <title>H. E.</title>, VI, 9,
               where it is said that after the 6th hour fighting-time is past. Probably however he
               is refering to the services and means <hi rend="singleQuotes">from matins till
                  sext</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 215, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Probably for sext.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 218, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>John would probably be from 14 to 18 at the time of A.'s arrival; see
               Introd.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 219, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Matth., XXII, 37-39.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 219, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Id., V, 39.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 219, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>Id., XIX, 17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 219, n. 4</orig>
               </choice>Ps. XXXVIII, 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 220, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ps. CXXVI, 5.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
