<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/808">Simeon the Mountaineer</title>
                <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/807"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/809"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/808.xml -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-16" n="16">
                    <head type="main">Next the Sixteenth History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2097">Simeon</persName> the Mountaineer the
                  Anchorite,</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-16.1" n="1"> This blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2097">Simeon</persName> then used to go about on
                  the mountains like the wild beasts, and these the rugged mountains of towering
                  height with valleys between them which are called the inner
                     <placeName>Karhe</placeName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>
                  and he had no intercourse except that with God, while at every moment he would
                  raise his eyes to heaven, and be lost in ecstatic wonder at the hosts above, how
                  they stand continuously before God without impediment, and that there is no
                  cessation in their song of praise even for a short space. And he would often in my
                  presence say these things: <quote>Wherefore do we wretched men, who were created
                     for the same expression of praise in like manner as these, and to whom a mouth
                     has been given and a tongue and power of speech, cease from the praise of the
                     merciful Creator, and busy ourselves with the vain <pb type="vol" n="230"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="230"/>things of this false and deceitful world? A great thing it is how our heart
                     is sunk and our mind blinded, and we do not consider the bounties of him who
                     created us, and brought us into existence out of nothing, how we, feeble dust
                     of the earth, <quote>live and move and exist</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> how the good Creator gave us the breath of this
                     pure air (<foreign xml:base="grc">άήρ</foreign>) to sustain our life without
                     anxiety, how he put together for us an organ (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όργανον</foreign>) for speech, and a voice and a mouth and lips and a
                     tongue and a palate, how he infused light into the pupils of our eyes, that it
                     might be an informant and a director to the whole body, how again he bestowed
                     hearing in the ears and breath in the nostrils, and understanding in the heart,
                     that by means of its perceptions it might know and discern creation which
                     declares him; and, again, that he always gives aliment also in all varieties
                     for the sustenance of the body, and again to the soul also besides, in
                     accordance with its nature and after the pattern of its airiness, he gave
                     spiritual life according to its spirituality, and again besides these things
                     his grace like a watchful guardian stands carefully over our life by night and
                     by day and delivers and guards us from mishaps and from all detriment that evil
                     things may chance to do, and while this our merciful <pb type="vol" n="231"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="231"/>Creator performs all these gracious acts in relation to us, and gave us all
                     these spiritual and bodily gifts, our wretched heart is sunk in the mire of
                     sin, and neglects to give thanks for these things. For we truly ought not only
                     to thank and praise him who created us as the angels do, but even many times
                     more than these, even as his care for us too is manifestly many times greater
                     than his care for them. And why again do we look at things that are small? But
                     let us regard with greater astonishment the thing that is greater and more
                     marvellous than all, and passes all bounds and all measures, that God himself
                     in his love descended from heaven to earth for our salvation, and sacrificed
                     himself on the cross for our sake, and gave us his living and lifegiving body
                     and blood to eat and to drink, and further promised us in his kindness
                     invisible blessings. And how do we not much more than the angels owe thanks for
                     great kindnesses such as these, which our good Creator and merciful God
                     performed in relation to us?</quote> While this blessed man was saying all
                  these things with ecstatic wonder, he was filling all his hearers with similar
                  wonder, while, his mind being uplifted by ecstatic contemplation of the glories of
                  the heavenly beings, he said many things beside that are greater than these. And
                  the occasion which called him to enter the limits <pb type="vol" n="232"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="232"/>of
                  men's habitation and say these things to them was as follows. In earlier times he
                  used to spend eight months on the mountains among caves and rocks, and for the
                  four severe winter months he would come down to a monastic convent which he knew
                  to be convenient for his occupation, on account of the hardness of the winter and
                  the severity of the snow. But once, while going round from mountain to mountain,
                  he chanced to be on rough mountains near the river <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/82">Euphrates</placeName>, belonging to the
                  village of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2864">ʾbdhyr</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> on the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/82">Euphrates</placeName>, a village which lies
                  and makes a boundary (?) with the territory of <persName>Claudias</persName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> and he saw that, though these
                  mountains were rugged and towering, houses and domestic brood-animals (?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> were scattered over them all, while
                  they were some five miles and some seven, and some as much as eight and ten from
                  the village; because the boundary of that village is so extended (and it is itself
                  also populous) that other hamlets are settled from it within its boundaries. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-16.2" n="2"> The blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2097">Simeon</persName> was amazed to see in
                  what a rugged mountainous district human beings were living, and moreover that
                  they possessed houses <pb type="vol" n="233"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="233"/>and cattle and were settled there
                  in confidence (one being three miles distant from his neighbour, and another five
                  and another two according to chance), and he was also astonished that all the
                  mountains were so full of people; and then, seeing some <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3699">shepherds</persName> at a distance from
                  the houses, he came near and inquired<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> from them the causes of this scattered character of this place of habitation,
                  because there are there not only cattle-sheds such as some men make, but great
                  houses and substantial dwellings. But the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3699">shepherds</persName> would state to him,
                     <quote>We found our fathers living in this way on these mountains; and,
                     inasmuch as we were born on them, lo! we also live on them.</quote> And again
                  he would ask them, <quote>How then, as you live on these mountains, are you able
                     to assemble in God's house, and to hear his word from the holy Scriptures, or
                     to communicate in the mysteries of his body and blood?</quote> But these men,
                  like some wild beasts, upon these words laughed at the blessed man, and they say:
                     <quote>How, blessed sir, does the oblation that a man receives profit him? For
                     what is the oblation?</quote>. When the blessed man heard these words, his
                  bones shook from his fright and his <pb type="vol" n="234"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="234"/>tears gushed out,
                  and he said to them: <quote>Tell me, my sons, are you Christians or Jews?</quote>.
                  But they were indignant at these words, and they say: <quote>O! indeed, blessed
                     man, we are Christians, do not call us Jews.</quote> The blessed man says to
                  them: <quote>And, if you are Christians, how is it that you have mocked at God and
                     said of his living and holy body and blood in which our life and our souls'
                     salvation consists, <quote>What does it profit us?</quote> or <quote>For what
                        is it?</quote>? How is it that you were not frightened to perform with your
                     tongues the acts of pagans and Jews, when you are as you say
                     Christians?</quote>. They, when they saw the awe with which he expressed
                  himself, became afraid themselves also, and they say: <quote>Forgive us, sir, for
                     we have no knowledge.</quote> He says to them: <quote>And have you not heard
                     the Scriptures, my sons?</quote>. They say to him: <quote>From our fathers we
                     have heard; but the Scriptures themselves we have not seen.</quote> Now those
                  who were speaking to the blessed man were as he used to state to us about thirty
                  years old. to them again: <quote>Are you, my sons, only in this state, or are all
                     who are living on these mountains the same?</quote>. They say to him:
                     <quote>Sir, it is not <pb type="vol" n="235"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="235"/>only we who are so, but there
                     are men on these mountains which you see who, unless they have heard from their
                     fathers, who carried them to church and had them baptized, do not know what a
                     church is. And this same thing happens now also to those who have children born
                     to them; on their account they go into a church and have them baptized;
                     otherwise none of us has entered a church since he was born; but we live on
                     these mountains like animals.</quote> The blessed man marvelled and wept, and
                  said to them: <quote>Well have you said <quote>like animals</quote>, my sons. For
                     animals are much better than you; since these have remained as the Creator
                     created them, without changing or being ungrateful to or blaspheming against
                     their Creator; and for this reason they do not come to judgment. But, as for
                     you, God created you in his image and in his likeness, and gave you his body
                     and blood for the life and salvation of your souls, and you have deprived
                     yourselves of eternal life, and have become very wild, surpassing the animals.
                     And now what hope have you toward God? for lo! you are unaware even of what
                     Christianity is.</quote> And, having spoken with them and warned them, he left
                  them and departed. And, being troubled in his thoughts, he would say to himself,
                     <pb type="vol" n="236"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="236"/>as he himself declared, <quote>How is it that these
                     men are like animals on these mountains?</quote>. Then he considered, and he
                  said in his heart as if from God, <quote>Perhaps it was indeed for this reason
                     that God's grace led me to the mountains here, in order that there may be
                     salvation for these souls that are in the darkness of error.</quote> And the
                  blessed man became enthusiastic, saying, <quote>God wishes for the salvation of
                     all these people more than mine. Henceforth I will not withdraw from this
                     place, unless these have been gained for God; since they are bound in error,
                     and are as if they were not Christians. What pagan is there, or what other
                     worshippers of creation, who for so long a period of time would neglect to pay
                     honour to the object of his worship, and would not always worship that which is
                     reckoned by him as God? These men neither worship God like Christians, nor
                     honour something else like pagans; and they are apostates against the one and
                     against the other.</quote> As he was going about, he found a kind of village on
                  the same frontier the name of which was <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2823">Mʿrbnʾ</placeName>; and he resolved to
                  approach this village, and learn what its condition also was. And on approaching
                  he saw in it a little church overshadowed with vines, and he rejoiced, and said:
                     <quote>Lo! here there is a sign of the presence of Christians.</quote>
                        <pb type="vol" n="237"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="237"/>And, when he had come up to it, he went in and saw that
                  it was full of wood and stones and dust; and the blessed man wept bitterly. But,
                  some men from the village having seen an old anchorite enter the church, one of
                  the old men came up to him, and received his blessing; and the blessed man asked
                  him, <quote>Is there a priest here?</quote>. He said to him: <quote>There has not
                     been a priest here during these times.</quote> And he asked him again:
                     <quote>And not even a brother<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> or
                     anyone whatever?</quote>. He said to him, <quote>There is none here.</quote>
                  Again he went on to ask him also, <quote>Where do you receive the
                     oblation?</quote>. He says to him: <quote>If one of us has business and has
                     happened to be present in one of these villages, he receives; if not, no one
                     here has this concern for the oblation.</quote> He says to him: <quote>And
                     wherefore have you no priests?</quote>. He says to him, <quote>It is not our
                     custom.</quote> He says to him: <quote>And how are you Christians, when you do
                     not follow the custom of Christians?</quote>. After conversing with him in this
                  fashion he says to him: <quote>Come let us sweep out and tidy up this church, for
                     I wish to take up my abode in it for a few days.</quote> And they swept and
                  scoured (?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> and tidied. And he said
                  to him: <quote>Gather together for me to-morrow all the souls that are in this
                     hamlet, men and <pb type="vol" n="238"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="238"/>women and children, and small as well
                     as great.</quote> And on hearing about some strange sight that they had never
                  seen they assembled together before him in the morning; and he conversed with them
                  in words of admonition, and said to them: <quote>Wherefore, O men, do you hold
                     your lives in contempt and take no thought for the salvation of your souls?
                     Wherefore, when God formed us in his image, do we on our part live animal lives
                     outside the orderliness of men? Know you not that you are men, and not animals?
                     know you not that even the animals have a greater blessing than you, they who
                     are not destined to rise, nor yet to enter the judgment of justice? Know you
                     not that the dread judgment of God's justice is at hand? and know you not that
                     you are destined to stand before the dread tribunal (<foreign xml:lang="grc">βήμα</foreign>) of God? Wherefore then do you make yourselves like the
                     animals on the mountains? and wherefore are you like them delivered
                     indiscriminately to death, in that you hold aloof from hearing God's word, and
                     are moreover deprived of the communion of the venerated body and blood of God,
                     and this is not reckoned by you as anything?</quote>. While the blessed man was
                  repeating such words to them, like some irrational animal, which when a man speaks
                     <pb type="vol" n="239"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="239"/>to it in order that it may be instructed only hears
                  and looks at him, so they also heard what he was speaking, and looked at him in
                  astonishment, and they had nothing to say. But he again said to them: <quote>Do
                     you not speak?</quote>. They said to him: <quote>What, sir, can we say to you?
                     There is no one to say anything to us or teach us: and this which you say has
                     never reached our ears; since we do not know the Scriptures.</quote> He says to
                  them: <quote>know you not that our <persName>Lord Jesus Christ</persName> came
                     down from heaven, and clothed himself in our body from a Virgin for our
                     salvation, and consorted with men as a man? are you aware of these things, or
                     not?</quote>. The old men among them say to him: <quote>Yes, sir, we hear the
                     things</quote>. He says to them <quote>Do you hear only without knowing the
                     truth? Know you not moreover that God suffered for our sake, and was suspended
                     on the cross, and was fastened with nails and his side was pierced by a lance
                     and blood and water flowed from him as a propitiation for men, and that he died
                     and by his death slew our death, and rose after three days, it is written and
                     raised us with him, having trodden the road and shown us the resurrection that
                     shall be ours, and before he suffered broke his body and blood<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> in an upper room and <pb type="vol" n="240"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="240"/>blessed it and gave it to his disciples and said, <quote>This
                        is my body that is broken on behalf of the life of the world for the
                        forgiveness of sins</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/>
                     and again that he said before, <quote>Everyone who eateth my body and drinketh
                        my blood, he abideth in me and I in him, and I will raise him at the last
                        day</quote>?<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> How then, when
                     you have heard all these things and know them, as you say, do you treat them
                     with contempt and pay no regard to your souls' life, and remain deprived of the
                     word of life in the holy Scriptures, and hold aloof from the communion of
                        <persName>Christ</persName>'s body and blood, and do not consider that any
                     loss falls upon you from this, whereas you suffer not loss of some small thing,
                     but utter destruction of your souls?</quote>. They said to him: <quote>And
                     what, sir, can we do?</quote>. But he laid a kind of penance upon them all,
                  admonishing them and explaining to them, <quote>Because your souls are waste and
                     barren by reason of your neglect, like soil that is barren on account of the
                     length of time during which thorns and briars have been springing up in it, so
                     that a man who wishes to till it first plucks up these thorns and burns them,
                     and then puts in his seed, so do you also go and fast this week and and pray,
                     and <pb type="vol" n="241"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="241"/>break bread on the first day of the week, and
                     bring it me; and all of you, great and small, meet together, and come and
                     present yourselves</quote>. And they consented to his proposal, and went and
                  fasted, and came. He says to them: <quote>Wherefore have your sons not been made
                     sons of the covenant,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> and been
                     instructed and placed in this church, and been making you hear God's
                     word?</quote>. They say to him: <quote>Sir, they have not time to leave the
                     goats and learn anything</quote>. The blessed man, marvelling at the people's
                  simpleness and carelessness, made the oblation, and communicated them; and then
                  they opened their mouth, and began to give thanks to God who sent him to them;
                  while he laid an injunction upon them that they should meet together every first
                  day of the week, keeping themselves from blasphemy and from fornication, and from
                  murder; because none of them reckoned the blood of a man, either of his neighbour
                  or of a stranger, as worth one locust, and there was none to require it; but the
                  blessed man made an inquiry into these things, and everyone in whose case he
                  learned that this thing had taken place he deprived of Christian fellowship, and
                  they were set apart as pagans and Jews. And then they began to feel a little fear,
                  both of God and of the blessed man himself, while he continued sending and
                  fetching all who were on the <pb type="vol" n="242"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="242"/>mountains to the house, and
                  converting them afresh, as if from paganism; and thus he used to gather them all
                  together like wild animals. After a short time, when he had gained information
                  about the children of each one of them, who had male children and who female, and
                  how many each of them had, while they were unaware of his purpose, what he
                  intended to do, he gave the order <quote>Next first day of the week see that no
                     persons stay away from the congregation</quote>; and he sent to the mountains,
                  saying, <quote>Let the little children also be present in the
                  congregation</quote>. When they assembled and came according to his instructions
                  (since they were indeed afraid of him), he provided himself with a razor, both
                  himself and a certain man who was in the secret who knew them well, and, when all
                  had received the oblation, he said to them: <quote>Allow all the little ones to
                     receive a present<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> to-day, and we
                     will bless them and speak with them, and they shall come; since to these from
                     to-day someone must always speak the word of God, that thus they may remember
                     it as long as they live; and do you go everyone in peace</quote>. And they
                  believed it, and went away, having induced the little ones to remain by these
                  words, <quote>You will receive presents, and we will mix them for you.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> Remain all of you</quote>. Then
                  they all remained, about ninety, males and <pb type="vol" n="243"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="243"/>females. And
                  he shut the doors, and came up and separated and arranged them with the help of
                  the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3701">man</persName>man who knew
                  them, separating one in three, and the females moreover on the same system;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> and, if there were two females and
                  one male, he would take one of the former; and so also with the males too, and if
                  again there were two,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> he would in
                  the same way take one of them; and he separated thirty of them and set them on one
                  side, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3700">eighteen boys, and twelve
                     girls</persName>; and the rest he led away and shut up in another room, lest
                  they should go and report what had happened. And he brought them up before the
                  altar, and shut the inner and outer doors, and made a prayer. over them, and the
                  two began to tonsure them, soothing them with blandishments; and of them some
                  wept, and some were silent; and thus they shaved <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3700">them boys and girls</persName> alike. And
                  then he released the first lot who had been separated and not tonsured, having
                  shown them their companions, that they might report to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3702">their parents</persName> what had
                  happened, and they might come, and he might speak with them, and might appease
                  those who were troublesome. When the news arrived, the women assembled with
                  lamentations, crying, <quote>Alas! what has taken place and what has befallen
                     us?</quote>. And some were binding themselves under a curse, saying, <quote>My
                     son shall not <pb type="vol" n="244"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="244"/>again be shaven, and the name
                        <quote>son of the covenant</quote> shall not again be called over
                     him</quote>. And some of them from the rage of their souls even betook
                  themselves to abuse of the blessed man; and so also the men. But he held his
                  tongue, and he continues laughing till their wrath is pacified; and some of them
                  acquiesced in what they had done, saying, <quote>Our Lord's will be done</quote>,
                  and, <quote>We would it were so</quote>. But, when two of them stubbornly stood
                  out, he exhorted and admonished them, and said to them: <quote>They are yours, my
                     sons; they are not going to destruction; they are being presented to
                        <persName>Christ</persName>, while they are yours</quote>. But they showed
                  violent indignation, saying, <quote>We will not present one of them to
                        <persName>Christ</persName>
                        </quote>. But he testified to them, saying,
                     <quote>I for my part have marked out this plot in <persName>Christ</persName>'s
                     name to his glory. Beware what you are doing. I am free from sin. He who
                     separates a soul from it and takes it out that he may bring it back to the
                     world, <persName>Christ</persName>
                            <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> will not resign that soul in this bodily life, because it is his and has
                     been marked in his name. I for my part have testified to you; you know</quote>.
                  But they came up, and laid their hands upon them and dragged them away and removed
                  them, blaspheming. The blessed man says to them: <quote>Have mercy upon your
                     souls, my sons, and do not be obstinate and deprive <pb type="vol" n="245"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="245"/>yourselves of your children, and incur blame</quote>. They said: <quote>Let
                     us be deprived this evening and we will not make our children
                     shavelings</quote>. He says to them: <quote>Beware, for, if you take them away,
                     I for my part have testified, and I testify again, that neither of them will
                     reach next first day of the week in this bodily life</quote>. They, when they
                  heard it, jeered at the blessed man, saying: <quote>If you think that your curses
                     are so well heard, go and curse these Huns who are coming and making havoc of
                        creation,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/> and let them
                     die.</quote> And so they took their <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3602">children</persName> away in good health,
                  and went off; and within three days both of them were smitten and died. Then the
                  terror of the blessed man fell upon everyone, when the power of his word and of
                  his prayer upon those men was seen; and they also repented, and they went and fell
                  down before him, weeping and saying, <quote>We have been presumptuous, sir,
                     forgive us; lest you curse us also and we die</quote>. Then he said to them:
                     <quote>I, my sons, did not curse these either (far be it!); but God took them
                     away, that he might chastise you yourselves for your presumption against his
                     word; since it was not in our name, but in the name of God himself and in his
                     word that I marked them. And now <pb type="vol" n="246"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="246"/>go repent and pray
                     to God that he will forgive you, lest you also perish as well</quote>. And they
                  in fear and entreating him departed. And from that time among all of them great
                  and low, if the old man wished to tonsure anyone, there was none who presumed to
                  speak; and thenceforth whoever pleased him he would mark and take away without
                  impediment. But for those who had been tonsured he made tablets for writing, and
                  wrote for them; and thus he would thenceforth frequently sit with patience as in a
                  school (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχόλη</foreign>), and would teach them, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3700">boys and girls</persName> together. And
                  down to the time when they reached an age at which they might receive harm from
                  one another, within four or five years, they learned the psalms and the
                  Scriptures; and thus thenceforward loud choirs were to be heard at the service,
                  and all these mountains also had been brought into subjection, and they trembled
                  to commit any breach of order, lest the old man should hear it and separate them
                  from the fellowship of men, or that<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/>
                  he should curse them. And accordingly twenty-six years passed while he was there,
                  and he was still in this life, and we were always receiving his blessing, and were
                  also in intercourse with him;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/> and
                  we used to learn from him about the <pb type="vol" n="247"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="247"/>uncivilized
                  character of that people and about their subjugation and about all the torments
                  that they had inflicted on him, when he was now old and decrepit, and these
                  disciples of his also had become grown women and men, and they were now becoming
                  readers and daughters of the covenant, and they were themselves teaching others
                  also as well. And accordingly the blessed man's name had gone out over all that
                  country, and he was a law (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμος</foreign>) and a judge of
                  the country; and every matter that was in need of reform was referred to him. And
                  now, because feebleness and old age had overtaken him, he was no longer able to
                  retire to the mountains outside according to his custom, but he used to carry out
                  his labour there in the same country in his cell, and he had also gained
                  possession of these men; and he was as a spiritual father to all of them, having
                  also converted them from the error of their apostasy to proper rules of life both
                  bodily and spiritual. </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-16">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-16.1" n="3"> The history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2097">Simeon</persName> the anchorite the
                  mountaineer is ended. </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 229, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. <hi rend="singleQuotes">whirlwinds</hi>; or perh. vocalize as <hi rend="singleQuotes">Krahe</hi> (bald). I do not know whence V. D. and L. get the
               rendering <hi rend="singleQuotes">vertebrae</hi>. Cf. <title>Anecd. Syr.</title>, II,
               298, l. 3, and <title>H. E.</title>, VI, 9. From these passages we see that they were
               near Melitene, but E. of the Euphrates.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 230, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Acts, XVII, 28.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 232, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See Mich., p. 649, 654.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 232, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Claudias lay W. of the Euphrates, which must have been the boundary. If the
               text is right, the meaning must be that the village territory lay on the river, and
               therefore at the extreme limit of the province.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 232, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Or, with V. D. and L.'s emendation, <hi rend="singleQuotes">cattle-sheds</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 233, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 39, n. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 237, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. a lay monk.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 237, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>No such meaning of is known to the lexicons.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 239, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 240, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., XXVI, 28; I Cor., XI, 24.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 240, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>John, VI, 54, 56.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 241, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I. e. received the first tonsure for orders or monasticism.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 242, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">blessing</hi>. The ambiguity is perh.
               intentional.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 242, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>It is assumed that the presents will be something to eat or drink.</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 243, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>The meaning clearly is that he took the threes from boys and girls
               indiscriminately.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 243, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. males.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 244, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 245, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Probably therefore these things in 515 (see p. 19, n. 2). The invasion of
               531/2 (p. 78, n. 2) is too late, for it would bring his death to 557, 17 years after
               J. left the East; see below, and p. 246, n. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 246, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 246, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>This seems to mean that he died 26 years after the beginning of his
               missionary life. In this case his death must be placed circ. 541.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
