<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/809">A Poor One</title>
                <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/808"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/810"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/809.xml -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-17" n="17">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-17">
                    <head type="main">Next the Seventeenth History Which Is That of One Of The Saints Who Would Not
                  Consent to State His Name, Except Only ‘<persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1988">Poor Man</persName>’.</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-17.1" n="1"> When therefore I consider the degeneracy of our times and
                  the confusion of our days, I marvel greatly to think how it is that the prophetic,
                  that is divine, saying does not rise into our mind, which says in a voice of
                  thunder to our error, <quote>Lo! the righteous hath perished and there is none
                     that taketh it to his heart, and saintly men are gathered and no heed is
                     given</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> If we truly
                  consider this, it has received accomplishment in our times, since all the great
                  pillars whom we have seen, who by means of theirj continual supplication and
                  petition bore up the tottering house of the world, have been gathered and passed
                  from the confusions of this life, and those again whose great modes of life and
                  mighty labours had been laid like huge base-stones at the foundations of the world
                  have been collected and removed from among us as it is written <quote>and there is
                     none that heedeth</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> For
                  this <pb type="vol" n="249"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="249"/>reason the whole habitable world of men has been
                  shaken and tottered and its structure has been loosened; and it has so to speak
                  already begun to fall; and there is none who takes note of these things and lays
                  them to his heart, in order that the passage of sacred song may be fulfilled upon
                  us which says, <quote>The Lord looked out from heaven upon men, to see if there
                     were any man that was understanding and sought God, and all had together gone
                     astray and become reprobate, and there was not even one who was doing what is
                     good</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> For, having taken
                  upon ourselves to trace, even if obscurely, a picture of the marvellous beauties
                  of the saints whom I met in the times of my boyhood and leave it for the general
                  benefit, if only to this remnant who have been left in our days, I am reduced to
                  marvelling greatly in my thoughts how it is that all these marvellous and
                  giant-like men have been collected like clear pure wine, and the world has been
                  reduced to disgusting dregs turbid with evil matter, and we lay not these things
                  to our heart. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-17.2" n="2"> Once, when we were in the holy <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2736">convent</placeName> adjoining the city of
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2735">Amida</placeName>, that is that
                  which is called the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2736">convent</placeName> of the holy Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John</persName>, as has been recorded by us
                  in one of the foregoing histories,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/>
                  since all these <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2736">convents</placeName>
                        <pb type="vol" n="250"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="250"/>surpassed everyone in devotion to hospitality, and were
                  fervent in love toward their brothers, therefore on account of the report of their
                  open-handedness men used to repair from all quarters to the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2736">convents</placeName> round the city,
                  because their zeal was in truth kindled by the love of God, so that they did not
                  in the case of any one of their brothers who came to them hold him to be merely a
                  man of flesh, but through a mean and poor body he appeared in their eyes as God
                  himself who became flesh, and so they were eager to serve and refresh and wash and
                  honour as it were <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, that everyone might share in
                  anything that might result through the blessing of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1988">the man</persName> whoever he were; and
                  great and small were alike so devoted that, if a stranger were in one of these
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2736">convents</placeName> a year and
                  two years and ten years and twenty and all the days of his life, there was no one
                  who would open his mouth and in any way give him to understand that he was not as
                  one of the old inmates; and so in the matter of clothing and in the whole supply
                  of necessities he was brought forward with the priests and before the whole of the
                  brotherhood; things which are objects of great admiration even down to the present
                  time. While they were showing fervour in these things every day, one day a certain
                  old man, poor and a stranger, came to the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2736">convent</placeName>
                        <pb type="vol" n="251"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="251"/>in which I myself was; and, when he had been questioned
                  with regard to h the faith and made a defence, and had come in at the hour of
                  vespers at the end of the service, they required him according to the custom
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμος</foreign>) which they followed to sit at the
                  seniors' table, that is the archimandrite's; and he on hearing this fell on his
                  face in entreaty, saying: <quote>Excuse me, my fathers, for
                        <persName>Christ</persName>'s sake; because I am a <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1988">poor man</persName>, and of this I am
                     not worthy</quote>. But he was a man with sparse hair and long beard; and so
                  many with the archimandrite himself among them rose to seat him at that table; and
                  he with his face cleaving to the ground entreated: <quote>Do me a favour, sir, and
                     allow me to sit at one of the other tables</quote>. And the archimandrite,
                  seeing his wish, said: <quote>Let him do what he likes</quote>; and so he
                  consented to rise from the ground. And, as if by the grace of God, he directed his
                  steps to the table at which I was sitting; and that though it was in the middle,
                  and we were sitting with other tables on both sides of us. And we all rose and
                  received that old man gladly and sat down. When a dish of cooked food had been set
                  on the table, the head of the table was requesting him to pronounce the blessing;
                  and he again continued making request saying, <quote>Excuse me</quote>; and he
                  strongly urged him, and he would not agree; and we were astonished at the
                  resistance which that old man made by <pb type="vol" n="252"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="252"/>reason of his
                  humility. And, every time that the blessed man reached out a spoon, his eye was
                  furtively and gradually raised upward, and his lips moved, as if he were making a
                  little sign; and thus regularly, whenever a morsel of food entered his mouth, a
                  sign of thanksgiving came up from his heart by the muttering of his lips and the
                  motion of his eyes. And, when the order was given by the archimandrite that the
                  wine and water should go round (since this was the custom (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμος</foreign>) that the wine and water should go round three times a week
                  besides the first day of the week<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/>),
                  and, when the steward came and the old man received one cup like everyone else,
                  since it was diluted with cold water, and one cup each only would be rapidly
                  carried round and collected, and everyone pronounced a blessing and drank, and
                  deposited the cup in its place, yet the blessed man would drink a sip at a time as
                  if it were hot and one could not drink, and he could not be induced to drink one
                  sip together with the next, but this is how he divided that cup, into as many sips
                  as the times that it pleased him to offer praise over it; and, though it was a
                  small cup, he divided it into more than a hundred sips. When the head of the table
                  saw it, he said: <quote>Perhaps the old man would like to drink it with hot water,
                     and <pb type="vol" n="253"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="253"/>for this reason he was afraid of the
                  cold</quote>; and he said to him: <quote>Do you wish us to bring you hot water,
                     our father?</quote>. He says,
                     <quote>No, excuse me. Whether it is cold or hot, this is my habit, to drink a
                     little at a time</quote>. When we were sitting, we asked the old man,
                     <quote>Whence, sir, does your holiness come?</quote>. But he, as if he were now
                  occupied in eating, silently bent his head down toward us, and was silent; and
                  again a second and a third time; and then at last he made this answer:
                     <quote>Excuse me, my fathers, I am hungry and need to eat</quote>. And then we
                  understood the blessed man's intention, and left him alone. And, when we had eaten
                  and the old man was looking down and privily signalling upward, when we had spoken
                  with him once and twice and thrice, and had asked him <quote>Whence are
                     you?</quote>, his tears suddenly gushed out; and when he had put force upon
                  himself to refrain and could not, he bowed his face down upon his knees, and
                  covered his head; and so he with difficulty constrained himself, and stayed his
                  sobs. And so we rose from the table, the old man standing in the midst with his
                  head covered; and, when we had offered praise over the tables, and the old man had
                  been washed according to custom (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμος</foreign>), a rug
                  was prepared for him in the chapel. And when he saw it he continued making request
                  and saying, <quote>Because I am feeble and weary, and cannot <pb type="vol" n="254"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="254"/>rise for service, for God's sake lay the bed for me outside in some
                     corner (ye)yte)</quote>. Then, lest he should really be troubled by the
                  service, they laid it for him as he asked. And, as there were some blessed men who
                  were eager to investigate such things, they observed the old man in order to
                  discover his intention. But he immediately fell upon his rug as if he had fallen
                  asleep; and, when everyone's voice had ceased and they had been gathered to their
                  beds, the blessed man turned upon his face on his rug, and he knelt and began to
                  weep, from the evening right on till the nocturns bell, not being aware that
                  anyone was aware of what he was doing, though those who were observing him had
                  become weary and been sunk in sleep two and three times, and they were astounded
                  to find that saint thus engaged down to the bell; but, when the bellman sounded
                  the bell, he covered himself like an infirm man and lay down, until the end of the
                  service; and then the same again until the morning, though not as he had done in
                  the evening, but with precautions against those who were looking after the land
                  (?) after service<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> and against those
                  who were learning the Psalms. But in the morning he continued requesting to be
                  dismissed and go; and the archi<pb type="vol" n="255"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="255"/>mandrite would not let
                  him, saying, <quote>Rest, our father, for five days and bless us, and then you
                     shall go</quote>. And the old man, having been detained, went out into the
                  garden to walk; and I, having learned these things about him from those who had
                  been watching him, went out after him; and he saw me, and stopped. And I,
                  beginning to enter into conversation with him, said to him: <quote>Wherefore, our
                     father, did you conceal from us what kind of man you are, and from what
                        <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2736">convent</placeName> you
                     come?</quote>. But on his side his tears at once gushed forth again, and he was
                  silent. But I said to him: <quote>If you are a Christian and he's bondman, I will
                     not let you depart, unless you have informed me wherefore last evening and now
                     you wept at this question. I have presumed, if you are God's bondman, to adjure
                     you by him whom you serve, inform me about this and also about your modes of
                     life for the sake of my soul's salvation</quote>. But the blessed man was
                  annoyed and indignant, saying: <quote>For such an adjuration there was no
                     need</quote>. And I on my side said: <quote>I made an adjuration that I might
                     profit, while you do not lose</quote>. Then the old man laid an injunction upon
                  me with an oath that, until three years had passed, no word should come out of my
                  mouth of what he would say to
                  me<!--</quote> I cannot figure out what quote is closed here. -->; and he said:
                     <quote>I, my son, have to-day spent thirty years in this discipline; and during
                     these years God will <pb type="vol" n="256"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="256"/>not judge me for having opened
                     my mouth over food which is derived from God's gift without stretching my
                     thoughts to give praise for his bounty. I hope in his name that I shall not be
                     condemned for having stretched forth my hand to my mouth without every time
                     that I stretched it forth similarly stretching forth my tongue to praise and my
                     mind to prayer on behalf of those who labour and sweat and toil to supply my
                     need. I shall not be despised by the Giver of our good things for having put a
                     vessel to my lips to drink water or wine, and drunk two consecutive sips
                     without giving thanks to the Creator of it and interceding for those who have
                     extended to me a share in their gift. And after these things last evening you
                     were urging me to neglect such rendering of thanks to my Benefactor as my
                     little strength is able to perform, and engage in vain talk. Or know you not
                     that it was God's bounty that we were eating, with the sins of men<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> moreover that stain us? And how
                     can it be, my son, that God will not be angry with us and deliver us to the
                     judgment of torments when we eat his bounty and instead of rendering thanks
                     engage in frivolous talk, and further, instead of prayers for the men the sweat
                     of whose labour we are eating, <pb type="vol" n="257"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="257"/>that<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> we should sit and enjoy ourselves
                     in idle talk? And, because you adjured me by God, lo! these are the reasons for
                     which last evening and now my sobs came up, since I said: <quote>How then
                           (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρα</foreign>) can the heart of a man who is fed
                        by God's bounty and mens' sin not tremble to emit words in any other kind of
                        conversation beyond that of thanks and prayer on behalf of the needy and
                        remembrance of those who are working and suffering hardship and distress and
                        want and need, while he is sitting thus without care and without fear, and
                        concerning himself with frivolous stories?</quote>
                        </quote>. I on hearing
                  these things from that old man did the only thing that was proper for me to do, I
                  bowed my face to the ground, marvelling at this extraordinary man and fixing my
                  gaze on him, and further also too how<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> in the evening at table he would not consent to take even two sips only
                  together. And such is our presumptuous impudence that I thought to myself while I
                  was standing, <quote>This man is a solitary, and further also he is his own
                     master, and there is none to command him, and it is easy for him; and moreover
                     neither is he pressed by matters of the obligation of domestic business; and
                     therefore he can observe this amazing canon (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κανών</foreign>). But how are we able to <pb type="vol" n="258"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="258"/>do
                     so?</quote>. But, while I on my part was secretly tracing these things in my
                  thoughts, that spiritual man openly told me them all as if he had written out my
                  thought and come to know it, saying: <quote>I have come to know what the evil one
                     has caused to creep into your mind, in order to deprive you of profit</quote>,
                  while he repeated everything to me as I had thought it. And then, when not only
                  fear but astonishment also as well fell upon me, I confessed that that was what I
                  had thought. But he sighed the more, saying: <quote>On account of these things, my
                     son, Christianity has been corrupted, and the ordinances of religion have been
                     thrown into confusion. If you are sitting at table, and enjoying the gifts of
                     the Giver, how can you bring in affairs of business and cheat God's kindness of
                     its due for the sake of his gifts? Or is not then (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρα</foreign>) the day sufficient for you for your business with its hours
                     and its moments, but at the moment at which one business only is required,
                     thanksgiving, are you on your part giving attention to stories? (and would they
                     were matters of business as you say; but they are actually detriments, and not
                     matters of business) and all the more since it is indeed no trouble to you,
                     since, while the outer man is feeding on his own food, it is easy, if you wish,
                     for the hidden man to nourish himself with his, unless conversa<pb type="vol" n="259"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="259"/>tion be unfairly brought in and cheat him of his due</quote>. When
                  the holy old man had spoken all these words, I began to request him to explain his
                  other modes of life to me. Then he cut me short, saying: <quote>On one point on
                     which you begged and pressed and adjured me you have heard me speak. Take a
                     short answer. If you repeat another word to me, I will not eat bread within
                     twenty miles of this city. But go and beware, and observe your promise, and
                     pray for me</quote>. And, understanding these things, that it was on account of
                  the fear of robbers that the spiritual merchant feared to show his riches, I fell
                  down before him and besought him to forgive me. And thus he departed and went away
                  after two days, without having consented to tell us his name or anything about the
                  other modes of life. And I have remained down to the present time lost in
                  admiration of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1988">the man</persName> of
                  God at all seasons. </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-17">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-17.1" n="3"> The history of one of the saints who would not consent to
                  state his name is ended. </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 248, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Is., LVII, 1.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 249, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. XIV, 2, 3.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 249, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ch. 13 (p. 197). As the monastery was then at Amida and John was in it, the
               date is 530-536 (see Introd.).</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 252, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">the first day of the week included</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 254, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>There seems to be something wrong here, since they could not look after the
               land at night and means 'perform' not 'look after'.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 256, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Cf. p. 175, l. 13.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 257, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 257, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
