<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/811">Zachariah</title>
            <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/810"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/812"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/811.xml -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-19" n="19">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-19">
               <head type="main">Next the Nineteenth History, of a Certain Old Man Whose Name Was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2153">Zacharias</persName>
               </head>
               <ab xml:id="section-19.1" n="1"> This holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2153">Zacharias</persName> was in one of the great convents; to which same convent I
                  used often to repair on account of the pre-eminently great modes of life of
                  certain saints in it, and I had much intercourse with this old man, while he on
                  his part made this his concern to shun intercourse with men, being a man who had
                  one intercourse only. This man therefore, when I used to entreat him, <quote>Our
                     father, let me not be deprived of the profit and gain that is acquired through
                     you, because it is written <quote>He who soweth receiveth wages, even if the
                        earth disappoint</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>
                     but, as for the saint, when he heard these things, his tears would gush forth
                     with sobs, so that for a whojohle hour would be putting constraint upon himself
                     to be silent, and was scarcely able to do so; and again he would cease and bow
                     his head in
                     silence.</quote>
                  <!-- This is not in translation but is required to make sense of the quotations. -->
                  And again I on my side would entreat him to give me the favour of his conversation
                  (for it was not his habit to converse on the spur of the moment with anyone). <pb type="vol" n="267"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="267"/>But on my pressing the blessed man, he said to me with
                  sighs: <quote>Why, my son, do you require me to speak? Lo you see that
                     Christianity has vanished from the earth, and religion has been forgotten, and
                     vanity and error have prevailed. And now what have we to speak, except to weep
                     for the decadence of our generation (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>),
                     since even we, who are in name Christians, enjoy the shelter only of this name,
                     while all the ordinances of Christianity are far from us? And now suffer me to
                     weep for my life, and pray for me</quote>. And again I said: <quote>How can we
                        live,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> our father?</quote>.
                  But he said: <quote>If you seek to live, lo! he into whose hands you will fall
                     teaches you. If you do not listen to him, why do you weary the piece of dust
                     your fellow-slave by superfluous talking?</quote> But, after I had pressed him
                  with many questions which I was asking him, he turned round and put his hand to
                  his mouth, and stealthily took a stone out of his mouth and dropped it into his
                  bosom; and he began thenceforth to speak easily with me without any impediment in
                  his tongue; while previously his words had been uttered with difficulty, and I on
                  my part had been putting this to the account of old age or ascribing it to a <pb type="vol" n="268"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="268"/>stammer, by one of which causes the old man's tongue was
                  restrained. But, when he suddenly conversed easily with me with many plain words,
                  I marvelled in myself and was thinking, <quote>What has happened to the old man?
                     for lo! during the space of three years<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> that I have been in intercourse with him he was a stammerer and slow
                     of speech, and in this hour the fastening of his tongue has been loosened and
                     he has spoken easily.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> And,
                     though he spoke many words with me in the way of admonition and caution, and
                     further on the subject of the end and the future judgment, which was the matter
                     on which my mind was above all things intent, I fell on my face entreating the
                     old man not to hide from me the reason of his previous and his present
                     demeanour; while I had moreover often seen an emblem of a thick thread
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νήμα</foreign>) with three knots tied on it and
                     tied to the palm of his left hand, which had sunk into his hand and was level
                     with the flesh, and, whenever I asked him, he used to tell me that it was a
                     case of disease; and about that also I continued inquiring of him with much
                     entreaty and violent
                     adjurations.</quote>
                  <!-- This is not in the translation but is required to make sense of the quotation marks. -->
                  But the saint took hold of me and raised me up, while he also repeated to me <pb type="vol" n="269"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="269"/>this saying from the gospel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">εύαγγέλιον</foreign>): <quote>The kingdom of God hath been suffering violence
                     from the days of John the Baptist and down to the present time, and violent men
                     seize it</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> But, when I
                  again continued to entreat him, he said to me: <quote>Since I have seen that you
                     are eager to learn about the character of virtue and the life of the soul, I
                     will not deprive you of what you wish; and this very consideration it is which
                     from the beginning constrained me to devote so much time to conversing with
                     you, in order that I might not be condemned on the charge of churlishness; and,
                     if, our brother, you count all the days of this year, my conversation that I
                     have held with men during the whole year has not reached the total of to-day's
                     conversation; since I myself am a sinner, who am not worthy that my mouth
                     should be opened and speak</quote>. Then he put his hand into his bosom, and
                  brought out a round river-pebble, white and shining, and showed it me, saying,
                  <quote>Since I have seen, my son, that you are eager to benefit yourself, lo!
                     this is what prevented me from speaking</quote>. But I said: <quote>And tell
                        me, our father, what benefit is derived from this stone. If we wish to be
                        silent, are we not silent <pb type="vol" n="270"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="270"/>without a stone?</quote> He
                  said to me: <quote>One who is alone and whom Satan leaves to himself can do so;
                     but in the case of one who is among many occasions must necessarily call and
                     speech come, however much guard a man keep over himself, because our will is
                     bound to the yoke of forgetfulness. And for this reason I have closed my mouth
                     with this stone, lest my tongue with or against my will cause me to slip; while
                     God knows that to-day this stone has been five years in my mouth without any
                     person being aware of it except a few who are in this convent who have adopted
                     this plan. And, for you, who have learnt it, I shall stand with you before God,
                     if men learn this during the days of my life. And, that you may not think that
                     I alone have adopted this practice, there are now fifteen persons (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>) in this monastery who have stones placed
                     in their mouths, that they may be trained to silence, and not slip in
                     speech</quote>. While marvelling at this, I made request to him about the
                  emblem on his hand also. He said to me: <quote>Now that I have laid an injunction
                     upon you, my son, listen. This emblem I had formerly tied to my neck; but,
                     because it was visible to many, I undid it, and tied it to my <pb type="vol" n="271"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="271"/>hand instead of my neck. Like the frontier which Jacob and Laban
                     set up and said, <quote>Thou shalt not pass this heap against me, and I again
                        will not pass it against thee</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> so I set this emblem on my neck, between falsehood
                     and wrath, the ministers of which are ministers of Satan, and not of God; and I
                     made a decree for my soul that, whenever it saw this frontier, it should not
                     allow wrath to enter from without, and, if it should be stirred up from within,
                     that it should again not pass this frontier to go outside, and falsehood again
                     should never go out from within. But these knots of the emblem I have put there
                     for private observation; and, of these three knots, one, the first, I have put
                     there as a guardian of my thoughts, lest they dissipate themselves in vain
                     things, and that, if error gain dominion over my mind, and it be suddenly
                     captured and dissipated by the sight of an object, I may remember my soul and
                     turn to God; and the second again is guardian of the remembrance of God, that,
                     as it does not depart thence, neither may my intellect also depart from the
                     remembrance of its Creator; and, if again the evil of error gain dominion over
                     and take possession of my intellect, when I see this <pb type="vol" n="272"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="272"/>object, I may suddenly turn myself and cry to God to deliver me from error;
                     and the third is a symbol of remembrance to keep the commandments of him who
                     said, <quote>If ye love me, keep my commandments</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> I know, my son, that these things are to many
                     folly, and lead them to deplorable laughter; but to me they are very useful,
                     and they are to me the irons of my service, but they are not manifest to
                     anyone. Mark that I have testified against you before God</quote>. But I, being
                  astounded at the old man's thoughts, and the secret ordinances of virtue that he
                  had stamped upon his soul, refrained also from repeating these things until his
                  departure, for eight years, while many miracles were also wrought through his
                  prayer and through the repository of his bones. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-19">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-19.1" n="2"> The history of a certain old man whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2153">Zacharias</persName> is ended. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 266, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>John, IV, 36(?). The sentence here breaks off, and the sense is completed
               differently.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 267, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sc. be <hi rend="singleQuotes">saved</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 268, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>B <hi rend="singleQuotes">hours</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 268, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Mark, VII, 34.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 269, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Matth., XI, 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 271, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Gen.,XXXI, 52.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 272, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>John, XIV, 15.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
