<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/812">A Monk</title>
                <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/811"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/813"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/812.xml -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-20" n="20">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-20">
                    <head type="main">Next the Twentieth History, of a Certain Brother From the Same Convent in Which
                  This Holy Old Man <persName>Zacharias</persName> Was Living, and About the
                  Beginning of Sound Training</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-20.1" n="1"> Since therefore I was always constantly going to that
                  convent, on account of the character of the old man's virtue, and that of all the
                  other saints in it, many of that Christ-loving brotherhood, as if they supposed of
                  us that we were something, used to come and make revelations about their thoughts,
                  and tell of the thoughts with which they had to contend (?); and such answer would
                  be made to each one of them as Grace supplied. And thus consolation derived from
                  conversation was gained by many; and thus they would rejoice and cause one another
                  to think that we, as a person raised above passions, were giving them consolation.
                  One day a certain brother,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> who
                  himself also possessed such great pre-eminence of character that the period during
                  which the whole of the sole of his foot was lying and resting on the ground during
                  the hour of service was reckoned by him as sin (<quote>I have removed myself from
                        <pb type="vol" n="274"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="274"/>fervour toward God</quote>); so that it was
                  impossible for anyone to see him (and neither did this man so act in common with
                  all, but specially<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/>) without his
                  eyes extended towards heaven, his soul also being in this way drawn upward with
                  his body, so that, whenever anyone observed the soles of his feet, he would see
                  him with his heels always raised, and moving up and down, so that in this way his
                  soul was extended upwards, and at one moment he would stand upon the very tips of
                  his toes, as if he were in the act of ascending, and at another moment, when his
                  toes were tired, he would let his soles drop, and again raise them, and so all the
                  service; so that, if barbarians<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/>
                  came in among them, he would be unaware of them and would not lower the gaze of
                  his eyes from heaven; insomuch that I, when he happened to be in front of me at
                  the service, was amazed at the fervour of his soul before God, since his hands
                  also under his robe, that is the palms themselves, were secretly extended, and
                  every part of him was being drawn upwards, while not a sentence was allowed to
                  pass out from his mouth without an expression of praise or thanksgiving Between
                  each several sentence, <quote>Praise to thee, Lord</quote>; <pb type="vol" n="275"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="275"/>again, <quote>Thanks to thee, our Hope</quote>; at another again,
                     <quote>Blessed art thou, our Creator. Praise to thy mercy, our Saviour</quote>;
                  and thus his tongue would give birth to these fruits all the time of his service,
                  and would send them to heaven in rapid succession without ceasing. This
                     earnest<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> man therefore fell on
                  his face before me weeping bitterly, and spoke with me, and said to me: <quote>I,
                     my father, am lost from before God; and from this time forth I am ashamed to
                     stand before that majesty inasmuch as I have provoked it; since I have deserted
                     it and have served with <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3651">Satan</persName>, doing his will</quote>. But I, when I heard it, was
                  astounded, and said: <quote>Tell me what the thing is</quote>, while others also
                  were standing and listening and marvelling. He says to me: <quote>I have committed
                     a great sin, and cannot confess it before men</quote>. I, thinking that perhaps
                  some temptation of fornication had somewhere come in his way and he had fallen,
                  say to him: <quote>Tell me your sin</quote>. But he objected, weeping, <quote>Be
                     not vexed, sir, that I cannot confess.</quote> But I, because I thought that
                  perhaps he would be ashamed in the presence of many persons, took him apart, and
                  said to him: <quote>In case the temptation of fornication has come in your way,
                     say, and be not ashamed; because this happened to mighty men also, <pb type="vol" n="276"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="276"/>and they repented at once, and were forgiven. And now say,
                     and I myself will repent with you</quote>. But he said, <quote>My sin, sir, is
                     more grievous and more lamentable than fornication</quote>. But I again, being
                  greatly distressed, raised my thoughts to terrible and grievous things, in which
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3651">Satan</persName> by the same
                  desire plunges and suffocates men; and, being afflicted at the thought of these
                  things, I said to him: <quote>Blessed man, our God is good and merciful; and,
                     however great are the wickednesses that a man commits, if so be he turns and
                     knocks at the door of his mercy, he does not reject him; but he rejoices over
                     him and receives him. See how his own chief disciple Simon fell not only into
                     the simple wickedness of denial, but also into that of oaths and curses; and,
                     when he poured out tears toward him, he did not remember his offence. And now,
                     if you are willing to tell your case –, and, if not, why do you trouble
                     me?</quote>. He said to me: <quote>Now, sir, I will confess. While I was
                     standing before God at the service, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3651">Satan</persName> threw one of the
                     brothers down, and he came and fell before my feet; and I on seeing it deserted
                     the service of God, and performed that of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3651">Satan</persName>, and I fell, and
                     laughed over that brother while I was standing at the service. And lo! this is
                     my disaster</quote>. When I on my part heard this, I also was smitten with the
                  same sin as he, <pb type="vol" n="277"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="277"/>and I laughed over all the depths and
                  heights of sins which up to now we had thinking that this might be. And, being
                  amazed at the blessed man's spirituality, to think what a height of wickedness the
                  saints reckon such a little shortcoming as is neglected by us so that we ourselves
                  do not even reckon it as a shortcoming, I said to him: <quote>In case you have
                     been constrained by shame to say one thing in place of another, beware lest
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3651">Satan</persName> deceive you,
                     and you be involved in two wickednesses and double your sin by the use of
                     falsehood</quote>. But he professed, <quote>This, sir, is my sin; and I seek to
                     learn from you how to meet God</quote>. But I, looking at the nature of the
                  man's pre-eminent character, did not bring his thoughts down to the level of our
                  contemptibility and say to him, <quote>This is not a sin</quote>, in the first
                  place because it is a sin, and in the second since excessive caution would do no
                  harm to the blessed man, saying: <quote>Go, our brother, again, and pray to God on
                     account of this sin; not for your own only, but also for the rest who slip and
                     fall into it like you. And do you, as far as you can, beware both of it and of
                     any other. But, if you fall into any sin, beware lest <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3651">Satan</persName> lead you into despair
                     and say to you, <quote>You have provoked, you will not be accepted</quote>;
                     but, whenever you have any ulcer of sin, lay the poultice of repentance<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/>
                            <pb type="vol" n="278"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="278"/>upon it immediately, and do not despair</quote>. And
                  so he accepted the advice, and went away; and from that time forward he used to
                  perform remorseful repentance for that sin by day and by night. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-20.2" n="2"> Next it has been my desire to record something on the
                  subject of the training which I have seen them applying in that convent to those
                  who come from the world to receive the religious habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>), which pleased me greatly. For these are not like all the
                  others who,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> if a man runs away by
                  reason of an offence committed, or from slavery, or from a quarrel with his wife,
                  or by reason of thefts and the menace of the law, then he goes to a monastery, and
                  at once has his hair shaven from his head, and has passed in and been admitted,
                  while the sensual methods and acts of the worldliness of this world are thronging
                  within his mind, and also, as soon as he has seen that his hair has been removed
                  and he has been clothed in the loose garment, he will think that he has now also
                  passed the limit of perfection and of monasticism. And for this reason there are
                  many also from whom the leaven of their worldliness does not pass away even when
                  they are in a convent many years, because the thorns and briers of their loose and
                  dissolute and sensual customs in the wordly estate were not from the beginning
                  cleansed, <pb type="vol" n="279"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="279"/>and then the pure unalloyed seed of the devout
                  and venerable habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) of religion falls
                  outwardly upon them, and they have put it on at once on the first day, and from
                  this time it has been in <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3651">Satan</persName>'s power easily to drag and entrap and lead many into
                  sensuality and pride as well as into actual dishonourable and odious customs and
                  passions of various kinds; because, if the root of worldliness remains in its
                  place, the thorns of disorderliness and sensuality and greediness and the love of
                  money and evil passions spring from it. In this convent therefore it is not so,
                  since from it there come monks indeed and not like that rabble who themselves
                  according to the words of Scripture seduced Israel to turn against the Lord who
                  delivered them to try him<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> As soon
                  as a layman comes who wishes to enter upon a course of training, at first they ask
                  him questions about his country and his family (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>), and what he possesses in the world, and what cause gave rise
                  to this resolution in him, inquiring of him <quote>Has any worldly cause turned
                     your thoughts to this purpose?</quote>; and, after the man whoever he be has
                  settled all these points, so that they may know the genuineness of his desire, if
                  again he in truth possesses this in his mind, they inquire of him, <quote>Lo! how
                     long have you <pb type="vol" n="280"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="280"/>had this resolution in you?</quote>;
                  and on learning all these things they allow him to stand at the gate for thirty
                  days, saying, <quote>Beware lest your thoughts urge you to return for any reason,
                     for the sake of kindred (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>), or for the
                     sake of wife, or for the sake of any property. Sit here, and try your thoughts
                     for thirty days, if you can die to the things of the world, and then you shall
                     come in to live with <persName>Christ</persName>, knowing this also, that, as a
                     dead man, after they have carried him out of his house and laid him in the
                     grave, is no longer able either in small or in great degree to consider or
                     think or know if he has any worldly property, so he who is buried with God, if
                     he seeks to serve him, has no more any kind of worldly property, so that not
                     only does he become a stranger to things outside him, but he also seeks even to
                     forget himself, that is to abandon his former habits, and then he
                     approaches</quote>. But after thirty days, if they see that he is kindled with
                  enthusiasm (?), they again say the same things to him and many words, and then he
                  comes inside, while they give him free admission and also require him to be
                  regular in attending service and watching with the brotherhood, and the weekly
                     ministration,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> and all the the
                  menial labour of the monastery for about three months, making trial of <pb type="vol" n="281"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="281"/>his earnestness and observing his alacrity. And, if they see him
                  to be eager to receive the mark, and if he is vigilant and presents a petition,
                  then indeed he is again called, and many things are said to him: <quote>You have
                     tried, and you have seen. Is it too hard for you? after you have received the
                     mark and laid a foundation for repentance, let not <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3651">Satan</persName> return again; for from
                     this time struggles and temptations such as you have never seen will assail
                     you</quote>. And, when he professes every thing, they present him before the
                  altar and make a prayer for him, and they take a small round piece from the crown
                  of his head, as the custom is (and they take it even from many laymen<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/>); and they say to him: <quote>From
                     this time onward you become a penitent, not a monk. Remember everything that
                     has been done by you, and make entreaty on account of it before God and repent
                     of your former habits, and forget them; and cleanse yourself from all worldly
                     foulness for three years. If so be you have cloven firmly to
                        <persName>Christ</persName>, then he will command, and they will clothe you
                     in the venerable robe (<foreign xml:lang="grc">στολή</foreign>) of his habit
                        (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>), and he will place on your hand
                     also the ring of observance of his commandments</quote>. And so they leave him
                  again for three more months; and again he presents a petition to be <pb type="vol" n="282"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="282"/>tonsured, while this also is their part, to urge him himself to
                  seek intercessors.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> And again they
                  require at his hands, <quote>Look to your thoughts. It is expedient for you now to
                     turn back and it is open to you to do so. Can you endure, even after yet other
                     days' journeys (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μανσίων</foreign>) have presented
                     themselves before you?</quote>. And, if again they see that he is in earnest,
                  they shave half his head only, so that for this reason one may see many among them
                  whose tonsures differ among themselves. And, at the end of a year of his
                  penitence, then his tonsure only is completed, while he is not allowed to clothe
                  himself in the coat, nor to bind on the girdle, nor the cloak, nor the cowl, nor a
                  regular tunic or a regular coat,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/>
                  but they bind a cord on him over a tunic of straw, and a hood moreover of straw,
                  saying, <quote>Be in earnest in your repentance</quote>; and thus they humble his
                  thoughts during his repentance, while he longs and expects and hopes until he be
                  thought worthy to approach the habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>)
                  also. And he completes three years,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/>
                  and then he comes before the altar; and again great cautions are pronounced, and,
                     <quote>In case you seek to turn back now, it is open to you</quote>. And so
                  they array him in the habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>), the first
                  foundation which he laid <pb type="vol" n="283"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="283"/>having been laid by him unto
                  his end. At these things I was greatly astonished, and they pleased me much; for
                  these men are in truth brought to religion. </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-20">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-20.1" n="3"> The history of a certain brother from the convent of the
                  holy <persName>Zacharias</persName>, and about the beginning of sound training is
                  ended. </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 273, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>The sentence is left unfinished, and the sense resumed in the next. PATR.
               OR. - T. XVII. - F. 1.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 274, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This is the best that I can make of this sentence, which is probably
               corrupt.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 274, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>V. D. and L. conj. <hi rend="singleQuotes">outsiders</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 275, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>The ms. reading might perh. be rendered <hi rend="singleQuotes">rapt</hi>
               (V. D. and L. <hi rend="singleQuotes">ecstaticus</hi>); but, as is not known in this
               sense, I prefer the easy emendation.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 277, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Cf. p. 52.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 278, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>The sentence is left unfinished and the sense completed in another
               way.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 279, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Num., XI, 4.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 280, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>The duties of the <foreign>hebdomadarii</foreign>; see p. 62, n. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 281, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. those who are not inmates of a monastery; cf. ch. 7.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 282, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. sponsors.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 282, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>John was perh. forgotten that he had mentioned the above.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 282, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>The time seems to be reckoned from the first tonsure (see p. 281, l.
               13).</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
