<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/813">Thomas the Armenian</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/812"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/814"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/813.xml -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-21" n="21">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-21">
                    <head type="main">Next the Twenty-First History, of the Great Blessed Man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2126">Thomas</persName> From <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/576">Armenia</placeName>, Who From Great Riches
                  Was Trained to Poverty of Spirit He and His Wife and His Children,</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-21.1" n="1"> A relation therefore of the history of the admirable
                  modes of life of this holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2126">Thomas</persName> did not seem to me to be alien to this holy series, even if
                  it be not related by us in accordance with its magnificence, on account of the
                  greatness of his later modes of life, and the fervour of his zeal in divine
                  things, and his mortification and the crucifixion of his body to this world; a <pb n="284"/>
                        <pb n="284"/>man with whom we were in pleasant and spiritual
                  intercourse for thirty years after his training.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>
                    </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-21.2" n="2"> This saint's father therefore, whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3260">Šnq</persName>, was formerly a great,
                  renowned, and distinguished man before the kings,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> and he held the office of the satrapy in the districts
                  of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/486">Syria</placeName> and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/576">Armenia</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> for many years, while the kings<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> and all the leading men listened to him and welcomed
                  him, insomuch that the man became exceedingly rich and great, in gold and silver,
                  and extensive lands, and many slaves; while everything that he possessed was on a
                  great scale, were it fields or woods, or parks (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παράδεισος</foreign>) or high buildings of vast size; insomuch that in riches
                  and dignity he held a very high place among those who were in
                     <placeName>p</placeName>. This man therefore had this devout son besides
                  another brother; and he also as well as himself was distinguished and renowned
                  before the kings;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> and he bestowed
                  great care upon him that he might receive the best possible education in the
                  wisdom of the Greeks, placing him at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/46">Berytus</placeName> and at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName> and at other places, while he also spent large sums of
                  money on him in accordance with the <pb n="285"/>
                        <pb n="285"/>scale demanded by
                  the high position. He therefore was brilliantly instructed, and sagaciously
                  educated, for many years; because by his own nature he possessed in general the
                  quality of sagacity. And, when the time came and he had been taught and had
                  received a first-rate education, his father began to occupy himself in introducing
                  him into the office itself, since he was indeed destined to receive the charge
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατία</foreign>) of the great governorship (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρχεία</foreign>);<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> and, while he was making these plans, the end overtook him; and <quote>on that
                     day</quote>, as it is written, <quote>all his plans perished</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> And this his son remained over his
                  house and over his office, his brother also having died; and he too began to
                  deliberate with himself and to say: <quote>My father, who acquired all this
                     dignity and greatness and property and riches, has left everything, and out of
                     all his house and his riches and his property and his office nothing has gone
                     with him except sins only; and I therefore now, if I stay and add to my
                     father's property to the same extent as he did, and to the same extent a
                     thousand times over, shall presently die as he did, and it will become the
                     property of others, and perhaps it will become the property of men who´are
                     prodigal and vicious and of fornicators, and they will squander it in evil
                     fashion; and to me what will come from it <pb n="286"/>
                            <pb n="286"/>except hell
                     and eternal torment, since neither has all this been amassed by justice or by
                     righteousness, but by plundering and cheating the poor? And now why do I need
                     office and governorship that passes away and decays, and gains nothing else for
                     those who enjoy it except a bad end and judgment and torment? And therefore I
                     will go up to the rulers, and surrender to them the governorship which is
                     theirs, and for me it is sufficient to sit in my house in the silence of my
                     soul and praise God; and what we have is sufficient for me and my children if
                     they live many times over(?)</quote>. He had taken therefore during his
                     life<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/>
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3233">a great wife</persName> from the
                  great and renowned family (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) of those who
                  are called Arsacids, who, as they say, were themselves also an exalted royal race.
                  Such thoughts then first sprang up in this blessed man; and he forth with began to
                  carry the thing out, not delaying, but going up at once to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/586">the royal city</placeName>, and making this
                  request of the king, that he would order them to receive an account of his office.
                  But the king continued to press him to fill his father's place; and he made
                  supplication and said: <quote>If your majesty's slave has found mercy in your
                     eyes, order me <pb n="287"/>
                            <pb n="287"/>only to sit in silence in my house in
                     your dominions; since I am indeed not equal to the position of ruler; and why
                     must I overwhelm myself and others and incur sin?</quote>. And the king,
                  admiring his words, did not press him, but ordered them to receive it<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> from him and let him be released.
                  And thus he was released, and went down to his house with joy, giving thanks to
                  God and saying: <quote>Now that God has delivered me from robbery and cares and
                     anxieties, I will attend to myself and my house and my properties (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ούσίaς</foreign>), and will administer them in a religious
                     spirit; and further I will remember my father who ran his course in the vanity
                     of this deceitful world, and amassed all these things for me. And, in order
                     that I and his own spirit itself may receive deliverance, since I know that he
                     did great injustice, I on my side will give alms out of the very sum that he
                     amassed, that he may find at least a little mercy on the judgment-day</quote>.
                  And from that time therefore he began to carry out these same things, and he did
                  not give and act in the ordinary way like other men, but he would in private grasp
                  the receiver, and in private fall on his face before him weeping and beseeching
                  him to entreat God to accept his purpose, and absolve his father also, saying,
                     <quote>Since you, <pb n="288"/>
                            <pb n="288"/>my brothers, have not provoked God
                     by robbery and injustice, entreat him on our behalf, of whose wickednesses
                     there is no end, that he may be reconciled to us, and have mercy upon us in the
                     great day; since even this which we are giving comes from the blood of the
                     souls of the poor and of the indigent, and of orphans and of widows</quote>.
                  When he had been doing these things for a long time, everyone was astonished at
                  him and praised God, thinking what a cruel and rapacious father had begotten what
                  a just and generous and merciful son. But, while he was making many distributions
                  of alms to all the needy and giving them, during these things his thoughts also
                  were receiving a praiseworthy advance, so that he began to lay a sound foundation
                  for penitence, with affliction and fasting and prayers at all times; and
                  henceforth out of all his great dainties and delicacies he fed on nothing except
                  bread only and salt; and gradually his thoughts progressed until they reached this
                  point, to sell all that he possessed and give to the needy as our Lord also
                  commanded, and take his cross and follow him.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> And this he did not delay to carry out, but he
                  thereupon sent a message to the magnates of the district his neighbours, and
                  stated that, if they were willing to buy his lands which bordered upon them and,
                  if not, they were not to be annoyed <pb n="289"/>
                        <pb n="289"/>at strangers buying
                  them. And, when this news was received, like that which our Lord says in the
                  parable, <quote>A man who finds treasure in a field hath sold all that he
                     possessed and bought that field</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> so everyone who had anything was eager to sell all that he had, and buy
                  one of these admirable and extensive fields. And so, since everyone hastened to be
                  the first to buy, and further since he himself also did not do much valuing, in a
                  short time he sold the great estate (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ούσίaς</foreign>),
                  not being deterred by the beauty of the buildings, nor the extensiveness of the
                  courts that were scattered over these lands, nor the thickness of the many woods
                  and of the parks (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παράδεισος</foreign>) with various kinds
                  of fruit, nor the attractiveness of the irrigation and of the gardens and of the
                  vines, and the circuit of long walls which formed a strong fence round the meadows
                  and vines and fruit; but, just as a man becomes often drunk from wines, so his
                  soul became drunk on God, and he scattered all his possessions in the fervour of
                  his love; since the eye of his mind was henceforth set on the possessions that
                  remain, and the scattering of temporal ones therefore did not trouble him, while
                  henceforth he devoted himself to making gifts on a large scale to the needy and
                  the distressed, and to those who had creditors, and to churches and monasteries,
                     <pb n="290"/>
                        <pb n="290"/>and he dissipated his possessions without stint in a
                  manner that cannot be understood and told; while he also built a certain monastery
                  (which is a well-fortified stronghold) for his own personal use and that of his
                  whole household, since both great and small and his wife and his children, and his
                  slaves also and many free men who were attached to him would promise him to yoke
                  themselves with him under the gentle yoke of monasticism, which they in fact did. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-21.3" n="3"> And he prepared two places, one for himself and the men
                  who were with him, and another for his wife and the other women who were with her,
                  while he collected certain renowned and distinguished blessed men, and they came
                  and made vigil and prayer, and gave them the habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>); and they used to teach them the methods of the religious
                  life and the ordinances of monasticism; and so again his wife also as well sent
                  and fetched for herself two great and holy women from the land of the
                  Cappadocians, and they lived with her, and taught both her and her one daughter
                  and everyone who was with her the discipline of religion. And henceforth all the
                  blessed men used severely to bind upon themselves great burdens of asceticism and
                  of watching and of abstinence and bear them, in order to subdue the worldly <pb n="291"/>
                        <pb n="291"/>animal instincts of their bodies, and beget mildness and
                  humility and religion instead of the things that are in the world, while the
                  report of their labours and of their asceticism was heard everywhere; and
                  thenceforth many magnates and sons of distinguished magnates, marveling at what
                  this blessed man had done, would imitate him, and like him despise the whole
                  world; and some would come to him that they also might receive the habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>), and some again would hasten to other districts
                  and well-known convents, which many in fact did. And accordingly this blessed man
                  had been made a great and beautiful sight for all men, while he had also
                  determined for himself that he would never throw himself upon his side or rest his
                  head upon a pillow, or let water fall upon his body, or oil, as far as was
                  possible, except under the pressure of great necessity (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άνάγκη</foreign>), which he in fact carried out, until his feet were like
                  charred columns, being thick and black, until after ten years they used to
                  discharge a large quantity of matter, and were as if they were not his, since he
                  was smitten with severe ulcers, and would not concern himself even to wash off
                  that discharge, and to apply a poultice, while we used often to say to him,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/>
                        <quote>While thinking <pb n="292"/>
                            <pb n="292"/>yourself to be showing prowess,
                     you will be defeated, if you do not attend to these ulcers, and you will
                     fall</quote>. But he would look in astonishment at us, saying: <quote>Then
                        (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρα</foreign>), when these feet are anointed with
                     drugs, and are rubbed by many persons and cleaned with great care, someone
                     would perhaps come and say, <quote>They have enough, now let them pay for the
                        outward show with which they have been magnified, lest they be requited for
                        it in hell</quote>
                        </quote>. And so, being amazed at the soundness of his
                  intellect, we would allow the matter to drop. Of the rest of the severe practices
                  and heavy labours which they laid not only on themselves, but also the rest of
                  their disciples and his wife and children,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> we are not capable of composing a relation or description, so far did
                  they transcend the limits of corporal creatures. And this again is a point that is
                  very admirable and great, that at the beginning when they began, the first day,
                  each one of them found the last day also, that of his end (?),<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> without wearying of the life or
                  slackening and falling off, through sicknesses, or through the infirmity of his
                  body, or through the intensity of the winter cold, or through the extremity of the
                  summer heat. But the <pb n="293"/>
                        <pb n="293"/>blessed man, hecause he used to
                  bestow much labour on reading, conceived the desire of obtaining some books of the
                  fathers; and in consequence of this desire he directed his journey to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName> the great with three
                  of his followers; and he entered into communication with the many holy bishops and
                  the others who on account of the persecution were at that time collected
                     there;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> and he was strengthened
                  yet more both in the faith and in labours. And he bought many great books of all
                  the fathers, the full amount that he could and was able to obtain, about five
                  large loads,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> and similarly also
                  some spices for a hundred <foreign>denarii</foreign> from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>; and he returned having
                  collected examples of virtue. And so he thenceforth occupied himself constantly
                  night and day, besides constant prayers and frequent repetitions of service, in
                  reading books of the fathers containing commentaries and exhortations and
                  dogmatics (<foreign xml:lang="grc">δογματικά</foreign>), so that thenceforward his
                  mind was enlightened like the sun. After twelve years during which the blessed man
                  with all the rest of his convent was thus distinguishing himself, the smoke of
                  heretical persecution was being exhaled in the same district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/576">Armenia</placeName>, the instigator and
                  perpetrator of these things being the likeness of the original
                     <persName>Antichrist</persName>, the man who held the authority of the
                  patriarchate in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>
                  at that time, <pb n="294"/>
                        <pb n="294"/>whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2274">Ephraim</persName> the son of Appian<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> of Amida; who in his own be done in
                  the world at the end by the false <persName>Christ</persName>. This man's
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3226">brother</persName> therefore was
                  in the district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/576">Armenia</placeName> and Syria, holding the office of the satrapy previously
                  held by the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2126">Thomas</persName> himself;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/> and
                  this man stirred up a cruel persecution against all the believers in the district
                  of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/576">Armenia</placeName>; and
                  thereupon the <foreign>chorepiscopi</foreign> and the heads of convents and the
                  rest of the priests of the villages assemble before the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2126">Thomas</persName> as before a teacher and
                  a learned man and a leader of men, so that a great assembly of five hundred men
                  was formed, saying, <quote>Everything that he commands we will do</quote>. Then
                  these things stirred up violent odium against the virtuous <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2126">Thomas</persName> himself, since they
                  said, <quote>He is a head and an example to all who are in this district to rebel
                     against us</quote>. Then, when the numbers of their assembly had further
                  mounted even to eight hundred, they thereafter received summonses to the <foreign xml:lang="la">praetorium</foreign> of the satrap, that they might do one of two
                  things, either assent to the impiety of the synod of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/622">Chalcedon</placeName>, or leave the <pb n="295"/>
                        <pb n="295"/>district. But they, when they came and stood before the
                  judge and were required to do these things, all as they had been taught by the
                  blessed man cried: <quote>We for our part will not deny
                        <persName>Christ</persName>; and we will not confess or introduce a
                     quaternity in place of the holy Trinity. Far be it from us to communicate with
                     the renegades</quote>. Upon these words being uttered in a loud voice by all
                  that great company the persecutor and judge and all the hearers were alarmed, and
                  trembling fell upon all of them, from the intensity of the one stern cry that
                  resounded like a great thunderclap; and, when the persecutor saw that, unless he
                  first bound the strong man, he could not reduce his camp,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/> he formed the plan of turning the whole force of his
                  efforts in the struggle against the blessed man himself in place of all that
                  company, saying to him: <quote>All these things are your doing; and, if all these
                     men die, they will die at your hands; and henceforth you must contend with the
                     king. Either depart from this district at once, or prepare yourself for the
                     struggle</quote>. But the blessed man as one possessed of confidence and
                  strength said to him: <quote>For my part, O man now exalted, I am not frightened
                     of your words, and your threats are of no account to me; nor in the matter of
                     the faith of <persName>Christ</persName> do I take account of the king, nor of
                     you, nor of anyone who lives in this <pb n="296"/>
                            <pb n="296"/>world. But, lest
                     you think that I for my part am bound by district or place, if you seek to
                     expel me from the district, I on my part will leave this evening, that you may
                     know that I am not bound by anything else except by <persName>Jesus</persName>
                     my God by whose name I was saved</quote>. He said to him: <quote>If you wish to
                     respect yourself, and not let there be slaughter in the whole district on your
                     account, depart from the district</quote>. But the blessed man gladly undertook
                  to depart, saying, <quote>Would that I the sinner might be persecuted on behalf of
                     the great name of <persName>Christ</persName> my God; for I neither have
                     merited nor do merit this privilege</quote>. And so he departed from his
                  district with all who were with him; and the rest of all that assembly journeyed
                  after him, and some to other districts, and some to the stern and rugged
                  mountains; and so all of them everywhere bravely endured the violent and cruel
                  persecution. But the blessed man crossed into <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2769">the district called Claudias</placeName>,
                  and there he bought a site; and on that site on the high mountains of towering
                  size above the river <placeName>Euphrates</placeName> he erected some small huts
                  forming two monasteries for women and for men; and there for the future they
                  valiantly carried out the labours which they habitually practised. When he had
                  completed the period of thirty years in banishment,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/> when afterwards we used to resort to <pb n="297"/>
                        <pb n="297"/>the presence of the same blessed man himself, and wished as it were to
                  offer him consolation, he would show his fortitude and his courage yet more by
                  saying, <quote>For my part I am ready not only to be expelled or to die one death
                     only for <persName>Christ</persName>'s sake, but also, if it were possible for
                     a man to die ten thousand deaths, even this will not distress me</quote>. And
                  so thenceforward the severe life of the mountains and the multifarious hardships
                  existing upon them were counted by those persons as a spacious garden; for, when
                  he had found that quiet retreat, he had great joy and pleasure, and he thereupon
                  made himself a small hut of planks, and used to carry out the great labour of his
                  secret practices in it, having laid down an absolute rule for himself not to taste
                  bread or wine unless constrained by necessity (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άνάγκη</foreign>); and thus he would feed on pulse and some fruit only,
                  sometimes from one week to the next and again on the first day of the week, and
                  sometimes every two or three days, so that he was granted the gift of secret
                  vision (<foreign xml:lang="grc">θεωρία</foreign>). And so also his sons too who
                  were three he used to train in this great method of life, in the same way as his
                  blessed wife who was called <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3233">Maria</persName> also yoked herself to the same mode of life, and she also
                  laboured in the same way, <pb n="298"/>
                        <pb n="298"/>while she never came within
                  sight of the blessed man nor yet of his sons, but each of them performed his<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a21" target="#n21" n="21"/> spiritual service alone and
                  solitary. And so everyone was amazed at them, to think to what extremity of
                  humility and of labours and of hardship like this persons who were already in the
                  world's eyes kings had been brought, and they gave thanks because of them and
                  praised God. And they departed from the world with a reputation for marvellous
                  modes of life; and the blessed man finished his course in the royal city, being
                  also interred in our convent at the holy <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2814">Mar Mama</placeName> beyond the water,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a22" target="#n22" n="22"/> and his blessed wife ended her
                  course at the same time in the district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/576">Armenia</placeName>. </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-21">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-21.1" n="4"> The history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2126">Thomas</persName> from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/576">Armenia</placeName>, and of his wife and of
                  his sons is ended </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 284, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 291, n.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 284, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">king and queen</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 284, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>This seems to be an exaggerated statement. The only satrapies were those of
               the 5 Armenian territories which Justinian in 536 combined into Armenia IV
                  (<title>Novella</title> 31), and that Šnq's post was one of these is confirmed by
               the fact that his son had a hereditary claim to the succession. The district was
               appy. Balabitene, since the hereditary tenure of the other satrapies was abolished by
               Zeno (Proc., Aed., III, 1). The 5 satrapies might be described as either Syria or
               Armenia, and perh. this is what J. means. Cf. p. 294.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 285, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I.e., to succeed to the satrapy.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 285, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. CXLVI, 4.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 286, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>His father's life must be meant. Perh. has fallen out.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 287, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. the account.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 288, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., XIX, 21 (X, 38).</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 289, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Id., XIII, 44.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 291, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This would probably be after the Th. had removed to Claudius (see below).
               The statement at the beginning that J. knew him 30 years from his entering upon the
               monastic life can hardly be reconciled with the statement that Th. lived 30 years
               after his banishment (p. 296), and probably the period should be reckoned from his
               banishment.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 292, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. <hi rend="singleQuotes">did the same</hi>(?). The Syriac is
               awkward.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 292, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>I do not understand this. V. D. and L.'s translation <hi rend="singleQuotes">
                        <foreign>omnes qualia die 1' facere coeperant, etiam postremo die talia
                     agentes vidi</foreign>
                    </hi> may express the meaning intended, but is not in the
               text.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 293, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>519-536.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 293, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Horses' burdens (?).</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 294, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Or, as a family name <hi rend="singleQuotes">Bar Afyana</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 294, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Cf. Land, II, 295. Hence it appears that these events happened at the same
               time of Ephraim's descent to the E., which was at the end of 536 or beginning of 537
               (see Introd.). The satrapies were abolished by the edict of 18 Mar., 536 (p. 284, n.
               3), but the provisions would take some time to carry out. The beginning of Th.'s
               monastic career must then be placed in 524.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 295, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., XII, 29.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 296, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This brings us to 566/7, but probably the sentence is faultily expressed,
               and J. does not mean that this was after the 30 years that he visited him. At p. 284
               the 30 years are reckoned from the beginning of his monastic life (524), which brings
               us to 544, but see p. 291, note. Since J. wrote in 566 (see Introd.), 30 years should
               probably not be taken as an exact reckoning.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 298, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. his or her.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 298, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>The convent was in Sycae (ch. 37), i. e. the suburb beyond the Golden Horn.
               Pargoire (<title>Izvestiya Russkago Arkheologicheskago Istituta v
                  Konstantinople</title>, IX, p. 261, (1904)) has shown that the palace of S. Mama
               was on the Thracian coast opposite Chrysopolis, and the monastery of S. Mama at
               Belgrad Kapu in the SW. of the city; and <hi rend="singleQuotes">beyond the
                  water</hi> shows the palace to be here meant, even if we did not know the site to
               be in Sycae. V. D. and L.'s rendering <foreign>ecclesia</foreign> in ch. 37 is
               erroneous, the Syr. having <hi rend="singleQuotes">house</hi> only.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
