<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/814">Addai and Abraham</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/813"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/815"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/814.xml -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-22" n="22">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-22">
               <head type="main">Next the Twenty-Second History, of the Two Blessed Anchorite Brothers <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1117">Addai</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1548">Abraham</persName> the Zealous Men</head>
               <ab xml:id="section-22.1" n="1"> These blessed men <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1117">Addai</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1548">Abraham</persName> therefore were brothers
                  on the mother's side, and at first they remained under training in a convent for
                  several years; and afterwards they formed the resolution of going out on
                  pilgrimage. And, when they had been thus going about for several years, they began
                  to deliberate between themselves, saying, <quote>Wherefore do we thus go aimlessly
                     about, and not show labour for our Lord, and erect places for his
                     praise?</quote> And so, as they were going about, they found a certain place
                  that was a convenient site for a <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3048">monastery</placeName>, and they planted their cross there, and made a cabin;
                  and they asked for iron tools, and began to dig out a site for a martyrs' chapel.
                  And, when the people of the district saw and heard it, they repaired to them from
                  all quarters, providing money and wood and everything that was useful. And in one
                  year they erected an extensive convent in that place, and they also gained
                  disciples; and when they saw it they rejoiced, and they say: <quote>Now it is
                     better for us than roving and going about aimlessly</quote>. And, when they had
                  trained some men and taught them the psalms, and shown them how to conduct
                  affairs, they conceived the plan of leaving them there as it were to govern
                  themselves and depar<pb n="300"/>
                  <pb n="300"/>ting, and erecting another place.
                  And thus they continued doing for twenty-five years, during which they erected
                  twelve monasteries; most of which I know, which they erected in the district, and
                  the rest, because they were some way off, I have not seen; but the men I saw at
                  last in that in which the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1117">Addai</persName> who was the elder died, and I was for some time in
                  intercourse with them, and they said, <quote>This is the twelfth <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3048">monastery</placeName> that we have
                     erected, since we devoted ourselves to this object</quote>. And in each of them
                  this is what they used to do. As soon as it was built, they would obtain
                  everything that they could for it, and appoint an archimandrite in it, and then
                  depart. But at last the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1117">Addai</persName> fell asleep in the twelfth. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-22">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-22.1" n="2"> The history of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1117">Addai</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1548">Abraham</persName> the zealous brothers is
                  ended. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
