<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/815">Simeon the Solitary</title>
            <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/814"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/816"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/815.xml -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-23" n="23">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-23">
               <head type="main">Next the Twenty-Third History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2099">Simeon</persName> the Solitary,</head>
               <ab xml:id="section-23.1" n="1">
                  This blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2099">Simeon</persName> 
                  therefore used to occupy himself with great and marvellous practices 
                  in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2736">a convent</placeName> adjoining 
                  the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>,
                  being distinguished for quietude and humility and obedience, and love of all spiritual
                  <pb type="vol" n="301"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="301"/>labours, and especially the service of the saints,
                  and great and abounding love towards all poor men and strangers. But, when he had
                  completed twenty years in these heavenly practices, he desired to adopt the life
                  of a solitary; and he set out and went to a certain mountain two miles from the
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">city</placeName>; and he passed the
                  night at a certain spot. And there he prayed and traced the plan of some cabins
                  for himself, and he began and built some huts there that were very marvellous,
                  being supplied by many persons with all that he needed; and thereafter he used to
                  carry out all the marvellous labours of his honoured course of life. But on
                  account of the abundance of his charity and the love of strangers and poor men
                  that burned in him he would not consent to make a court or gates for his huts,
                  saying, <quote>Thus it will be open to <persName>Christ</persName> my Lord when he
                     comes to me to enter my dwelling in the person of his bondmen simply and
                     without impediment; that so he may grant me the blessing of his favour</quote>.
                  And so much was this saint smitten with the love of God, and with the love of his
                  brethren, that, when occasion called bim to leave his huts, he did not close the
                  door and conceal any one of the articles of furniture in his cell, but also he
                  used to do a thing that is particularly great and splendid and marvellous to hear,
                  when it happened that he was absent were it one day or two or three from his cell.
                  Not only did <pb type="vol" n="302"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="302"/>he not trouble himself to bring in any one
                  article of furniture in his cell, but also on the day on which he left his cell he
                  would first cook food, and would lay a table, and moisten bread and temper wine,
                  and put it out, and a tablet inscribed and laid on the top of it as follows (which
                  we have also often read), on which were these words: <quote>Welcome, our brothers,
                     <persName>Christ</persName>'s bondmen; come into your bondman's house
                     confidently and refresh yourselves, and hesitate not. Since occasion has called
                     me the sinner to go on necessary service, here is a present of what is required
                     to satisfy need from the gift of our Benefactor set ready. For the sake of his
                     true love, whether it is one or many whom <persName>Christ</persName> my Lord
                     is preparing and sending to his bondman's house, shrink not from coming in and
                     satisfying all your need, though I myself am absent in the body. If it be
                     possible for him to wait till I come, I beg him to do so; if not, let him
                     refresh himself out of our Lord's gift and bless the Giver, and leave us the
                     blessing of his prayers, and thus go in peace; and, if he need anything else
                     besides, lo! the whole cell is committed to <persName>Christ</persName>'s
                     hands, and at his hands let him satisfy all his need without restraint from
                     everything that is in it. But let him leave this writing of ours in its place
                     for the rest of our brethren who shall arrive in order to inform them <pb type="vol" n="303"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="303"/>also</quote>. And so the fame of this saint's great
                  charity was spoken of over the whole of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">city</placeName> and that district. But once
                  two young men who were passing came, and they found the huts open, and no one was
                  to be seen all round; and they went in and ate and drank, and the rest they put
                  into their packs; and they loaded themselves, and started to go. And, when they
                  had passed out of the door, their feet stuck there, and they stood still bearing
                  their loads till the evening and standing erect; and they became incapable of
                  moving, or of laying down their loads until <rs ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2099">the blessed man</rs>. And on seeing them
                  from a distance he understood what had happened; and they themselves cried with a
                  loud voice and say, <quote>Sir, have mercy on us for we have sinned against you,
                     and forgive us</quote>. But <rs ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2099">the
                        blessed man</rs> immediately raised his eyes to heaven, and prayed, and said:
                  <quote>Lord, deliver thy creatures, and free them from the deceitful teaching
                     of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3651">the enemy</persName>; and
                     remove from them <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3651">the teacher of
                        evil</persName> who incited them to these things</quote>. And the same hour
                  they were released, and fell on their faces before him. And he on his side said
                  these words to them: <quote>Knew you not, my sons, that I had committed this cell
                     to <persName>Christ</persName> my Lord, and him nothing escapes? or know you
                     not that, wherever <persName>Christ</persName>'s name is called, everyone who
                     presumes <pb type="vol" n="304"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="304"/>to stretch out his hand and lay it upon
                     anything has to deal with God the Judge of all? And now, my sons, go and beware
                  </quote>. And so he dismissed them.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>
                  And the fame of the saint's triumphs was spoken of everywhere. But afterwards the
                  storm (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χειμών</foreign>) of persecution was stirred up
                  against the same <rs ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2099">blessed man</rs> also
                  together with all the rest of the church; and he bravely and heroically contended
                  in the conflicts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>), while all the convents
                  were overcome and defeated by the persecution, and driven from the whole
                  district.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> And he himself held
                  firm; and thus he persevered and maintained a heroic contest; and he used to go
                  about the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">city</placeName> itself at
                  the very height of the persecution, and give absolution and baptize night and day,
                  while he had previously determined this also, that nothing should enter his belly
                  except from the labour of his hands; but he used to labour with his hands in
                  proportion to his own needs, and those of the other strangers whom he was in the
                  habit of receiving in secret and relieving out of his labour. And thus he
                  contended several years while occupied in this labour; and he ended his life with
                  this reputation, in the triumph of heroism, while contending until death on behalf
                  of the truth. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-23">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-23.1" n="2"> The history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2099">Simeon</persName> the solitary is ended.
               </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 304, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>A
               similar story is told in Rufinus, Hist. Mon., 6 (Dyakonov, p. 385).</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 304, n.
                     2</orig>
               </choice>This seems to mean that some submitted and others went into
               exile.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
