<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/816">John of Tella</title>
                <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/815"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/817"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/816 -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-24" n="24">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-24">
                    <head type="main">Next the Twenty-Fourth History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/50">John</persName> Bishop of the City of
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/200">Thella</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>
                    </head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-24.1" n="1"> When therefore we approach the history of this holy
                  bishop <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/50">John</persName> that abounds
                  in beauties, we need the help that is brought through his prayers, and then we
                  shall be able, even if obscurely, through the vile pigments of our words, to lay
                  down and trace out a delineation of the features of his divine beauties;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> and indeed his beauty does not shine
                  from one side only, but from all sides the rays of his light flash upon the soul
                  that wishes to gaze at him; for, if in accordance with the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1983">Paul</persName>'s saying<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> one seek him among solitaries, he is
                  a perlect solitary, and, if among priests, a high-priest, and, if among persecuted
                  men, one who bears his cross on his shoulder every day, and, if among the public
                  contests of combatants (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγωνιστής</foreign>), a brave
                  combatant (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγωνιστής</foreign>) and a hero, and, if again
                  in the series of martyrs, a true martyr for the truth of his faith; and this is
                  the consummation of all his <pb type="vol" n="514"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="312"/>beauties. This saint, for
                  whom also, I think, the appellation 'God-clad’ is not inappropriate, after the
                  pattern of the ancient <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/544">Ignatius</persName>, the saint and bishop and martyr, who earned this name
                  (and, if perhaps it is not audacious to say it and to presume so far, this man
                  seems to have shown yet even more valour than he in the contest on behalf of the
                  whole church of the believers, that is, he distinguished himself to perfection in
                  his acts), this man therefore at first distinguished himself in the laborious and
                  divine practice of the solitary life; and by God's grace he was also advanced to
                  be bishop of the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/200">Thella</placeName>. And, when again he had for some years<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> led a severe life in this same city,
                  the severe persecution set on foot by the partisans of the schismatic synod of
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/622">Chalcedon</placeName> was wafted
                  like smoke everywhere, and it blinded everyone whose spiritual eyesight was not
                  founded upon a sound basis, and concealed the light of their truth, and they
                  became accomplishers of the saying, <quote>They changed God's truth into a
                     lie</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> When therefore this
                  troublous time came to this blessed man, and sought<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> to unsettle him like many and turn him away from his
                  steadfastness, he on his side was more resplendent and beautiful; and, having
                  repelled the <pb type="vol" n="515"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="313"/>heretical communion from him, he was driven
                  from his see with all the other holy bishops, about twelve from his neighbourhood;
                  and thenceforth they endured the severe labours and grievous hardships of
                  banishment, and wanderings in every place. But this blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/50">John</persName> joyfully resorted to his
                  former anchoritic habits, which he had previously desired to do; and often he
                  wished to leave his see and depart, and he was hindered and stayed by the fear of
                  judgment and requital for deserting the rational flock that had been entrusted to
                  him; and now he found an opportunity, and returned to that for which he was ready,
                  first to his <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/356">former
                     convent</placeName>, which was in the city of <persName>Callinicus</persName>,
                  which was called that of Mar <persName>Zakkhai</persName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> and when he had been a short time in this convent, the
                  adversary came thither also as well, and a second time the blessed man was again
                  in banishment with his convent, with the rest of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2736">convents</placeName>, and with all the
                  other bishops also; and thenceforth they were driven to the outer deserts,
                  rejoicing and exulting that they had been thought worthy to suffer persecution
                  with Christ,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> since the other
                  bishops also were scattered over all the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2736">convents</placeName>. But, when the period
                  of persecution had lasted about ten years,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> the rest of the <pb type="vol" n="516"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="314"/>believers everywhere were in
                  difficulties about ordinations (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροτονία</foreign>); and
                  they began to have recourse to the believing bishops. But the blessed men,
                  inasmuch as they were troubled by fear of lighting the furnace of persecution more
                  hotly against them, refused to practise this<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> openly, though they did a few things in secret; and a
                  murmuring on the part of those among the believers who had been banished from
                  every quarter began to be stirred up against the blessed men, since they had been
                  reduced to great difficulties, while they spoke and sent messages to them at all
                  times, asking them to give a hand of ordination (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροτονία</foreign>) to the church of the believers, <quote>because it is in
                     great difficulties</quote>. Then all the bishops assembled together, and
                  considered what to do. If they should give the hand <quote>crowds of believers
                     will come from every quarter, and the persecutors will hear it, and be more
                     inflamed with rage</quote>; and on this ground they finally out of fear refused
                  the thing. Then, as it is written that <quote>The Lord stirred up the spirit of
                        <persName>Zurbabel</persName> and the spirit of <persName>Joshua</persName>
                     the son of <persName>Jozadak</persName> the high-priest to stand up and build
                     the Lord's house</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> so
                  also here it were fitting to say that the Lord stirred up the spirit of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/50">John</persName> to stand up and visit the
                  Lord's <pb type="vol" n="517"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="315"/>church, which is the persecuted in every quarter.
                  Then he was moved with indignation in his spirit and argued against his
                  fellow-bishops, saying: <quote>Lo! see that henceforth we are not perfect in the
                     love of God, since according to the saying of Scripture, <quote>He who feareth
                        is not perfect in love</quote>; and again <quote>There is no fear in
                        love</quote>; and again <quote>Love casteth out fear</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> And now we our own selves have
                     stated it; and henceforth whither shall the persecuted and distressed believers
                     who are with us go? Do you wish, pray, that we should send them to those that
                     are every day killing them? for God knows that I for my part was ready for a
                     life of quietude. by myself, and that I should leave God's people and church in
                     distress and need, and serve my own self, far be it from me in the Lord's name.
                     But now either consent to stretch out a hand to the believers in the boldness
                        (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>) of our God, and let us contend
                     valiantly each of us doing his part, and, if not and you are afraid, give me a
                     mandate and a licence from the patriarchs and from yourselves, and save
                     yourselves; and I for my part will be persecuted, and I am ready even to die
                     also a thousand times, if it were possible, for the sake of the believing
                     people</quote>. The bishops rejoiced at this, and said: <quote>It is better
                     that one of us only should be known by this in <pb type="vol" n="518"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="316"/>the
                     affair, and not all of us; and take also authority and licence from ourselves;
                     and we will refer this by letter to our saintly father the patriarch,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> and he will issue a mandate to
                     us, that it shall be permitted to give a hand to all expelled men who come to
                     you from all parts</quote>. And the blessed man clad himself in this
                  zealousness, and thenceforth this became known to the expelled multitudes
                  everywhere; and from that time they rushed in crowds to come to the blessed man
                  freely without impediment like a flood that is produced in a river by thick
                  clouds, while he was sometimes. to be found in his same monastery and received
                  them there, and sometimes in the desert, and sometimes in some convent, receiving
                  and dismissing companies of fifty and of a hundred in a day, and even now and
                  again as many as two and three hundred a day, giving expositions and injunctions
                  and caution and instruction, and performing the ordinations after careful
                  investigation and many testimonies given, subjecting every man to a careful
                  examination and test in reading the Scriptures and repeating the psalms, and
                  ability to write their names and signatures, not admitting anyone whomsoever who
                  did not sign his name, and, if anyone was incapable of doing so, he would bid him
                  learn, and his companion would write for him,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/>
                        <pb type="vol" n="519"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="317"/>and thus therefore they were received and dismissed;
                  while he also inquired and learned who were the men of knowledge in all the
                  districts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χώρας</foreign>), and he would send and fetch
                  them, and give them instructions, and hand them the impress of his name and his
                  monogram (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σημείον</foreign>), themselves to see by
                  investigation who were fit to become priests, and to write and send them to him,
                  that he might not perform ordinations at random. Accordingly in every city as far
                  as the frontier, and as far as <placeName>Armenia</placeName> and
                     <persName>Arzun</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> and
                  the land of the <persName>Cappadocians</persName> and the sea-coasts,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> men were chosen and appointed to
                  send candidates to him after investigation; and, if it happened that anyone came
                  to him without a letter from the man that had been appointed in the region from
                  which he came, he would return empty, until he brought a letter, and then he would
                  be received; as no believing bishops were to be found except at these three places
                  only, at Marde<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> and in the land of
                  the <persName>Persians</persName>, and at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/579">Alexandria</placeName>. When the whole
                  earth, so to speak, had been filled with tlhe ordination (ysporovia) of believers,
                  in the cities and the monasteries and the villages and everywhere, insomuch that
                  some of those <pb type="vol" n="520"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="318"/>that were in communion with the heretics
                  would every day arrive and come to repentance, then these things exasperated those
                  that held authority both in the churches and in the world, so that they did not
                  shrink from writing a report of these things even to the wielder of the royal
                  authority, first concerning all the believers, and concerning all the freedom
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>) that they had shown, and then
                  concerning him who had been made the cause of these things. Thenceforward they
                  hunted after the blessed man's life to take it away<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/>, while the occupiers of the sees at first sent him
                  threats and orders and mandates issued by the king that, if he performed
                  ordination (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροτονία</foreign>), he should die; and he
                  on his side sent them this message : <quote>I for my part have received a gift
                     from God, and with it I am trading and am not negligent;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/> and know this, that, as long as I am in the bodily
                     life, and a hand is given me to extend to anyone that is in need, not you nor
                     an earthly king shall hinder me from performing the service that the heavenly
                     king has given me.</quote>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/> When
                  they saw the man's readiness and courage, they threatened the more; and
                  thenceforth he did not show himself openly with the former freedom (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>), but at the time when believers arrived he
                  on his side <pb type="vol" n="521"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="319"/>would spring up there, and therefore he
                  would dismiss many at night, as he was the first to admit our meanness also with
                  the rest of our brothers, the members of our convent, to the order of the
                  diaconate, in the year eight hundred and forty,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a21" target="#n21" n="21"/> when we came down to him and received the privilege of
                  seeing him by night, when we were also astonished above all things by his attire
                  and the austerity of his garb, since an unsightly cloak had been cut in two, and
                  so he clothed himself with half of it and covered himself with half of it,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a22" target="#n22" n="22"/> and thus therefore he had no
                  superfluity either of clothing or of covering. When he saw our company and our
                  habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>), and especially the fact that he
                  had seen<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a23" target="#n23" n="23"/> that he had not much
                  trouble with us, because all of us, who were about seventy men, came from
                  well-known Amidene convents, and we read and wrote witlh confidence, then he said,
                     <quote>I am satisfied with you, my sons; and lo! I say to you <quote>Pray and
                        cease not</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a24" target="#n24" n="24"/> for a time
                     is coming when men to give a hand to believers shall be wanting and shall not
                     be found</quote>. And so we received his blessing, and returned, and his
                  prophecy also was in truth fulfilled, and they were sought and not <pb type="vol" n="522"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="320"/>found, so that for many years a man would go into <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/579">Alexandria</placeName> to become a
                     priest<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a25" target="#n25" n="25"/> and thence to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/586">Constantinople</placeName>, and return
                  perhaps after a year of days without gaining any satisfaction from his labour, as
                  I saw happen to many; and at the time when I was in the royal city (and the same
                  thing happened in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/579">Alexandria</placeName> also) the believers were in this difficulty; and the
                  frontier of the Persian territory moreover was closed by war, and I always
                  remembered the saint's prophecy. But after a time the blessed man fell into the
                  enemies' hand,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a26" target="#n26" n="26"/> and they satisfied
                  all their malice upon him, and in their craftiness they also hanted for the
                  documents (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χάρτης</foreign>) that contained the anathemas
                  against them and the names of the believers who received the priesthood from him,
                  and God hid them from them, the number of whom, as was posted up (?) by those who
                  counted them, amounted to a hundred and seventy thousand, who received ordination
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροτονία</foreign>) from the blessed man. But they
                  on their side carried him up to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>, and he fell into the hands of the man that one would
                  perhaps not go wrong if one were to name the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2274">executioner</persName> (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κυαιστιωνάριος</foreign>) of the believers, who was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2274">Ephraim</persName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2737">Amida</placeName>; and he inflicted on him
                  severe tortures<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a27" target="#n27" n="27"/> and close painful
                     impri<pb type="vol" n="523"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="321"/>sonments, and thus he suffered martyrdom and
                  died at their hands there, after a period of such-and-such a number of<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a28" target="#n28" n="28"/> years during which he had been
                  undergoing the conflicts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">àgών</foreign>) of martyrdom
                  inflicted upon him there, and the successions of tortures and torturers that were
                  imposed upon him in daily variety in the hope that he might be weakened in his
                  constancy. And, inasmuch as he on his side was girded with the breastplate of
                  righteousness. on the right hand and on the left as it is written, and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a29" target="#n29" n="29"/> held the strong weapon of readiness
                  that contends with death, the burning, that is heretical, darts<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a30" target="#n30" n="30"/> of his persecutors were not able to
                  pierce and penetrate the sound breastplate of his constancy, though many beasts
                  were set round him on all sides to guard him, like that which the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/544">Ignatius</persName> also, the bishop and
                  martyr, to whom at the beginning also we compared this second <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/544">Ignatius</persName>, as he is indeed
                  exceedingly like, thus wrote in his epistle to the
                     <persName>Ephesians</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a31" target="#n31" n="31"/>
                  about certain soldiers (<foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατιώται</foreign>.) to whom he
                  was committed that they might conduct and convey him to
                     <placeName>Rome</placeName> to be martyred there : <quote>Ten cruel savage
                     beasts were committed<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a32" target="#n32" n="32"/> to me,
                     between whom I was bound for my <pb type="vol" n="524"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="322"/>custody that I might
                     go to <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                        </quote>. So therefore in the same way there
                  were committed<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a33" target="#n33" n="33"/> to this man not ten
                  only, but rather many, so that no one whosoever among the believers was able to
                  approach him, he being confined alone, and two<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a34" target="#n34" n="34"/> blessed men that were attached to him alone, who also
                  were combatants (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγωνισταί</foreign>); and thus he ended
                  his life in this conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">àgών</foreign>) in a great
                  martyrdom. And thereupon after his martyrdom his words, of which he had also
                  gained intimation by the revelation of the Holy Spirit, received accomplishment,
                  for he would testify to every man and warn him concerning what was about to come,
                  viz. violent persecutions, lacerations of the believers, scarcity of pastors, with
                  the rest of the sore distresses, even as they were from all sides laid upon those
                  of his ordination (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροτονία</foreign>). Some, that is
                  many, they seized in every city and re-ordained; and some fled to distant regions,
                  and there ended their lives; some departed from life under imprisonments and
                  stripes; and some were burnt with fire in the sight of the peoples of the
                     cities.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a35" target="#n35" n="35"/> A thing which perhaps
                  even the ancient pagans would have been afraid to do, Christians were here thrown
                  into the fire and <pb type="vol" n="525"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="323"/>burnt in the sight of those who also
                  were reckoned and called Christians; and the steam of the savour of their flesh
                  was woefully wafted to heaven and also into the air breathed by men; and so few
                  were left <quote>like doves upon ledges</quote>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a36" target="#n36" n="36"/> as it is written. And thenceforward the remnant of the
                  orthodox (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθόδοξοι</foreign>), great multitudes who were
                  in banishment or in places of exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορίας</foreign>),
                  or those again who had hidden themselves in the cities and in the villages, or in
                  villas, were in great sorrow and sore need, since for a space of so many years
                  there was none to give them the communion of the lifegiving mysteries. But God,
                  who saw the distress, did not neglect in accordance with his mercy to give a
                  little refreshing to his church, though in distant regions, by means again of
                  another <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/50">John</persName>, who also was
                  in truth <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/50">John</persName>, of whom
                  also we determined to compose a history separately,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a37" target="#n37" n="37"/> that we may not protract the history to a great
                  length; while we have also not sought to comprise any of the rest of the
                  afflictions of this saint and of his conflicts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">àgών</foreign>) and of his asceticism, and of his conduct moreover and of his
                  abstinence in our history, inasmuch as it is endless, but we have rapidly run
                  through these points, which are patent to him who knows all. By the <pb type="vol" n="526"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="324"/>prayer of him who presents them<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a38" target="#n38" n="38"/> and of all saints like him, who present propiatory
                  fruits to God, may he visit his church in mercy, and be gracious to us her
                  children, who through our sins have made ourselves sons who provoke, and may they
                  be expiated by the blood of the only God over all for ever and ever. </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-24">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-24.1" n="2"> The history of the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/50">John</persName> bishop of the city of
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/200">Thella</placeName> is ended.
               </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 311, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Constantina. See the longer life by Elijah in C. S. O. tom. XXV (1), and cf.
               'Zach Rh'., VIII, 5. He was commonly called Bar Q (wr s w s (C. S. C. O., IV, p. 144;
               cf. 'Dion'. ap. Kleyn, <foreign>Bijdrage</foreign>, p.70), and is author of 2 sets of
               canons published by Lamy (<foreign>Diss. de Symporum fide</foreign>. Louvain, 1859)
               and Kuberczyk (Berlin, 1901) and translated by F. Nau (<foreign>Anc. Litt. Can.
                  Syr.</foreign>, fasc. 2, 1906).</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 311, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 1, 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 311, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>II Cor., XI, 21-29.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 312, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Really 2 years (Vit., p. 56). As his episcopate began after Justin's
               accession (id., p. 50), his expulsion was probably in 521.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 312, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Rom., I, 25.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 312, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Sic.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 313, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This sojourn is not mentioned by Elijah.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 313, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., V, 11, 12.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 313, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>The time must be exaggerated even if the persecution is dated from 519,
               since the author was ordained by John in 529 (p. 319) and he had then been performing
               ordinations for some time.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 314, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 314, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ezra,, V, 2; Hagg., I, 14.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 315, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I John., IV, 18.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 316, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Severus of Antioch.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 316, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>I cannot reconcile this with the statement that he ordained no one who could
               not write. V. D. and L.'s interpretation of the writing and signing as a repudiation
               of the synod (though it has some confirmation from p. 320) seems to me at variace
               both with the Syr. and with the context; cf. also p. 319.</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 317, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Arzanene. This was in Persian territory; see p. 145 and p. 340.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 317, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>This usually means the province of Phoenice Maritima.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 317, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>That J. was at Marde the author tells us in ch. 15 (p. 228); but he does not
               plainly state it here, nor is it mentioned by Elijah. See also Sev., <title>Select
                  Letters</title>, V, 14.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 318, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I Kings, XIX, 14.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 318, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., XXV, 14-30.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 318, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Acc. to Elijah (p. 35, 59) John and 7 other bishops went to Constantinople
               by the emperor's orders. It is strange that our author omits this.</note>
                <note xml:id="n21" target="#a21" n="21">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 319, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>529.</note>
                <note xml:id="n22" target="#a22" n="22">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 319, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>This probably menas that he divided it into an inner and an outer garment;
               ch. ch. 36 (f. 97 r' a), 49 (f. 116, r' b), 58 (f. 135 v' b). A similar story is told
               of James (ch. 49).</note>
                <note xml:id="n23" target="#a23" n="23">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 319, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n24" target="#a24" n="24">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 320, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Acc. to Elijah (p. 61, 62) he ordained bps. also, though no names or sees
               are given. From ch. 50 one would suppose that James and Theodore were the first
               Monophysite bps. ordained after the schism. E. mentions 4 other bps. as associated
               with John.</note>
                <note xml:id="n25" target="#a25" n="25">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 320, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>He was arrested in Persia and extradited (Vit., p. 68 ff.).</note>
                <note xml:id="n26" target="#a26" n="26">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 320, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>No tortures are mentioned by Elijah, and the word is probably not to be
               understood literally.</note>
                <note xml:id="n27" target="#a27" n="27">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 321, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>He was arrested 1 Feb., 537 (<title>Vit.</title> p. 69), reached Nisibis 2
               days later (id., p. 69, 70), remained there 30 days (id., p. 74), occupied 30 days in
               the journey to Antioch (id. p. 86), and died 6 Feb., 538 (id., p. 94). His
               imprisonment at Antioch therefore lasted 10 m. 2 d.</note>
                <note xml:id="n28" target="#a28" n="28">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 321, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n29" target="#a29" n="29">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 321, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Eph., VI, 14-16.</note>
                <note xml:id="n30" target="#a30" n="30">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 321, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Corr. from <hi rend="singleQuotes">strangers</hi>. The ref. (it is not a
               quotation) must be to Rom., V (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μέχρι 'Ρώμης θηριομαχώ....
                  ένδεδέμενος δέκα λεοπάρδοις</foreign>).</note>
                <note xml:id="n31" target="#a31" n="31">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 321, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>Sic.</note>
                <note xml:id="n32" target="#a32" n="32">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 322, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic.</note>
                <note xml:id="n33" target="#a33" n="33">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 322, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Acc. to Elijah (p. 88, 90, 92) there were at first 4, one was removed and
               afterwards brought back, and two were persuaded to leave.</note>
                <note xml:id="n34" target="#a34" n="34">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 322, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>This refers to Cyrus, a presbyter of Amida, who is said to have been burnt
               in the <foreign>tetrapylon</foreign> by bp. Abraham ('Zach Rh.,' X, 3; B.O., II, p.
               52; Mich., p. 272).</note>
                <note xml:id="n35" target="#a35" n="35">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 323, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ezek., VII, 16.</note>
                <note xml:id="n36" target="#a36" n="36">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 323, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ch. 25.</note>
                <note xml:id="n37" target="#a37" n="37">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 324, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. the afflictions.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
