<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/817">John of Hephaestopolis</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/816"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/818"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/817 -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-52" n="25">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-25">
                    <head type="main">Next the Twenty-Fifth History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John</persName> Bishop of the City Of
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2788">Hephaestu</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> In <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, Who
                  Repeats the Conflicts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of the Holy
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1813">John</persName> Who Precedes
                  Him.</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-25.1" n="1"> Since the purpose of our work and the course of our
                  history aims at showing and describing the circumstances of the perfect lives
                  which the saints lived, therefore we say that in the order of our history we will
                  insert spiritual pastors,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> and will
                  also in our work state the circumstances of their activity <pb n="527"/>
                        <pb n="325"/>in God's church, since they also were complete and perfect in both
                  forms of beauty;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> and for this
                  reason, though we seem to be passing from one subject to another, we did not think
                  it alien to the excellent purpose to describe and hand down to remembrance for the
                  glory of God the life that was practised by these divine men also. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-25.2" n="2"> This blessed man again, the great and divine <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John</persName> the bishop, was by his birth
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) a <persName>Syrian</persName>, that
                  is a Palestinian, from tlhe city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/87">Gaza</placeName>, and he lived in a great <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2832">convent</placeName>convent called that of
                  father <persName>Peter the Iberian</persName>, the doer of great and apostolic
                     signs.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> This <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2832">convent</placeName> was expelled with the
                  rest, and came into the territory of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2734">Alexandria</placeName>; and there it lived
                  in a place called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/473">Ennaton</placeName> which means <hi rend="singleQuotes">ninth</hi>, viz.
                     miles;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> and there the saint dwelt
                  with the rest of his <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2832">convent</placeName>, living a devout life and following great and divine
                  practices. While the church was still at peace in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2734">Alexandria</placeName>, and the blessed
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/784">Theodosius</persName> was seated
                  on his throne,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> he heard of his
                  manner of life and of his teaching, and sent and seized him and made him bishop in
                  one of the cities of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> which is called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2788">Hephaestu</placeName>. After a period of
                  such-and-such a number<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> of <pb n="528"/>
                        <pb n="326"/>years during which the blessed man had distinguished
                  himself in his pastorate, to which he had been called by the providence of God
                  against his own will, preparations for persecutions were then stirred up against
                  her whom one of the doctors names <quote>the <persName>Egyptian</persName>
                     virgin</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> and severe
                  fighting and much slaughter took place in it, as is common in that great city; and
                  the blessed archbishop <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/784">Theodosius</persName> with the rest of the eminent men of his jurisdiction
                     were<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> driven from their sees, and
                  they were also invited to the royal city and went up thither through certain
                  eminent men attached to the court, the adversaries thinking that by threats or
                  blandishments they might perhaps bring them to communicate with them.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> And, when they resisted strenuously
                  and they were unable to overcome the constancy that was in their souls, a
                     well-known<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> and cruel place of
                  exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>) was then given to the holy
                  archbishop himself and the whole of his company (<foreign xml:lang="grc">συνοδία</foreign>), the bishops with the most eminent clergy (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χλήρος</foreign>), about three hundred of them, in the interior
                  of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2854">Thrace</placeName> a day's
                  journey (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μανσίων</foreign>) off, a certain fortress
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">xάoτρa</foreign>) called Dercus, to which also we
                  often used to go to visit the same saints, as well as the blessed man the perfect
                  and great old man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName>
                  the celebrated <persName>Syrian</persName>
                        <pb n="529"/>
                        <pb n="327"/>from the country of Sophanene,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> who also was confined with them; and thenceforth they
                  were kept in custody there, though the Christ-loving <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">Theodora</persName>, who was perhaps
                  appointed queen by God to be a support for the persecuted against the cruelty of
                  the times, showed great attention to them. as well as the other persecuted men
                  everywhere, supplying them with provisions and liberal allowances (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άναλώματα</foreign>). </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-25.3" n="3"> While these men were suffering distress there, and every
                  where also the believers in all quarters were similarly suffering, they used to
                  betake themselves from all quarters to the royal city itself, firstly on account
                  of the persecutions in all quarters, and secondly for the sake of ordination
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροτονία</foreign>), as there was absolutely no man
                  to extend a hand of ordination to any believer in the whole Roman territory as far
                  as the Persian frontier; and accordingly many used to go to the same saints in
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2854">Thrace</placeName>, lamenting
                  and representing their trouble; but even there they gained no hearing, as it was
                  indeed in truth impossible for them to live if an ordination (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροτονία</foreign>) were performed there, if the adversaries
                  heard of it. But this holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John</persName>, when he heard these things, would shed bitter tears every day
                  for the distress of <persName>Christ</persName>'s <pb n="530"/>
                        <pb n="328"/>church, insomuch he that would often say in our presence: <quote>We for our part
                     have been named pastors of God's church to no purpose, since we have suffered
                     her lambs to be torn by wolves, and have come and sat down by ourselves, and
                     have not consented to die for the sake of religion. What is the benefit that we
                     ourselves are now doing to God's church? for lo! we are unwilling to cure or
                     heal even those that come to us buffeted and bruised from a journey of sixty
                     days</quote>. And these things he would say weeping, <quote>I stand in awe of
                     him who is the head;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> otherwise,
                     as <persName>Christ</persName> lives, nothing would have prevented me from
                     performing ordination (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροτονία</foreign>) in the
                     great church of the city if I had found opportunity, or in an open space (?)
                        (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χώρος</foreign>) in the city in the sight of all
                     men</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> When many were
                  coming every day, and he continually heard the same things and could not contain
                  himself, he was moved with zeal and his spirit was roused, and he said: <quote>Far
                     be it from me in the Lord's name to hold aloof longer and pay no heed to the
                     affliction of <persName>Christ</persName>'s flock which was bought by his
                     precious blood;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> for, even if I
                     die on its behalf, it is a boast to me</quote>. Then he concocted pretexts, and
                  under pretexts of illnesses he went and begged the patriarch and the custodians
                  for permission to go into the city to see physicians; and, because they heard <pb n="531"/>
                        <pb n="329"/>mention of illness, therefore they did not prevent him
                  from going, and this matter also about the cause of his coming was made known to
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">the queen</persName>; and by
                  divine dispensation she also received him with great joy, and she gave orders that
                  spacious quarters (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μέτατον</foreign>) also should be given
                  him in the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2739">great
                     mansion</placeName> called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2739">Anthemiu</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> and an
                  allowance (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άνάλωμα</foreign>) also for him and his slave
                  should be assigned to him there. And thenceforth the will and the zeal of the
                  blessed man found expression; and from that time companies of those who were in
                  distress, and had been for a long time beaten and buffeted and had none to relieve
                  them, betook themselves to him, and he would dismiss them all<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> and they would return to their own
                  countries with joy, while he also anointed many altars that had been set up for a
                  long time to be anointed and go to the countries, and himself also fixed an altar,
                  and he was filled with great boldness (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>)
                  showing keen enthusiasm and confidence that contends with death. When he had stood
                  up and become openly known, envy like <persName>Cain</persName>'s was sown in the
                  hearts of many who were inside and not outside; and they used to address mandates
                  to him, saying, <quote>We are standing in a lion's mouth, and you are causing him
                     to rend us all and cast us away in one hour</quote>. <pb n="532"/>
                        <pb n="330"/>But he said, <quote>As for the lion that is coming let no man stand before him;
                     let him send him against me myself only; since it is I as you say that have
                     provoked him, and God will do as he wishes. The mouths of lions are wont to be
                     closed by command from on high<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/>
                        </quote> And so he did not cease from his zealousness. But afterwards they
                  wrote to his patriarch also as well to inhibit him. But the saint, who saw his
                  zeal, and on his own side also was not displeased by the saving and refreshing of
                  the believers, passed over the sayings that were concocted against the same
                  blessed man without notice, saying, <quote>He has gone away from my presence, and
                     is in the city, and the queen also has received him; and she further knows that
                     I have not ordered him to do such things.</quote> And so he took no account of
                  the matter as one that knew it and did not know it. But the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John</persName> would accept all who came
                  from all quarters, that is on the testimony of those who presented them; and,
                     though<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/> they were strangers, he
                  did not immediately apply a hand of ordination without witnesses and persons to
                  present. But, when those whose envy...<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/> saw it, and he also made them hostile to him, who were believers,
                  members of his company (<foreign xml:lang="grc">συνοδία</foreign>), and some of
                  them also even bishops, they <pb n="533"/>
                        <pb n="331"/>went and told <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">the queen</persName> about him, having
                  concocted a petition purporting to come from him that she would give him an order
                  to leave the city for a short time. And she, inasmuch as she thought that he was
                  perhaps in need of recreation, in order to gratify him, gave the order, and she
                  also wrote, <quote>Go</quote>. But these men took the order, and formed a plan to
                  catch the blessed man by terror by means of the order, in that they went and they
                  say to him as if speaking in the person (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>) of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">the
                     queen</persName>, <quote>Do not linger another hour in this city or see my
                     face; otherwise you will die. And the order has reached yourself (?), lest you
                     die an evil death; since you have been accused to the king, and he ordered your
                     death.</quote> But the intelligent man, inasmuch as he was in truth ready for
                  death, determined <quote>If I depart, be it to death or to life, I will not depart
                     before I go into the palace (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>) and
                     know the truth</quote>. Then he made these men think that he had been
                  frightened and was packing his things to depart; and he went out and left them,
                  and went down and came to the palace (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>)
                  without these men heing avare of it; and he went in confidently before <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">the queen</persName> with the great
                  boldness (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>) of the heavenly King,
                  manifesting wrath also and threats against the king and queen on account of all
                  the persecution of the believers. And, when <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">the queen</persName> saw him, she was
                  alarmed at his wrath, and says: <quote>Who <pb n="534"/>
                            <pb n="332"/>has injured
                     you, sir? What is this affair?</quote>. And he said : <quote>Who has injured
                     and disturbed me or God's church except you and your husband?</quote> And she
                  was astonished, and said : <quote>For what reason? Who has said anything to
                     you?</quote> He says to her : <quote>You<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a21" target="#n21" n="21"/> ordered my death, and your<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a22" target="#n22" n="22"/> order came to me to leave the city hastily; and what more do you
                     want to learn?</quote> When she learned that it was not at his instigation that
                  they had come and received the document from her, and that<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a23" target="#n23" n="23"/> she herself had written in order to gratify him, she
                  issued an order, and these enemies quickly came, while she said, <quote>Whom else
                     was it your purpose to deceive except God and me and this saint?</quote> Then,
                  when she threatened them with such things as their tricks deserved, the blessed
                  man with great entreaty delivered them from death, and did not requite them
                  according to their deeds. But on the matter of ordinations (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροτονία</foreign>) she said to him : <quote>See that you
                     remain within the palace (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>),<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a24" target="#n24" n="24"/> lest trial in trutlh come upon
                     you. Remain still and keep quiet like your companions and do not make priests
                     in this city</quote>. He said to her, <quote>I will not do it; and, that you
                     may know that I have no desire for this business, I was just about to request
                     your majesty to order me to go out to a villa oustide for a secret retreat of
                     thirty or forty days, as I now <pb n="535"/>
                            <pb n="333"/>also request, since I
                     nam indeed ill</quote>. And she on her side gave him his will, and also
                  dismissed him, since he was indeed really weak in bodily health, and, his body
                  being greatly afflicted, he constantly suffered from diseases. But the blessed man
                  was determined that, if anyone interfered with him in the way of preventing him
                  from extending a hand of ordination to the believers within, he would go out and
                  visit them himself in the district where they were, in the fervour of his
                  enthusiasm; which also he did not delay to do, but under the appearance of having
                  gone out to the villa he went on board a ship, and went out first to Lydia, and
                  thence to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2746">Asia</placeName>, in
                  which there were in fact many convents of believers; and thus he visited in all
                  districts and passed through them; and he came down as far as <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/196">Tarsus</placeName> in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/55">Cilicia</placeName>, while he never spent a
                  whole day in a place, but night and day devoted himself to travelling in all
                  directions. And thereupon the report of him was heard over all that land; and,
                  while the report of him was reaching the bishop of the district<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a25" target="#n25" n="25"/> or of the city, he himself did what
                  he required and passed from it; since before he entered a district he would learn
                  about the believers, and he would send a message two or three days beforehand that
                  the men of every <pb n="536"/>
                        <pb n="334"/>place should assemble and be ready
                  along his route<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a26" target="#n26" n="26"/> (?) at one day's
                  journey (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μανσίων</foreign>) from one another; and thus he
                  visited as far as <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/196">Tarsus</placeName>, intending to go down over the whole of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/486">Syria</placeName>. And there they learned
                  about him; and there was great commotion, and much searching through the whole
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/586">city</placeName> on his account;
                  and so he left his things there, and took his departure like a poor man, and was
                  not caught. When he saw that the countries had been thrown into commotion, he
                  thought <quote>Before search is made and the commotion reaches the king, I will
                     return</quote>; and so he came back after two months, and he went straight to
                  the villa, as if he had not gone anywhere. And he sent a letter to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">the queen</persName>, saying, <quote>Since
                     I, my lady, have on account of ill health not been able to come in and make
                     obeisance to you all this time, send me by letter what you wish to say</quote>.
                  And she on her side consented, and sent him a present also there. And during the
                  same days a letter from the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2274">patriarch</persName> of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a27" target="#n27" n="27"/> and all the rest of the bishops was brought in to the
                  king which stated, <quote>One of the bishops who are there has come out, and has
                     thrown the whole church into confusion, and has performed ordination (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροτονία</foreign>) and given penances (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κανόνας</foreign>) and absolution,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a28" target="#n28" n="28"/> from the royal <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/586">city</placeName> as far as <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/486">Syria</placeName>
                        </quote>. And, when a
                  great search had been made, he <pb n="537"/>
                        <pb n="335"/>said: <quote>Perhaps it
                     is so-and-so who lhas not been in the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/586">city</placeName> all this time</quote>.
                  Then by the grace of God no ordinary person, but <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">the queen</persName> herself, came in to
                  give evidence on behalf of the blessed man, saying: <quote>That man is sick and
                     laid up in such-and-such a villa; for indeed it was by my order also that he
                     went out thither; and only a few days ago he sent to me</quote>. And, when
                  everyone testified that he was in his place, they dropped the matter. And so,
                  vhile tlhese men wrote forcibly, they gained no hearing, and a message was sent to
                  them to say, <quote>If you can, arrest him, for perhaps he is an impostor. No one
                     lhas left this place</quote>. Again on another occasion, when this had been
                  forgotten and had blown over, he succeeded in getting an order given him to go as
                  far as the hot spring<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a29" target="#n29" n="29"/> on account of
                  his diseases, and he was sent away; and he went out and passed over all the
                  islands of the sea-coast<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a30" target="#n30" n="30"/> and those
                  within the sea as far as <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/714">Cyprus</placeName> and visited the believers, and as far as <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/53">Caesarea</placeName>; and so he returned
                  without anyone discovering it. Again after this (on which same visitation we
                  ourselves encountered him), he made a visitation and went down as far as
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1534">Rhodes</placeName>, and there we
                  were privileged to see him. And, when he told us his intention, that he intended
                  to pass through <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2746">Asia</placeName> a
                  second time about six years after the <pb n="538"/>
                        <pb n="336"/>first, since we
                  were ourselves going up from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2734">Alexandria</placeName> to the royal city,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a31" target="#n31" n="31"/> he returned with us. And so, when we had travelled a
                  day's journey (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μανσίων</foreign>), at every lodging-place,
                  he would send envoys taken from the believers to go among them, and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a32" target="#n32" n="32"/> at every place we used to find from
                  a hundred and fifty and from two hundred assembled waiting for him. And thus we
                  passed through the cities and villages together; so that in the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2857">Tralles</placeName> inside the church,
                  while the clergy were performing the service, he made more than fifty priests.
                  Since we were a large party, and there were distinguished gentlemen among us, we
                  were given permission to occupy an upper space, in the upper
                     <foreign>catechumenia</foreign>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a33" target="#n33" n="33"/>
                  of the church; and so they would come up there three and five at a time, while men
                  stood at the doors and kept watch, and men who arranged these and sent them on,
                  and this while I myself was carrying the oblation and the sacrament,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a34" target="#n34" n="34"/> and he was standing and blessing and
                  administering the oblation and dismissing them, and those below were performing
                  the service; and I was amazed at the man's courage and fortitude. In the house of
                  Mar <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2803">John</placeName> at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/623">Ephesus</placeName> again the same, more
                  than seventy men <pb n="539"/>
                        <pb n="337"/>were assembled; and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a35" target="#n35" n="35"/>, they having been instructed to
                     assemble<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a36" target="#n36" n="36"/> by night in the open
                  space in the western court of the paved precinct (?) (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πλάκια</foreign>) of the same house of Mar <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2803">John</placeName>, he there ordained them by
                  night. And so from that place we again separated, he to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1529">Chios</placeName> and thence to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2734">Alexandria</placeName> and to Palestine,
                  and we to the royal city, wondering at the grace of God which had stirred up this
                  man to visit the believers, and had given him moreover [. . . . to]<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a37" target="#n37" n="37"/> the whole church, while all the time
                  that he had been away those who came to the city had been in distress and had been
                  waiting for him as a good hope and a granter of their requests. And he also
                  returned and came, and found many in distress and waiting for him; since, though
                  there were many others in the city itself, there was no man whosoever to stretch
                  out his hand to ordain by reason of his fear. These things, on account of the
                  abundance of his zeal and the greatness of the goodness of God with the man,
                  impelled us to stray into such a length of narrative, while we have repeated few
                  of his actions, such as relate to the method in which he carried out his
                  visitation, while on that which is indeed too great to tell, the subject of the
                  rest of his brave character and his humility, we have kept silence, lest <pb n="540"/>
                        <pb n="338"/>we exceed the fixed limit. These things which tend to
                  preserve the memory of these holy and zealous men mighty in conflicts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) on behalf of religion, the first <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John</persName> and further this second
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1813">John</persName>, we have
                  committed to the record of history, in the first place in order that the world may
                  [reap benefit] from the description [of...]<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a38" target="#n38" n="38"/> their ascetic and virtuous life, and in the second in order to make
                  known the graciousness of him who saved his church by his precious blood, how in
                  this time of its distress also he set up these two pillars of light in it to
                  comfort it; by whose holy prayers may schisms and strifes be done away from within
                  it until the end, Amen! And may mercy light upon the sinner who wrote it through
                  their prayers. Amen!<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a39" target="#n39" n="39"/>
                    </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-25">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-25.1" n="4"> The history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1813">John</persName> bishop of the city of
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2788">Hephaestu</placeName> in
                  <placeName>Egypt</placeName> is ended. </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 324, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. <foreign xml:lang="grc">'Ηφαίστου πόλις</foreign>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 324, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. bishops</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 325, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. the pastoral and the ascetic.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 325, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Usually called the monastery of Theodore ('Zach Rh.,' VII, 10; see
                  <title>Vit. Petr.</title> Ib., p. 134).</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 325, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 325, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>535/6.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 325, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>Not more than 1 1/3, Th. returned to Alexandria not earlier than July, 535,
               and was expelled not later than Dec, 536 (<title>Byz. Zeitschr.</title>, XII, p.
               494).</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 326, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I do not know the source of this quotation.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 326, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 326, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>See Introd., p. V.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 326, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">definite</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 327, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See ch. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 328, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. Theodosius.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 328, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Since our author was not in CP. between 535 and 540 (Introd., p. IV, V), and
               appy. did not meet John till 541 (p. 336, n. 1), these words seem to be recorded out
               of place.</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 328, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Acts, XX, 28; I Pet., I, 19.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 329, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. <foreign xml:lang="grc">τά Άνθεμίου</foreign>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 329, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>We are left to understand that he ordained them; see below.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 330, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Dan., VI, 22; Hebr. XI, 33.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 330, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>We should expect 'because'; but the meaning perh. is that: though there was
               in the circumstances a difficulty in getting proper testimony, he would not dispense
               with it.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 330, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Some words have fallen out.</note>
                <note xml:id="n21" target="#a21" n="21">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 332, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Pl.</note>
                <note xml:id="n22" target="#a22" n="22">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 332, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sing.</note>
                <note xml:id="n23" target="#a23" n="23">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 332, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n24" target="#a24" n="24">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 332, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. the palace of Anthemius.</note>
                <note xml:id="n25" target="#a25" n="25">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 333, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. the province. The metropolitan is therefore meant.</note>
                <note xml:id="n26" target="#a26" n="26">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 334, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This is appy. the meaning. We should perh. read ; or we might render <hi rend="singleQuotes">every place of its territory</hi>. V.D. and L. pass over the
               word.</note>
                <note xml:id="n27" target="#a27" n="27">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 334, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ephraim.</note>
                <note xml:id="n28" target="#a28" n="28">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 334, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. to converts from Diphysitism.</note>
                <note xml:id="n29" target="#a29" n="29">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 335, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Syr. <hi rend="singleQuotes">Hamimtha</hi>. Probably some hot spring near
               Constantinople is meant, not the well-known Hamimtha in Mesopotamia (p. 224; ch.
               35).</note>
                <note xml:id="n30" target="#a30" n="30">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 335, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Phoenice Maritima.</note>
                <note xml:id="n31" target="#a31" n="31">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 336, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This must have been in 541 (see Introd., p, V, which throws back the 1st
               journey to 535; but, as Theodosius did not leave Alexandria before the end of 536,
               the 6 years must be one of the author's inaccuracies. See also p. 328, n.2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n32" target="#a32" n="32">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 336, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n33" target="#a33" n="33">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 336, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Women's gallery; see Ducange, s. V. <foreign xml:lang="grc">κατηχούμενα</foreign>. Ms. q t n k w m l y w n.</note>
                <note xml:id="n34" target="#a34" n="34">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 336, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Viz. as a deacon.</note>
                <note xml:id="n35" target="#a35" n="35">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 337, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n36" target="#a36" n="36">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 337, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n37" target="#a37" n="37">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 337, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. torn.</note>
                <note xml:id="n38" target="#a38" n="38">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 338, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. torn.</note>
                <note xml:id="n39" target="#a39" n="39">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 338, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>This is almost certainly a scribe's addition, but is written as part of the
               chapter.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
