<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/820">Mary the Mourner</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/819"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/821"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/820 -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-28" n="28">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-28">
               <head type="main">Next the Twenty-Eighth<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> History,
                  of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1881">Mary</persName> the
                  Anchorite.</head>
               <ab xml:id="section-28.1" n="1"> Therefore neither was the history of this holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1881">Mary</persName> unworthy of admiration, a
                  woman who by nature only bore the form of females, but herself also too bore in
                  herself the character and soul and will not only of ordinary men, but of mighty
                  and valiant men. </ab>
               <ab xml:id="section-28.2" n="2"> This blessed woman therefore also was the daughter of
                  distinguished persons and a high family (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>)
                  in the world. Now there was a great old man of God who was living as a recluse in
                  a village bordering on their village, a man far advanced in years; and to this
                  saint the blessed woman's people used frequently to come, she being with them,
                  when she was ten years old. And, when the damsel saw the serious character of the
                  old man, solemn feeling was stirred in her mind, and she despised all the world
                  with all that is in it, meditating in herself and saying: <quote>Lo! they are rich
                     who <pb n="560"/>
                     <pb n="358"/>possess the world that passes not away for ever
                     and ever, not we wretched persons among whom, as soon as a man has become rich
                     and proud<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> and boastful, and
                     believed himself to be lord of his own riches, death has come and cast him down
                     into <foreign>sheol</foreign>, and others have taken away his toil in which he
                     toiled from his childhood even to his death, and which has perhaps been amassed
                     by sin, and the sin has remained with him, and the riches have become the
                     property of others. Lo! then the things that are in this world are all deceit
                     and vanity. For what reason do we not voluntarily leave a thing which we must
                     in any case leave even if we do not desire it? and for what reason do we not
                     become as this old man? Is not this<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> a human being? Far be it from me henceforth to let the world deceive
                     me, and refrain from following the course of life of this old man</quote>. And
                  from that time the damsel's mind became inflamed, and she cut herself off
                  completely from eating flesh and from drinking wine; and she began to fast and
                  pray, and to run in the road of excellence. But her people, when they saw these
                  things, used to reprove her, and to press her to continue eating flesh and
                  drinking wine; and she would not obey, having cast her body, and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> all the enticements. of youth, and
                  the adornment of childhood behind her, and begun to walk <pb n="561"/>
                  <pb n="359"/>soundly in the lofty road of anchoritism and asceticism. Since she had been
                  betrothed by them to a certain rich man, they began as people of the world to be
                  distressed and to think thoughts which were not theirs only but those of the hater
                  of good things also as well, <quote>Let us rise and make a wedding-feast for her,
                     lest she run away and go to a monastery, and we lose the man who was to take
                     her to wife</quote>. And, when they on their side had begun to prepare and make
                  ready the things required for the wedding, the blessed woman became aware of it
                  and said to them: <quote>Do not toil<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> to no purpose and lose your money; for my part I hope in him who invited the
                     pure and holy and virgin to recline at his eternal wedding-feast that ceases
                     not that I shall make no bodily partnership, nor corrupt the purity of my soul
                     by fleshly conjunction with a mortal man</quote>. But, when this incited these
                  people all the more, so that they met together (?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> in order to constrain her, she left them and went to a
                  monastery; and she shaved her head and took the habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>). And from that time she took that holy old man as her model
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τύπος</foreign>) in all things, in standing and
                  abstinence and vigils and eating once in three days, while she also made for
                  herself a hair-shirt and sandals (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σανδάλια</foreign>), and
                  <pb n="562"/>
                  <pb n="360"/>moreover from the first day on which she received the
                  mark never again cut her hair, so that it became long and abundant, until it was
                  wound round her four times up and down, so that at last (it is said) it became<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> a great weight. And she also
                  distinguished herself in the conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of
                  persecution for fifteen years, no longer passing night-vigils, but vigils lasting
                  even a week, and ten days, and then she would taste something. And, when she had
                  walked strongly and heroically in the road of righteousness for thirty years, she
                  finished her course and received the crown<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> earned by her life, and fell asleep in peace. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-28">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-28.1" n="3"> The history of the 
                  blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1881">Mary</persName> the 
                  anchorite<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> is ended. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 357, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ms. om.; see Introd., p. IX.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 358, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ms. om.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 358, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">This man is not</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 358, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>Ms. om.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 359, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ms. <hi rend="singleQuotes">lament</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 359, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>This is perh. corrupt.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 360, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ms. om.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 360, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>II Tim., IV, 7,8.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
