<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/821">Malka</title>
                <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/820"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/822"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/821 -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-29" n="29">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-29">
                    <head type="main">The Twenty-Ninth(?).<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> History,
                     of<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/>
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1862">Malkha</persName> the Mendicant and
                     Stranger<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/>
                    </head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-29.1" n="1"> Once when we were in 
                        our <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> adjacent to the city of
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> 
                        before it was driven into banishment
                  by the heretics, at the time of the second <pb type="vol" n="563"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="361"/>Theshri<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> 
                        a <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1862">certain stranger</persName> arrived among us,
                  clad in dirty and much-worn raiment; and, when he had been received and been
                  required to anathematize the heresy that prevailed at that time, as it was the
                  custom to require, he stood with us at vespers and at table in silence and without
                  speaking, now and again looking furtively to heaven. And so, when he had been
                  hospitably received and his soul had been refreshed, he simply refrained from
                  conversation and filled his mouth with<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> 
                        thanksgiving. But some of the houseworkers (?),<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> 
                        when they saw his habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) 
                        and his downward looks and the indication provided by his
                  practices, recognised his character and said to the rest, <quote>This <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1862">stranger</persName> 
                      is in truth a servant of God</quote>. And the man who said it himself came up and continued asking him
                  and saying: <quote>Whence comes your holiness, father?</quote>. But he continued
                  looking downward and sighing. He says to him: <quote>Forgive me, sir. I am a
                     miserable stranger</quote>. He says to him: <quote>All of us, father, are
                     strangers, and sojourners.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> But
                     we wish to learn whence you come</quote>. But he on his side <pb type="vol" n="564"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="362"/>said : <quote>Why? What need is there to inquire? When you see that I
                     am a son of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1560">Adam</persName>,
                     know that I am dust like <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1560">Adam</persName> who was taken from dust, and upon whom through his sin
                     sentence was given whither he should return. Lo! I come from him if you wish to
                     learn; for I have no other place here; but pray that I may have one</quote>.
                  These things that blessed man said with emotion when he was questioned, and ceased
                  speaking. And so a place was prepared for him according to the custom in the case
                  of strangers, and he fell asleep like everyone else. But there were some whose
                  sleep was wakeful, and who used to watch the brotherhood, who<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> after the house was at rest would
                  stand in different places, while some bowed themselves down, and some knelt, and
                  some again went outside, and so knelt in corners (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γωνία</foreign>) and in corridors (<foreign xml:lang="grc">στοά</foreign>),
                  and prayed; and they saw that this blessed man from the weariness caused by his
                  journey fell asleep at once; and again it happened that in the middle of his sleep
                  he raised his head and saw that the servitors<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> were not yet gathered in and all had not fallen
                  asleep, and he waited a short time; and, when he saw that everyone was gathered
                  in, that he might not show himself to be up, he wrapped himself in his coat, and
                  fell upon his face on his rug; and this while he was weeping gently that no one
                  might hear, until he heard the sound of the first bell while the blessed men <pb type="vol" n="565"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="363"/>were marking him the whole night. And, when he heard the
                  sound of the bell, he stretched himself on his rug, and was rising with everyone
                  else just as if he had been heavily sunk in his sleep. And, when the houseworkers
                  had risen and recited the service,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/>
                  the same again went on till morning, and thus he would weep lying on his face, in
                  order that he might not rise and show his labour to anyone, until his eyes became
                  swollen and greatly inflamed. And in the morning, when <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3183">the archimandrite</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> and the houseworkers also<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> saw his eyes, they say to him:
                     <quote>What has happened to your eyes, our father?</quote>. But he on his side
                  said to them: <quote>The air (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άήρ</foreign>) of yesterlay
                     affected me on the road and therefore my eyes swelled<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/>
                        </quote>. But those who had seen the manner in which
                  he had been employed all the night continued saying <quote>Leave the blessed man
                     alone</quote>. During the day he went out into the precinct of the monastery,
                  and found a concealed spot, and there he bowed himself till the midday bell,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> while they were seeking him all over
                  the monastery; and then as they were going round they found him howed down and
                  weeping. They say to him: <quote>Be so good<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> as to go in, father; for <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3183">the archimandrite</persName> is asking
                     for you</quote>. He came; and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3183">the archimandrite</persName> said to him: <quote>Where have you been,
                     father?</quote>. He says to him: <pb type="vol" n="566"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="364"/>
                        <quote>Forgive me,
                     sir. I was going round the garden and seeing the trees</quote>. <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3183">The archimandrite</persName> says to him:
                     <quote>I also know that you desire to see the trees of the garden,
                     father</quote>. Then with the usual kindness he bade him, inasmuch as he was
                  worn out with labour, go to rest before the vesper hour. But he fell on his face
                  and continued entreating and saying: <quote>Because I was greatly worn out
                     yesterday, I both ate inordinately last night and caused a pain in my stomach
                        (<foreign xml:lang="grc">στόμαχος</foreign>); but for God's sake allow me to
                     wait with the houseworkers, in order that my previous food may digest itself,
                     and so go to rest with them</quote>. And, when he had pressed him strongly and
                  he would not give way, he allowed him to do as he wished. And the blessed man,
                  when the service was over, went to the corner (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γωνία</foreign>) where he had been before; and so with his hands stretched out
                  to heaven in the form (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τύπος</foreign>) of a cross he
                  continued crying with tears and saying: <quote>Who is there, my Lord, who is
                     sufficient to entreat thee for me the sinner, except thy great mercy that is
                     poured out upon our race (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>)? I am
                     ungrateful, my Lord, and a provoker. Come, I pray, to my aid. Abandon me not, I
                     pray thee, my Lord. Save me, my Lord, and let me be at peace, before I go and
                     am no more. Save my life from the corruption of my sins, Lord my God. <quote>Be
                        pleased, Lord, to deliver me</quote>
                            <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/>
                            <pb type="vol" n="567"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="365"/>from the confusions and falseness and the
                     deceitfulness of this world, and from all that is in it; and have mercy upon me
                     in the day of thy judgment, with all the rest of thy servants, for the sake of
                     thy holy Name, my trust from my boyhood</quote>. While that blessed man was
                  thus mightily crying with many tears, and thought that there were no persons near
                  or seeing or hearing him, some men were standing behind the wall, and listening to
                  the sound of his sighs, and marvelling at his sorrow and tears before God. After
                  three days, when he had seen the doings and practices of the convent, that even
                  the very houseworkers also were eager to run with all their might after practices
                  of excellence, he made up his mind to pass the winter in the same <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, and at the coming of
                  the milder season to return to the same mountains. And he came to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3183">the archimandrite</persName> and said to
                  him: <quote>For my part, sir, I intended on account of my bodily weakness and fear
                     of the winter and the cold to go down to the south; and, since perhaps our Lord
                     sent me to be with you this winter, if it is convenient to you I will stay with
                     you this winter; and, if so be I am alive and our Lord is willing, in
                        <placeName>Nisan</placeName>
                            <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/>
                     I will <pb type="vol" n="568"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="366"/>return toward the north</quote>. And <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3183">the archimandrite</persName> and all the
                  other members of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> also rejoiced, since this was indeed their custom
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμος</foreign>), that, if a stranger wished to stay
                  as long as a year and two years and ten, they rejoiced over him, honouring him in
                  every respect like <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3183">the
                     archimandrite</persName>. And they consented and they say to him : <quote>We
                     beg you, our father, to be with us<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/> and edify us by the sight of you, and by your helpful conversation</quote>.
                  And from that time he determined to remain; and so he thenceforth doubled his
                  labour, keeping silence and hiding his head and weeping. Even when eating and
                  sitting at table, even so also his tears could not be restrained, but he would eat
                  and bow his head down and weep; and so no words came rapidly out of his mouth
                  except prayer and thanksgiving, and unceasing sighs. When some time had passed,
                  those who cared about methods of life, and judged and repelled their thoughts,
                  used to go and beg him one by one to tell them a rule of life and an illustration
                  of the method of contending against the thoughts of the rebellious fiends. But he
                  in great humility would fall upon his face and make entreaty, saying:
                     <quote>Forgive me, <pb type="vol" n="569"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="367"/>brethren, for I am sick, and pray
                     for me; and, seek not such things at the hands of me a sinner. Be persuaded by
                     the blessed apostle who says: <quote>If a man hath not been able to rule his
                        own house aright, how is he capable of ruling God's church?.</quote>
                            <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/> And now I for my part am sitting
                     in the darkness of sin; but show your love and pray for me</quote>. And, when
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3183">the archimandrite</persName>
                  often pressed him to speak, he himself said to him at last <quote>Father, show
                     your love to God and pray for me, with all the rest of your <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>. For as for me the
                     day has come for me to set out on my journey, and I am not sufficient for
                     it</quote>. They, thinking that he meant <quote>I am setting out for the
                     mountains</quote>, say to him: <quote> Rest yourself, our father. It is still
                     winter and no man, can set out on a journey to-day</quote>. He says to them
                  weeping: <quote>Nay indeed, the winter has not yet come, but it is just coming; in
                     which as you say no man can either set out on a journey nor yet work.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a21" target="#n21" n="21"/> And now, my fathers and my
                     brothers, pray for me. This is my convent; for God sent me to you, that through
                     the remembrance of your petition I may find mercy in that day. My sins have
                     overtaken me and I could not see it. My brethren, pray on my behalf, that I may
                     escape from the torment. The end has overtaken me, and the day after tomorrow I
                     shall depart from this life to <pb type="vol" n="570"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="368"/>our Lord. Accordingly
                     I entreat you one and all to make entreaty on my behalf; and you yourselves
                     also, my brethren, be strong. You are running well.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a22" target="#n22" n="22"/> Perform this your life-service unto the end; for in
                     every matter about which you concern yourselves there is one object that is
                     sought. You know all; you are perfect in all; and you are able to admonish
                     others also. And therefore, my fathers and brothers, inasmuch as a few days ago
                     also your affection required of me to speak these words, now in order not to be
                     ungrateful for your affection and your good will, lo! I put you in mind of
                     these your principles, not teaching you, but<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a23" target="#n23" n="23"/> things on which you are meditating at all times.
                     Our Lord is at hand. Be anxious for nothing, but always let your prayers and
                     requests be made known before God's.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a24" target="#n24" n="24"/> For, <quote>when ye see all these things, know that it has reached
                        the door</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a25" target="#n25" n="25"/> For from
                     this time we must truly know that it has reached the door; for the word of him
                     who said it is not falsified. And again we know that this also is written,
                        <quote>There is great fear of falling into the hands of the living
                        God</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a26" target="#n26" n="26"/> and again
                        <quote>We shall all stand before that dread judgment-seat (<foreign xml:lang="grc">βήμα</foreign>) <pb type="vol" n="571"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="369"/>of
                        righteousness, that each one of us may be requited for that which has been
                        wrought by him, be it good or be it evil</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a27" target="#n27" n="27"/> Let us think upon these things, my brethren. Let
                     us, my beloved, fear the dread final hour. Let us dread the moment when each
                     one of us shall receive an account upon his fingers, and his hands shall be
                     hung up and his neck shall be laid bare and he shall be made an accuser against
                     himself in the presence of justice. For who shall contrive a means of shunning
                     or escaping that hour, since who is there who shall be hidden by his eloquence?
                     Who shall say <quote>Thou art innocent, my heart, and thou hast been purified
                        from sins</quote>?<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a28" target="#n28" n="28"/>
                     Accordingly, my brethren, inasmuch as we are all abundantly persuaded of these
                     things, let them be depicted before our eyes at all times, and written on the
                     tablets of our heart,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a29" target="#n29" n="29"/> that so,
                     while we rest before the grace that is full of mercy all the days of our life,
                     even if we are not capable of doing aught else, at that moment of trepidation
                     and fear it may spread its wings and cover us, and we may by it be delivered
                     from the eternal torment, of which we ought not to hear with indifference as if
                     it were a tale, but with great fear and mighty trembling</quote>. While then
                  that blessed man was saying all these things in the presence <pb type="vol" n="572"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="370"/>of us all amidst his many sighs, and amidst copious tears, with great
                  emotion and with many sobs, he caused us also to listen to him in great
                  astonishment at him, since we saw that no sign of bodily infirmity was to be seen
                  on him, and he confidently pronounced that after three days he would depart from
                  the body. While we were thus gathered together, for two days and nights he sat and
                  said the same things to us all; but on the third night he again requested that
                  prayer might be made for him and incense set, and he might receive absolution
                  while he wept and said: <quote>It is written <quote>None that liveth shall be
                        innocent before thee</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a30" target="#n30" n="30"/>
                     Therefore we must not trust in
                  ourselves.</quote>
                        <!-- This end quote not in Brooks but required by the sense. -->
                  And, when we had all knelt, and prayer had been made, and when the altar had been
                  opened, and incense set, and everyone was overpowered with sorrow on account of
                  the words spoken, he was standing and weeping, and at last he continued crying to
                  all of us: <quote>My brethren, pray for me; for I am not repeating my praises
                     before you; <quote>he who praiseth himself is not he who is approved, but he
                        whom God praiseth</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a31" target="#n31" n="31"/>
                     Upon me has come the end of death; and human praise is no longer needed by me,
                     nor yet honour; but, since God sent my sinfulness to you to bury my body, I
                     will not prevent <pb type="vol" n="573"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="371"/>any of you from knowing the things
                     that he worked with me by his help all my days. It is to-day thirty-nine years
                     that I have worn this habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>), on
                     mountains and in caves and among men; and, since I received the habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>), I have not possessed anght heside
                        <persName>Christ</persName>. No lie has come out of my lips; I have not
                     spoken evil words to men or reviled any man. My speech has been naught but as
                     our Lord said, <quote>Yea, yea</quote> and <quote>Nay, nay</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a32" target="#n32" n="32"/> I have not said
                        <quote>Yea</quote> unless it was in truth <quote>Yea</quote>, nor yet
                        <quote>Nea</quote> without it also being true. I have not sought anything
                     that would benefit me and harm another. I have not murmured against my God
                     during my troubles and distresses and he himself is my witness. This is the
                     time during which amid the troubles of pilgrimage (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ξενία</foreign>) I have not murmured in my heart against any man who did
                     not receive me and entertain me. The man who reviled me and drove me away was
                     not treated by me with less respect than the man who honoured and entertained
                     me. And these things, my brethren, I have repeated before you even as they are
                     manifest before God, because I saw that these objects lie before you too, and
                     not in order that you may imitate me, but let us all imitate
                        <persName>Christ</persName> our God the teacher of these things, because he
                     himself truly taught this humility in his person, and showed it to us. My <pb type="vol" n="574"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="372"/>brethren, pray for me and abide in peace. God keep
                     your community</quote>. And the blessed man went into the vestry<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a33" target="#n33" n="33"/> in order to pray and stretched
                  himself out and lay down there, while everyone was looking for him to come out.
                  And <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3183">the archimandrite</persName>
                  went in and saw him lying on a paving-stone and said to him: <quote>Father, be so
                        good<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a34" target="#n34" n="34"/> as to lie upon a
                     rug</quote>. And, when he had spoken to him, he gave up his soul to God. And on
                  this happening great fear fell upon everyone; and so in fear they brought the
                  blessed man out; and he was buried with a great procession of all the believers of
                  the city. May God whom he served for a long term of years magnify his memory with
                  that of the saints who did his will, and that of the holy God-bearer
                     <persName>Mary</persName>, and may we for our part be helped through their
                  prayer, Amen and Amen! </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-29">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-29.1" n="2"> The history of<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a35" target="#n35" n="35"/>
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1862">Malkha</persName> the mendicant and
                  stranger<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a36" target="#n36" n="36"/> is ended. </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 360, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om., number uncertain. See Introd., p. XI.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 360, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. ins. 'Mar'. The name Malkha does not occur in the chapter.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 360, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">written by Mar John of Asia</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 360, n. 6</orig>
                    </choice>Cf. p. 249.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 361, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Nov. This must be the 2nd expulsion, since J. did not enter the monastery
               before the first. The date is therefore 530-6; see Introd., p. IV.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 361, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 361, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Lit. <hi rend="singleQuotes">those of my lord's house</hi>. V. D. and L.
               render <hi rend="singleQuotes">
                        <foreign>domestici</foreign>
                    </hi>; but were there
                  <foreign>domestici</foreign> in a monastery? From p. 365 they seem to have been an
               inferior class of men, yet at p. 363 they associated with the archimandrite. The
               lexx. give no help. They were perh. novices or lay monks who were required to perform
               certain menial offices; cf. p. 280. The fact that they recited service (p. 363) is
               hardly decisive against this, since we find the laymen Abraham (p. 121) and Tribunus
               (ch. 44) reciting service. They perh. derived their name from being specially
               attached to the archamandrite.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 361, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Gen., XXIII, 4; Lev., XXV, 23; Ps. XXXIX, 13; Hebr., XI, 31.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 362, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. the brotherhood, as the grammar shows, cf. ch. 35.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 362, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 62, n. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 363, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. nocturns. He was no doubt sleeping in the chapel; see p. 204, 225,
               253.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 363, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Abba; see ch. 58.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 363, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Lit. <hi rend="singleQuotes">rest of the houseworkers</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 363, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 363, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. for sext.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 363, n. 6</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 79, n. 2, and Addenda to part 1.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 364, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. XL, 14.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 365, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>April.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 366, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 367, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I Tim., III, 5.</note>
                <note xml:id="n21" target="#a21" n="21">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 367, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>John, IX, 4.</note>
                <note xml:id="n22" target="#a22" n="22">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 368, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Gal., V, 7.</note>
                <note xml:id="n23" target="#a23" n="23">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 368, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. <hi rend="singleQuotes">put you in mind of</hi>. The syr. is
               confused.</note>
                <note xml:id="n24" target="#a24" n="24">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 368, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Philipp., IV, 5, 6.</note>
                <note xml:id="n25" target="#a25" n="25">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 368, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., XXIV, 33.</note>
                <note xml:id="n26" target="#a26" n="26">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 368, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>Hebr., X, 31.</note>
                <note xml:id="n27" target="#a27" n="27">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 369, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>II Cor., V, 10.</note>
                <note xml:id="n28" target="#a28" n="28">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 369, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Prov., XX, 9.</note>
                <note xml:id="n29" target="#a29" n="29">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 369, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>II Cor., III, 3.</note>
                <note xml:id="n30" target="#a30" n="30">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 370, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. CXLIII, 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n31" target="#a31" n="31">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 370, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>II Cor., X, 18.</note>
                <note xml:id="n32" target="#a32" n="32">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 371, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., V, 37.</note>
                <note xml:id="n33" target="#a33" n="33">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 372, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>House of the <foreign xml:lang="grc">διακονικά</foreign>. Cf. p. 103.</note>
                <note xml:id="n34" target="#a34" n="34">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 372, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 79, n. 2, and Addenda to part 1.</note>
                <note xml:id="n35" target="#a35" n="35">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 372, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">Mar</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n36" target="#a36" n="36">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 372, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">written by Mar John of Asia</hi>.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
