<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/823">Elijah and Theodore</title>
                <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/822"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/824"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/823 -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-31" n="31">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-31">
                    <head type="main">Next the Thirty-First History, of Two Brothers Who Were Traders, Who Beside
                  Worldly Trade Engaged Moreover in Divine Also, Whose names are <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1705">Elijah</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3140">Theodore</persName>.</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-31.1" n="1"> Since therefore it is our purpose to tell the stories of
                  men who walked in the path of religion, and in the course of our history to make
                  the glories of their practices known, accordingly neither have we kept the glories
                  of these excellent men hidden, who in their garb (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) were reckoned laymen and traders, but were constantly
                  occupied in the practices of angels. These are two brothers, and in the time of
                  their boyhood they served for pay with traders, and travelled with them, each of
                  them in his own direction, that is, to the regions of the
                     <persName>Persians</persName> both of them. And they formed in their mind <pb type="vol" n="577"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="375"/>the purpose of following a religious life; and they
                  determined that whatever God provided for them should go to their own use, and
                  that of everyone else whom they saw to be a stranger like them and in need. And
                  thus they thenceforth did; for they carried on their business, and distributed to
                  the poor and to the strangers. And, when God saw their zeal, he caused everything
                  to which they put their hand to increase abundantly in their hands. And thus a
                  blessing rested on everything that passed through their hands, they having
                  resolved to abstain entirely from the evil practices which traders. of the world
                  are wont to follow, i.e. from oaths of all kinds, and from lying, and from
                  extortion, and from diverse weights and diverse measures.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> They told everything to the man who was buying from
                  them or selling to them fairly and honestly without contention; but, if that man
                  whoever he might be began oaths and bargaining, they on their side would say to
                  him shortly as follows: <quote>Brother, accept what I have told you honestly,
                     without extortion and without fraud and contention, and without bargaining and
                     oaths. If it suits you buy (or sell). Wherefore are you making havoc of (?)
                     oaths and allowing Satan to thrust you into sin, when you are under no
                     necessity <pb type="vol" n="578"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="376"/>to buy (or sell) whether you want or not?
                     Now, if it suits you, take it without oaths; and if not, pray for
                  us</quote>.<!-- Brooks' use of quotations here is really confusing. -->
               </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-31.2" n="2"> And thus these excellent men followed their employment in
                  the fear of God, each of them serving for two and three years at the salary of
                  five or six <foreign>denarii</foreign>. And, when those under whom they were
                  employed saw that God caused everything that they did to prosper in their hands,
                  they appointed them ten <foreign>denarii</foreign>; and again, after some years
                  during which they had been willing to travel, they appointed them twenty
                     <foreign>denarii</foreign> a year; and at last, when they saw the blessing that
                  grace brought about through them, they appointed them thirty
                     <foreign>denarii</foreign> a year, that they might remain with them only,
                  having committed to their hands all that was in their houses; and they had very
                  large storehouses (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άποθήκη</foreign>), and they used to do
                  business in many regions. But these excellent brothers, when they had completed
                  twenty years at this salary, and Grace fed them out of their honest labour,
                  deliberated with one another, saying, <quote>It is better for us for the future to
                     go and carry on business ourselves on our own account out of that which Grace
                     has provided for us; that it may in be our power and choice to give to God out
                     of that which he gives us without fear of others.</quote> And so after twenty
                  years they returned to <pb type="vol" n="579"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="377"/>their country i. e. to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>. Now they had two sisters
                  who also had been engaged in practices of asceticism and sanctity in virgin
                  fashion from their childhood, and at all times constantly devoted themselves to
                  sorrow and tears and petitions and prayers, and that while they were mourning over
                  these same brothers during so long a time in which they had not seen them, but had
                  only heard from time to time that they were alive and in the land of the
                     <persName>Persians</persName>; and when they came they did not recognise them
                  on account of the lapse of time, until they themselves informed them. And they
                  determined to make a gain of their sisters' spiritual blessing also all the days
                  of their life; and so they removed and went and settled the four of them together
                  at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/136">Melitene</placeName> a city of
                     <placeName>Cappadocia</placeName>, and there they thenceforth began to labour
                  in spiritual fashion at their business, and all the income that they received they
                  used to divide equally between themselves and the strangers and poor. And from the
                  time when they began, because God also was pleased with them, they both received
                  the gratitude and the blessings of the poor and needy every day, and further the
                  business carried on without deceit and extortion and lying ascended like the
                  vapour of incense at all times from the devout men themselves to him who knows
                  all, and so according to the riches of his mercy he <pb type="vol" n="580"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="378"/>who
                  has not deserted and does not desert any who trust in him showed his favour
                  openly, and his blessing rested on all that they did. And thus in a short time
                  they attained to great wealth, while even they themselves marvelled and wondered
                  how it was that, while they were always scattering it, it increased with them. And
                  thenceforth the fame of their kindness and of their almsgiving went out
                  everywhere, and needy persons from all quarters used to come to them, and supply
                  their needs from them for each man according to<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> his due; and moreover the visitation of the persecuted
                  whom they heard to be in need everywhere they would console through their gifts.
                  And accordingly they disregarded the worldly trade, and strenuously and earnestly
                  followed the spiritual one with great watchfulness, insomuch that they would press
                  the same upon their blessed sisters with regard to the trade carried on through
                  the gifts derived from their labour, that they also might add this to the rest of
                  their practices. And thus each would on his part give as he was able, and still
                     it<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> increased the more, so that
                  in that place was manifestly fulfilled that which was said in the prophet,
                     <quote>I will pour blessings upon you till ye shall say
                     <quote>Enough</quote>
                        </quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/>
                  Thus therefore it happened to these men from <pb type="vol" n="581"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="379"/>God,
                  insomuch that they were unequal to the task of bringing forth and giving, while
                  their house was turned into a hospice (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ξενοδοχείον</foreign>) for strangers and other persons in need And accordingly
                  there were a multitude (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όχλος</foreign>) of many persons
                  in that house, of slaves and hired men and bondmaids, and travellers besides and
                  strangers who were gathered together for God's sake, and girls also, and old
                  women, and blind and maimed men, insomuch that they practised the ordinances of
                  monasticism in all the departments of their house, fasting and abstinence and
                  asceticism; and they had weeks<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> as
                  in a monastery and did menial work, and separate cells for prayers and for secret
                  labours by night, since each of them used to watch and pray. And accordingly all
                  the night there was heard from their cells spiritual singing and the reading of
                  the Scriptures; and so in the morning also as well, until each one's repetition of
                  the service was finished, he would not consent to go out at all and make an answer
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άπόχρισις</foreign>) to anyone's call. But the elder
                  whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1705">Elijah</persName>
                  they would urge, for the sake of the security (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άσφάλεια</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> of the
                  house, to take a wife; and he yielded to the pressure, and he alone took a wife,
                  while with him also the Scripture-saying was fulfilled which says, <quote>A <pb type="vol" n="582"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="380"/>good woman shall be given to a man who feareth the
                     Lord</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> For this woman,
                  when she came in and saw that they were bent on running in the path of
                  righteousness, began and quickened the running, and passed them all, in sorrow and
                  tears and fasting and watching and prayers, while she also learned the psalms by
                  heart; and she was further prepared to go out to a monastery or to the desert. And
                  she had sons born to her beside one daughter; and she at once made her a nun. And
                  so all these excellent persons ran after spiritual things. But, if it happened
                  that cases of necessity (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άνάγκας</foreign>) arose for them
                  to make an answer (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άπόχρισις</foreign>) to a call during
                  the night, one of them would be chosen and appointed the evening before to perform
                  that office, while he would make entreaty and request all the others to entreat
                  the Lord for him <quote>because I am neglecting the praise of God, for the sake of
                     which he gave me a mouth and a tongue.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> Pray for me that God may preserve me, lest a stain of sin be
                     secretly formed<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> in me through
                     the things that I am doing</quote>; and thus he would carry out that office; so
                  that on account of the fame of their excellent mode of life, when occasions called
                  us to the royal city,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> we used to
                  make our lodging with them, and it might happen that we even passed several days
                  in their house both on the <pb type="vol" n="583"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="381"/>way up and on the way back,
                  since they had now made a martyrs' chapel in one of the chambers of their
                  dwelling, and at the hour of their own assembly for service they used to meet
                  there, and anyone who was known and honoured by them they would receive there.
                  Accordingly, when we looked at these persons who were called by the name of
                  laymen, and at their regulations and customs (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμος</foreign>), how great and small down to little children and hired
                  servants and slaves male and female passed their time in devout practices and
                  rendering of praise and thanks to God, and in fasting and prayers at all times, we
                  inwardly despised ourselves, crying woe upon our life, since the Christian name
                  only without deeds was called over us, while we also remembered with sorrow the
                  words of our Lord who says, <quote>The tax-gatherers and the harlots go into the
                     kingdom of heaven before you</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> And so we marvelled at these things while we were with them; and we
                  were especially astonished at the greatness of their kindness and the direction of
                  their will toward God, so that, whenever they saw us great and small, they would
                  thus with as little intermission as possible refuse to leave us, but, thinking of
                  us that we were in truth actually Christians, each of them would <pb type="vol" n="584"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="382"/>ask to hear from us about his thoughts and about the other modes of
                  life, and <quote>How must I deal with such-and-such a thought?</quote> and
                     <quote>What labour will bring me near to God?</quote>, each of them separately
                  according to his station, whether women or men.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> And we like what our Lord said also to the scribes and
                  Pharisees, <quote>Ye bind heavy burdens upon men's necks, but ye yourselves do not
                     touch them not even with one of your fingers</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> similarly would urge them to things to which we were
                  ourselves strangers by describing a model of righteousness and by stories of the
                  fathers. And they all vied with one another the more in the ardour with which they
                  carried out their observances. But, inasmuch as the profit of the spiritual trade
                  in those who flocked to them every day was not enough for them, they resolved that
                  one of these excellent brothers should take what God had provided for them, and go
                  out to the districts in which the persecuted and ill-used convents were dwelling,
                  and distribute his bodily things among them, and himself make spiritual gain
                  through their prayers; since the time had in fact come when the believers were
                  persecuted and maltreated in every district. And so he would go out and go round
                  the whole of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/486">Syria</placeName>, and
                  as far as <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/716">ʿArab</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/109">Callinicus</placeName> and the desert, accompanied by two bondmen, and he did
                  so in <pb type="vol" n="585"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="383"/>the dress (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) of a secular trader without being known, and he was making
                  spiritual gains. And so by the love of God which they showed in their trade these
                  admirable men would every day send great loads to heaven, and completed the days
                  of their life in practices which it surpasses even the power of words to describe,
                  in love of the new life of the kingdom of heaven, while we have not been competent
                  to describe any part of the greatness of their glory. But at last they even sold
                  all that they had also, their mansions and the rest of the worldly goods that they
                  possessed, and distributed it among the poor and the monks; and so they all became
                  monks. The blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1705">Elijah</persName> had departed from the world before taking the habit
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>); but his wife and daughter ended
                  their lives in a women's monastery in the territory of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2812">Mabbug</placeName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> and their sisters are even down to the present time
                  also, which is the year eight hundred and seventy-eight,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> living in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Anzetene</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/>
                        <placeName>the country of the Urtaye</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/> and they preside over a monastery in the village of
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2827">N'ns</placeName>, and they are
                  in extreme old age, and occupied in labours of perfection. </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-31">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-31.1" n="3"> The history of two brothers <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1705">Elijah</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3140">Theodore</persName> the traders is ended.
               </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 375, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Prov., XX, 10.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 378, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms.
               om. There is perh. further corruption in the sentence.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 378, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sic
               syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 378, n.
               3</orig>
                    </choice>Mal., III, 10.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 379, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>See, p. 62, n. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 379, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>If
               'permanence' is meant, the end of the ch. shows that the object was not
               obtained.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 380, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Sir., XXVI, 3.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 380, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Cf.
               p. 229.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 380, n.
                  3</orig>
                    </choice>
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr" dir="rtl">ܐܬܛܪܛܝ</foreign> is not elsewhere known
               in this sense, but means <hi rend="singleQuotes">was stained</hi> with ref. to the
               object stained.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 380, n.
               4</orig>
                    </choice>535 and 540; see Introd., p. IV, V.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 381, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., XXI, 31.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 382, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Cf. p. 273.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 382, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>Luke, XI, 46.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 382, n.
               3</orig>
                    </choice>The plain of Mesopotamia and Orshoene.</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 383, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Hierapolis.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 383, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>567.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 383, n.
               3</orig>
                    </choice>Syr. <hi rend="singleQuotes">Hanzit</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 383, n.
               4</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 135, n. 2.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
