<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/824">A Monk</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/823"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/825"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/824 -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-32" n="32">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-32">
               <head type="main">Next the Thirty-Second History, of a Certain Brother Who Was Caught By the
                  Enticement of Temptation to Theft and Afterwards Came To Repentance.</head>
               <ab xml:id="section-32.1" n="1"> A certain blessed man had been settled for a considerable
                  time as a solitary in a cell in the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/473">Ennaton</placeName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>
                  <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> with two
                  disciples; and, when we ourselves arrived at that place<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> and went in to him and received his blessing, three
                  days after we had departed from his presence a brother from one of the well-known
                  convents of the place came to him under the plea of desiring to live with him,
                  even as I had myself made the acquaintance of that brother in his convent; and,
                  when he had come in and passed about one week with him, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3651">Satan</persName> put it into his heart to
                  take the contents of that solitary's cell and flee. And, having looked and learned
                  everything, and devised in his mind a plan of action, he rose by night and
                  collected everything that he could (since that blessed man had indeed no small
                  number of saints<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> and books), and he
                  took them, a great load, and fled. And he went and found camel-drivers going into
                  the desert above <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2810">Libya</placeName>
                  that is called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2766">Cellia</placeName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> and he gave
                  them a fee, leading them to think that he was carrying his own <pb n="587"/>
                  <pb n="385"/>belongings in order to go thither. And they took him, and he went into
                  the desert with them; and he went in to a certain man there, and made search for a
                  cell for himself in which to live and be a solitary. And, when he had passed one
                  week there, his thoughts began to pass judgment upon him, and his heart to smite
                  him, and he would say to himself, as he himself would inform us about everything,
                  weeping: <quote>
                     <quote>In what way, O wretched man, did you wish to become a
                        solitary? To <persName>Christ</persName>, pray, or to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3651">Satan</persName>? Lo! you have
                        performed the service of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3651">Satan</persName>, and executed and fulfilled the will of a demon, and
                        afflicted a soul fashioned in the divine likeness, and carried off the toil
                        and sweat of that holy old man's labour; and he is sobbing and crying before
                        God on your account at all times. And how have I hope of life and
                        salvation?</quote> Then</quote>!-- This is really awkward. It seems like the
                  previous quote within a quote should just be a quote and Then he said should not
                  be in quotations at all. --&gt; (he would say) <quote>I passed one week in penitence
                     and horror and tears, weeping for myself, and meditating upon these things and
                     saying, <quote>What has befallen me? Who led me astray? What shall I do? How
                        shall I weep for myself? Alas for me! since my companions are secretly
                        stealing a kingdom, and I stole eternal torment for myself. What will happen
                        to me when I am about to go to God? What defence (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άπολογία</foreign>) have I to give for this wickedness?</quote> And,
                     while I on my <pb n="588"/>
                     <pb n="386"/>side was weeping for myself, my hearers
                     were wondering, and were desirous of learning the cause of the lamentation and
                     weeping on my part. Then I revealed it to them, and they marvelled. And I said
                     to them: <quote>What do you advise me to do? because my meditation is inciting
                        me to strangle myself and perish out of this life, which deceived me and
                        incited me to this crime</quote>. And these saints advised me to return the
                     stolen goods to their owners, saying to me, <quote>If you listen to us and make
                        restitution and humble yourself and ask mercy for this your offence, God
                        will be merciful to you and men also will forgive you; and even they
                        themselves will be merciful to you and forgive you, and will also make
                        petition for you</quote>. And, while they pressed me, I on my part was
                     restrained by my shamefacedness and hindered from doing this, saying to them:
                     <quote>My face is ashamed to do this. With what face, or with what colour
                        (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χρώμα</foreign>), or with what brazen front can
                        this be carried out?</quote> But the blessed men went on saying to me,
                     <quote>Which is better for you, to endure reproach and transitory shame
                        here, and repent and live while you have opportunity, while you further
                        relieve the souls to which you have given sorrow and bitterness, or to be
                        consumed in the <pb n="589"/>
                        <pb n="387"/>eternal torment, where shame and
                        reproach and torment are not finished and brought to an end for ever and
                        ever?</quote> When these words had been spoken to me by many men, I rose and
                     left all the utensils and the books and the martyrs under seal, and I came in
                     shame; and lo! I am settled here till intercessors are found for me</quote>.
                  All these things about himself that brother was relating by word of mouth in my
                  presence with great humility and copious tears; since, while I was going round the
                  districts to be blessed by the saints, I found him in a monastery called that of
                  father <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2738">Andrew</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> on the farther side<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> where the holy Mar <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2819">Menas</placeName>
                  <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> is, which is called the desert of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2821">Mendia</placeName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> and, when I saw him, I was astonished in his presence,
                  and I greeted him, having no knowledge of what had happened; and he on his side
                  was bowed down, and was melancholy and wretched. And on my inquiring of him about
                  his sorrow he sat down and accused himself and told the story of his crime at a
                  length many times greater than what I have put in writing. And, when I heard it, I
                  admired the man's penitence; and I comforted him by saying to him: <quote>You have
                     done a great deed and one that deserves admiration, in that for the sake of
                     your soul's healing you have despised shame,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> and have taken upon yourself that, be it igno<pb n="590"/>
                     <pb n="388"/>miny or reproach, or chastisements and everything that
                     comes here, you will submit to them, they being things that are transitory, in
                     order to escape from the severe and terrible chastisement in hell which lasts
                     for ever. And now fear not. You did well in that you did not carry out the work
                     of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3651">Satan</persName> and his will
                     to the uttermost, though he caused you a fall inasmuch as you are a
                     man</quote>
                  <!-- This close quotation is missing in Brooks but these requires it. -->.
                  He on hearing these things was comforted; and he went on entreating us to return
                  with him to the owner of the stolen property, in order to entreat him to receive
                  his own in full and forgive the transgression. When we saw that it was a labour of
                  profit to gain our brother,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> we did
                  not refuse; and further also we were required to fulfil the precept given in the
                  command, <quote>If thy brother shall force thee to go one mile, go with him
                     two</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> And so we returned
                  with him, and went in to that blessed man, having left him some distance away. And
                  we found him agitated with great grief and much distress on account of the martyrs
                  and on account of the books especially; and, when we began to speak before him,
                  <quote>Indeed we can find your property for you</quote>, he was astonished, and
                  began to make inquiries. Then we on our part asked him to perform a request for
                  us, and all his belongings would be found complete; and he on his side <pb n="591"/>
                  <pb n="389"/>answered <quote>Everything that you command I for my part am
                     ready to carry out even without that</quote>. Then we offered him repentance,
                  having taken it upon ourself, and we said: <quote>Since <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3651">Satan</persName>, father, caused us to
                     fall like men, and we sinned against God and your holiness, receive your own,
                     and forgive the crime, and remain without ill-feeling, in order that you may be
                     a fulfiller of the command which said <quote>Forgive and it shall be forgiven
                        unto you</quote>
                     <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/>
                  </quote>. But
                  the blessed man was much grieved over him and was distressed, saying: <quote>Even
                     if he does not restore me anything and you command, all the days of my life I
                     will consent that he shall live with me without ill-feeling, and I will never
                     remind him of this matter</quote>. And so that brother came, repenting and
                  weeping and with his face bowed down to the ground, and bitterly accusing himself,
                  in such a way as he could not have been accused by one who hated him. When that
                  blessed man saw his penitence, and all of us<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> alike greatly wondered and marvelled at the grace
                  which had opened his heart and caused him thus to repent and to act in this way
                  (and all who heard the story wondered and marvelled at it), then he in this way
                  received thanks from everyone in place of punishment. And the blessed man received
                  <pb n="592"/>
                  <pb n="390"/>him, and laid a penance upon him, and absolved him.
                  And he hired an ass for him; and that brother set out, and so he went and brought
                  all the articles, not having forgotten anything. And thenceforth he continued to
                  repent of his offence like a guilty man, and he was diligent in showing repentance
                  for it, insomuch that we on our part left him in this condition, admiring what he
                  had done and thanking God. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-32">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-32.1" n="2"> The history of a certain brother who was caught by the
                  enticement of temptation to theft and afterwards came to repentance is ended.
               </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 384, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>See p. 325 and ch. 56.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 384, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>In 534 or 541; see Introd., p. IV, V.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 384, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>Sc. relics; cf. p. 114.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 384, n. 4</orig>
               </choice>Ruf. <title>Hist. Mon.</title>, XXII; Soz. VI, 31. Acc. to Rufinus it was 70
               stades from Nitris.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 387, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Andrew the soldier is commemorated with Menas on 12 July (V. D. and L.; see
               Acta Sanct., XXX, p. 289).</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 387, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Sc. of the Nile. The meaning of in our author is as here given, not <hi rend="singleQuotes">exadversum as V. D. and L. See p. 289, n. 2, and Dyakonov, p.
                  84.</hi>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 387, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>See p. 209, n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 387, n. 4</orig>
               </choice>See p. 190.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 387, n. 5</orig>
               </choice>Hebr., XII, 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 388, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Matth., XVIII, 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 388, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Id., V, 41.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 389, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Luke, VI, 37.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 389, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>The other persons present were perh. the hermit's disciples.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
