<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/826">Simeon the Scribe</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/825"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/827"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/826 -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-34" n="34">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-34">
               <head type="main">[Next the Thirty-Fourth History, of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2098">Simeon</persName> the Old, the Scribe of
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>.]<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>
               </head>
               <ab xml:id="section-34.1" n="1"> [....] he used to expend upon them, until for many days
                  nothing succeeded in <pb n="602"/>
                  <pb n="400"/>reaching his own particular table
                  and those with him, while everyone was overpowered with great astonishment at the
                  abounding willingness of this man of God, how he was not wearied or annoyed and
                  vexed by all that great number of poor who were constantly with him, though often
                  both we and other lazy persons like me felt weariness, and we were annoyed by the
                  clamour and turmoil of many persons when we were present with him, and we said,
                  <quote>How is it, our father, that you endure all this turmoil from morning
                     even to evening, and do not tell them fixed times at which they may
                     come?</quote> But he on his side would say: <quote>Do you tell me, my brethren,
                        have we a time at which we knock at God's door and are not received? has he
                        someone at his door who is vexed with us or makes announcement to us and says,
                        <quote>Go now and come at another time</quote>? Lo! is not his door open
                        before us at every [time] if we on our side wish to knock at it? and how then
                        do you advise me that, when he himself comes to my door, I should turn him
                        away, or, when he knocks, I should not answer him, or that I should fix a time
                        for him? Is it not enough that <persName>Christ</persName> comes on his feet to
                        my door, but that<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> I, a vile
                        piece of dust of his formation, should open my mouth to him in insult? or do we
                        not believe what he told us in his preaching, saying, <quote>To me ye did
                           it</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/>
                        <pb n="603"/>
                        <pb n="401"/>whether it be what is good or what is evil? And he
                        said not <quote>To vile and feeble men</quote>, but <quote>To me ye did
                           it</quote>.</quote>
               </ab>
               <ab xml:id="section-34.2" n="3"> And these things this true bondman of God would say with
                  sorrow and tears besides many others. But at first he was indeed actually in great
                  straits, because he had not supplies sufficient for his abounding willingness; but
                  at last, when he had continued for several years, and the fame of his practices
                  had been reported all over the city, God also who had seen his love used to send
                  him what he needed in abundance, and thenceforth the holy old man would contrive
                  not merely to plant his foot in one footprint (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τύπος</foreign>) of the patriarch whom he was desirous of imitating and remain
                  there, but would<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> enlarge his
                  steps<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> to run and reach many of
                  his footprints; so that, besides the love and alacrity and hospitality which he
                  possessed like him, in this also as well he did not fall behind him, that he
                  personally and with his own hands performed all the service; and, as the
                  patriarch, when he possessed all that host of bondmen and servants, when he saw
                  the men who were received by him as guests, did not order someone else to run to
                  the herd to fetch the calf, but ran himself in his old age that he might be the
                  receiver of the blessing and not another, so this man with all that advanced <pb n="604"/>
                  <pb n="402"/>old age used himself to perform all the service of the
                  whole day, though many were then living with him in the cell, and he did not allow
                  them to wait either upon him or upon anyone, but he himself would wait upon them,
                  and often, whenever any necessary service was required, he would himself rise from
                  table, and fulfil it; and (a great thing which astonishes many) that<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> he would actually himself stand
                  before the cooking-stand every day and cook without tiring, having laid down the
                  following law (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμος</foreign>) for himself, that, as soon
                  as they had finished nocturns, he would dismiss his companions to their bodily
                  rest, and would himself direct his steps to the kitchen, and himself begin and
                  cook until morning on account of the poor people who were in the habit of coming
                  early, and would put the food together, and make it ready; and so he would go out
                  and wake them, and they<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> would rise
                  to matins; and as soon as the service was finished they would place tables both
                  within and without. Moreover, as if greedy for his great spiritual trade, he did
                  not stop at<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> waiting on those who
                  came and went, but he brought <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3685">four
                     blind men</persName>, and placed them in his cell at his table; and thenceforth
                  he was not to be seen except distributing the food and placing it in the mouth of
                  each <pb n="605"/>
                  <pb n="403"/>one of them by his name,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/>; and, if it were a portion of bread (?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> or some herbs, or a cup, he would
                  grasp each of them with his hand, calling them by their names, and entreating and
                  pressing them to eat, while he also grasped the hand of each one of them and made
                  it feel the dish; and again that,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/>
                  if anyone soever great or small came to him, there was no possibility of his
                  separating his food from theirs, so that many great and distinguished men who used
                  to visit him on account of his extreme old age and his extraordinary practices and
                  were possessed by friendship for him did not like this that he used to make them
                  sit among these <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3685">blind
                     men</persName>; and he on his side paid no heed to these men, but these
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3685">blind men</persName> were
                  greater in his eyes than anyone, and he used to wait on them as if they were
                  <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, and there was no means of distinguishing
                  either his own proper food or that of anyone who visited him from them<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> or from all the other guests, but he
                  himself would wait both on them and on everyone, and would pour out wine and bring
                  hot water, and himself mix it, everyone disliking this on account of his venerable
                  old age; and, if anyone made any answer to him or wished to do anything instead of
                  him, this is what he would say to him: <quote>I, my brother, <pb n="606"/>
                     <pb n="404"/>have not insulted you or done you any harm. Wherefore do you insult
                     me?</quote>. When then this saint had completed about ten years in the royal
                  city itself, since, inasmuch as he had found material for his trade in it, and
                  inasmuch moreover as the persecution which was always everywhere did not cease, he
                  had now chosen to continue to remain in the city occupied in this labour, we
                  ourselves having been in intercourse with him for about twelve years while he was
                  following these practices, so then this extraordinary man ended his life,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> having strenuously completed all his
                  days in these great labours, so that, when he had become very infirm, and God
                  wished to take him to his abode in heaven, and he felt that he was dying, he gave
                  each of his companions a present out of his cell as he knew to be suited to him,
                  as well as the furniture of the altar, since indeed besides these things his cell
                  was actually a church also, and an altar was continuously set ready in it, and a
                  large congregation used to assemble before it. And he ordered all that he had to
                  be sold and given to the poor; and so it was done. And he departed from this world
                  according to the commandment of God. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-34">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-34.1" n="3"> The history of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2098">Simeon</persName> the old, the scribe of
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, is ended. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 399, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>The beginning is lost.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 400, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sic syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 400, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Matth., XXV, 40.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 401, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sic syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 401, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Ps. XVIII, 37.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 402, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sic syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 402, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Sc. the monks.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 402, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>This must be the meaning of <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܬܟܠܝ ܥܠ</foreign>. The
               lexicons do not give the phrase.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 403, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sic syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 403, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Ms. <hi rend="singleQuotes">portion</hi> only. Perh. a word has fallen out.
               but cf. p. 393, l. 10.l</note>
            <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 403, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>Sic syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 404, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ms. om. Since he lived 10 years in CP. and was in intercourse with J. for 12
               years, he probably came to CP at the same time as J. (540) and died in 550.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
