<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/827">Monks of Amida</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/826"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/828"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/827 -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-35" n="35">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-35" n="35">
                    <head type="main">Next the Thirty-Fifth History, of the Great, Admirable, and Renowned <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1934">Community of the Holy Convents of the
                     Amidenes</persName>, Who Distinguished Themselves in Great Conflicts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of Persecution, Who Were Expelled in the Year
                  Eight Hundred and Thirty-Two.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>
                    </head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-35.1" n="1"> Since then thirty years ago also in another book about
                  the persecution<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> we put in writing a
                  certain amount about <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1934">this holy
                     community</persName> also, we now too thought it right in the series of
                  histories of the saints also to put a memorial of it in writing; for how could it
                  be anything but a reprehensible act, while relating the stories of persons
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>) living a solitary lile, to cover
                  with silence the story of a great and admirable <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1934">community</persName> of saints a thousand
                     in<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> number as to which too, if we
                  wish to put an account of it in writing, we shall fall no small distance inside
                  the boundary of the subject of its history. This <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1934">divine community</persName> then was
                  composed of a combination of the convents great and small round the city of
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName> and those inside
                  it, and those of its territory (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χώρα</foreign>), and, as
                  we stated above, contained not less <pb n="608"/>
                        <pb n="406"/>in number than a
                  thousand men;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> so that, having all,
                  small as well as great, been fired by zeal for the faith, and having been duly
                  girded with the armour of truth, they also entered valiantly and heroically and
                  courageously into the struggle against the defenders of the corrupt synod of
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/622">Chalcedon</placeName>, insomuch
                  that by reason of these things they were by a violent persecution expelled from
                  their convents, and met together and were marvellously combined in a great and
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1934">spiritual community</persName>,
                  so that they were driven from place to place and from region to region, and after
                  settling in many places were driven out, or because they were not convenient and
                  not large enough for their numbers arrived<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> at the great and extensive convent in the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2796">village of Hzyn</placeName> in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2858">Ṭyšf</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> which is called that of the blessed Mar <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2813">Mama</placeName>; but, though it was large
                  and spacious from the times of the great fathers who built it, yet, even though
                  this is the case, this great <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1934">community</persName> was cramped and straitened for room while living in it
                  for the space of five years;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> so
                  that our meanness also, though we had still only attained to the tender age of
                  boyhood, were<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> with many others
                  attracted by the renown of this <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1934">community</persName> to come from the district of <pb n="609"/>
                        <pb n="407"/>
                        <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2798">Ingilene</placeName>, and
                  received the privilege of living in it, i. e., in the renowned convent of the
                  blessed Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> while we also marvelled and wondered
                  and were amazed at the great and divine spiritual practices of that great and
                  spiritual people, whom it is impossible fittingly to write about or describe. Even
                  if there were in that <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1934">community</persName> a man of deaf intellect and blind heart and hardened
                  soul, it would be impossible that he should not be affected and bowed down and
                  repent, and be roused as from deep sleep, and come to compunction, and gain
                  affliction of mind, and pour out piteous tears, and betake himself to spiritual
                  works of righteousness, and embrace the strenuous running in the lofty road on
                  seeing revered old age with honourable white hairs bound to the yoke of spiritual
                  labours and duly dragging it, and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/>
                  middle age and the tender years of youth also being drawn along in the pursuit of
                  abstinence and asceticism, and holiness and watching and fasting and prayers that
                  never cease at all hours of the night and day, who<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> used to stand constantly before God; while it was a
                  great marvel to hear the thunder of their admirable voice, and to listen to their
                  holy and divine singing, not only those<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> of the canon,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> but those
                  also which took place privately and separately <pb n="610"/>
                        <pb n="408"/>during
                  the winter season, from all the rooms and from all the cells and from all the
                  doorways and from all the corners (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γωνίa</foreign>), and
                  the corridors (<foreign xml:lang="grc">στοά</foreign>) and halls of all that great
                  convent. But in the summer-season these were the things that one might see and
                  hear with great astonishment, especially during the whole extent of the nights, in
                  all the surroundings of this convent, especially in the broad and spacious stony
                  ground, up to some distance from which there were men standing and reciting the
                  service two and two, or four or less or more, or a master and his disciples, and
                  others were lying alone upon their faces, and some way apart from one another,
                  whose voice was heard from all sides with mighty crying of rushing tears of
                  weeping, from after the canonical nocturns till the matins bell, and so they would
                  again meet together for the holy canonical singing, and so afterwards they would
                  the whole day meditate on the law (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμος</foreign>) of the
                  Lord as it is written,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> while
                  reading the Scriptures and reciting the service and the regular prayers of the
                  hours, terce, that is, and sext and nones and vespers and compline,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> while all idle and vain speech had
                  fled and been cast out from among them with all human conversations, or <pb n="611"/>
                        <pb n="409"/>jesting or laughter, or suchlike things, but instead of
                  these things was to be seen thanksgiving according to the apostolic saying,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> and sorrow and compunction, and
                  tears, one conversation only, that with God, one order, and one habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>), one union, one concord, one serenity, one
                  quietude, one love, and downcast looks, and gentle and sorrowful speech at all
                  hours; and, though there were to be found some who were young and some who were of
                  light disposition or who were loose in their speech, when we looked at one another
                  and wondered, they would thenceforth take example (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τύπος</foreign>) from one another, and learn devoutness, and be rivals in
                  works of righteousness; so that, if any discerning man observed the practices that
                  were common to all these spiritual ranks, and their sorrowfulness and their habit
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) and their praises that ceased not
                  night and day, and took note of their open as well as their secret acts, he would
                  think that he was already dwelling among heavenly, not among earthly beings, while
                  all these spiritual and brave combatants (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγωνιστής</foreign>) used to pass most of all the protracted hours in tears
                  and labours with unceasing sorrow; so that from the first <pb n="612"/>
                        <pb n="410"/>hour of the night or at latest the second<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> no man in full health was to be found on his rug, or not lying on his
                  face with genuflexion and tearful prayer, everyone thenceforth emulating and
                  rivalling his neighbour; and, though emulation is in its nature a deadly and
                  destructive thing, there an emulation was seen that is beautiful and good and
                  sound, a thing that it is difficult for hearers to believe, that emulation ever
                  was a good thing; for, when everyone saw his neighbour active and eager and
                  constant for prayer and genuflexion and tearful sorrow for the space of a whole
                  night and day, and others ranged in rows and standing on standing-posts, and
                  others who had fastened their bodies to the walls all the night without
                  standing-posts, and others who were tied to the ceiling of the room by ropes and
                  vinebranches, and were suspending themselves by them in a standing posture all
                  night, having put them under their armpits, and others who were sitting on seats
                  and never falling on their side, old and young and strong and weak,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/> and that to so great an extent that,
                  even if there were a man who was idle and stolid and careless and lazy, he would
                  be incited by the sight of these labours, and awake with astonishment as from deep
                  sleep, and would thenceforth labour, and emulate these heavenly practices, while I
                  also the wretched <pb n="613"/>
                        <pb n="411"/>and poor, though deficient in years
                  which were in the age of boyhood, thought to emulate such things, and I would also
                  go out by night and see them in these great and marvellous conflicts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) and labours, and he who knows<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/> all knows that our description of
                  them contains no embellishment or flattery, nor are we able to record a tenth part
                  of the truth of them, and,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/> if
                  anyone wish to write a record of these holy labours, he will leave off far short
                  of the end, with regard to that constant affliction, and with regard to the
                  unremitting contrition spread over men great and small, and the unceasing sighs,
                  and the copious tears, and the crying and severe sobs because everyone was looking
                  at his fellow, and everyone was emulating his neighbour and learning and acting,
                  and was practising and imitating and was eager to pass his fellow in the race of
                  righteousness; so that many among them had the power of performing signs, and used
                  by faith to drive out fiends before our eyes, even as in the series of the
                  histories we have recorded the story of some of them who were tricked by the evil
                     one,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a21" target="#n21" n="21"/> and many acts of power and
                  signs took place among them secretly and openly, insomuch that paralytics who used
                  to come on the report of the benefits <pb n="614"/>
                        <pb n="412"/>conferred by them
                  were straightened and healed, and would immediately come to receive the habit
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) of monasticism, itself, and chosen
                     vessels<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a22" target="#n22" n="22"/> were even made out of
                  many of them, so that everyone marvelled at the report of these wonderful things,
                  and crowds of men from distant countries would hurry to this holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1934">community</persName> and arrive among it
                  in order to receive prayer and blessing from these saints, and many who needed
                  healing were relieved, and everyone marvelled and gave thanks to God. But we do
                  not wish to cover with silence one at least of the many miracles which God wrought
                  in this same <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1934">community</persName>,
                  one that resembles the abundance brought about by our Saviour among the many
                  thousands out of the little bread in the desert. Once, when a dearth had occured
                  in the districts of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2774">the
                     East</placeName>, God who knows his own and is known by his own blessed the
                  district in which this holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1934">community</persName> was settled, in order that he might show his loving care
                  for it, so that the produce of that year came forth in it plentifully, and there
                  was a great and rich abundance in it, so that the whole district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2774">the East</placeName> had recourse to it to
                  buy corn; so that one day a great crowd of strangers was assembled at the door of
                  that convent, and extraordinary expense was incurred upon them in the way of
                  hospitality, so much so that the bread which had according <pb n="615"/>
                        <pb n="413"/>to custom been prepared by the servitors<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a23" target="#n23" n="23"/> for the food of the brotherhood was actually on the
                  point of being exhausted, insomuch that the chief servitors and the stewards were
                  coming to the great seniors and saying ruefully: <quote>The provision of bread and
                     cooked food which had been according to custom prepared for the food of the
                     brotherhood has reached the point of exhaustion; and there are still many
                     strangers lying at the door, and we have no means of supplying the need of
                     these and of the brotherhood</quote>. But these divine seniors answered them
                  quietly, saying, <quote>Glory to our Lord! Go, our sons, and bring forth and
                     relieve the poor and the strangers; and, if anything remains over for us
                     ourselves, well, and if not, we will keep fasting vigil today, and let the
                     needs of the strangers and the poor and the needy only be supplied, and let
                     them not be cut short by us</quote>. Then these men expended what was prepared
                  according to the order, until a small quantity was left. And, when the canonical
                  service of vespers was finished, and it was known that a small proportion of what
                  was needed remained over for supper, some words of admonition and of exposition
                  were addressed by these holy seniors to all the brotherhood, in which they said:
                     <quote>Since our brothers the strangers came to satisfy the necessities of
                     their life, that which was prepared <pb n="616"/>
                            <pb n="414"/>for us according
                     to custom was brought out, and little remained over. Let each of us receive a
                     little present<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a24" target="#n24" n="24"/> with thanksgiving
                     and continue without murmuring, for thus he will have a recompense from
                     God</quote>. And so everyone accepted the words that were spoken by the
                  fathers; and they gave thanks, and sat down to the little food that was set upon
                  the table, so that everyone thought that something to put into his mouth would
                  reach him once or twice. And, when all had eaten and been satisfied, the tables
                  were found to be full of bread in abundance, more than every day, though that
                  great number of men, which as we have often said, was not less than one thousand,
                  had been satisfied; so that, when this miracle was suddenly seen, and all had
                  observed it, all marvelled and were astonished, and were excited. And the whole
                  brotherhood stood on the tables themselves together with all the old heads of the
                  convents, and they cry <quote>
                            <foreign>Kyrie eleeson</foreign>
                        </quote>. with great
                  awe many times, with many tears; insomuch that these holy old men addressed many
                  words to the brotherhood with emotion, saying; <quote>Lo! see, our sons, our lack
                     of faith and our churlishness toward God at all times, that, while he in his
                     mercy is always visiting us, and showing his care for us, we wished to <pb n="617"/>
                            <pb n="415"/>be churlish to our brethren the strangers who came to
                     us, for whose sake also this sign has appeared among us as well as for our
                     reproof, since we wished to take thought only for ourselves</quote>&gt;, besides
                  many other things of this kind which were spoken by the seniors; and awe and
                  thanksgiving were excited in everyone. And so a great basket (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κάψα</foreign>) was brought in that four men could scarcely
                  carry after it had been filled; and, though not half of it had been placed upon
                  the tables, out of the remnants which remained after all that great multitude had
                  been satisfied it was filled to overflowing, and would not hold the remnants that
                  were taken from the tables, but, when it was filled and packed(?), 
                  it<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a25" target="#n25" n="25"/> was falling from it this side and
                  that; and great fear and thanks to God were called forth in everyone, while the
                  story of this miracle was also spoken of in all these countries with great wonder
                  (for everyone pressed to take some of these miraculous. remnants, and keep them as
                  a blessing and a great help) and our own meanness was there at the supper as the
                  truth witnesses that we also ate and were satisfied with everyone, and we took a
                  blessing from it; and we have recorded these things not as having been conveyed to
                  us by report, <pb n="618"/>
                        <pb n="416"/>but because we were eye-witnesses and
                  partakers, so that we have also recorded the truth of them and borne witness to
                  it. But he who performs the will of those who fear him worked other such
                  marvellous signs among these same saints of that holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1934">community</persName>, and all these great
                  holy convents had also henceforth one convent and one rule in one concord and
                  unity of the spiritual brotherhood, and one administration, and one expenditure
                  and revenue, and one table, and one service, and they had one coalition
                  throughout, twenty servitors out of each body of fifty men being combined together
                  to perform the duties,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a26" target="#n26" n="26"/> the separate
                  character of each convent being preserved in this only, the fact that its own
                  brotherhood was separate, and its belongings and its archimandrite and its
                  priests, while all the affairs of them all were administered in common, together
                  with all the spiritual labours of brotherly concord of the types which we have
                  imperfectly recorded above in few words. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-35.2" n="2"> When then they had completed a space of five 
                  years<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a27" target="#n27" n="27"/> in that convent, they determined to
                  take up their abode in the neighbourhood and vicinity of their province (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ύπαρχία</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a28" target="#n28" n="28"/> 
                  of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, though by
                  reason of the persecution it <pb n="619"/>
                        <pb n="417"/>was only under difficulties
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άνάγκη</foreign>) that they could appear in the same
                  province (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ύπαρχία</foreign>). Then they came and took up
                  their abode in the district called that of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2774">the East</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a29" target="#n29" n="29"/> 
                  in a <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">monastery</placeName> called that of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2834">the Poplars</placeName>, on the border of the territory of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, in the district opposite
                  the hot spring<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a30" target="#n30" n="30"/> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2751">Abarne</placeName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a31" target="#n31" n="31"/> 
                  so that, when they saw that the place suited them, but
                  that <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">monastery</placeName> was very
                  small and confined for the purposes of their habitation, then they were compelled
                  all the summer-time to set up tents for themselves outside on the mountains and
                  under the wild trees surrounding that convent, and erect huts in extended and
                  varied lines for themselves to dwell in; and so they accomplished the great labour
                  of their marvellous practices, being also compelled to build and prepare for
                  themselves great houses for winter habitation in that <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">monastery</placeName>. When then they had
                  completed a space of two years and a half<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a32" target="#n32" n="32"/> 
                  in this place, while we were also with them, they were ordered to enter
                  their convents at the beginning of the reign of king <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a33" target="#n33" n="33"/> 
                  And, when they had also completed
                  nine years and a half in the first persecution dated from the expulsion of their
                  convents, they <pb n="620"/>
                        <pb n="418"/>returned and came in on the invitation,
                  and they found their convents destroyed and demolished and knocked to pieces and
                  turned to earth, insomuch that they were obliged to set themselves to labour night
                  and day, and build, and set up and restore all these convents, while the whole
                  city also, so to say, used to hold sacramental assemblies with them, so that few
                  remained with <persName>the Synodites</persName>; so that again, when they had
                  completed seven years and a half<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a34" target="#n34" n="34"/> in
                  the convents after their restoration, then the furnace of persecution again blazed
                  up against them, and they were expelled and departed a second time; and in this
                  way also a great <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1934">community</persName> was assembled, though smaller than the previous one, when
                  they also came and dwelt in a convent which itself too had once been a great one
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2850">Thella d Thuthe</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a35" target="#n35" n="35"/> 
                  in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2783">Gumtha</placeName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a36" target="#n36" n="36"/> 
                  and, having again been expelled from this also as
                  well, they came back again to the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">monastery</placeName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2834">the
                     Poplars</placeName>. And, when they had thereafter been completing the labours of
                  these divine practices in this <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">monastery</placeName> for the space of three years,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a37" target="#n37" n="37"/> 
                  then occurred the descent of <pb n="621"/>
                        <pb n="419"/>
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2274">Ephraim</persName> the
                  persecutor, the patriarch of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>, to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2774">the
                     East</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a38" target="#n38" n="38"/> And, when he
                  had several times sent them a persuasive document in order to make them members of
                  his communion, when they did not yield to him, then he sent armed and armoured
                  hosts of fighting men against them as if to fight against barbarians, and they
                  expelled and ejected and scattered and dispersed them over the countries; so that
                  in respect of this time also one might now describe many marvellous things which
                  God wrought, if it were not for the length of the history, and further also
                  because the standard of our work is not now raised to relate the story of the
                     persecution,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a39" target="#n39" n="39"/> but it aims at
                  describing the excellence of the practices of the saints. When then by reason of
                  the persecution of the impious <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2274">Ephraim</persName> they were thenceforth scattered and divided, each one of
                  the convents went to any quarter that they found and settled there, and in some
                  places two; so that they were divided over the territory 
                  of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2775">the Edessenes</placeName> 
                        and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2839">the Samosatenes</placeName> 
                        and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/94">the Perrhenes</placeName> 
                        and the men of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2818">Melitene</placeName> and the other
                  districts, and some of them from the stress (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άνάγκη</foreign>) of the persecution even withdrew as far as the southern
                  desert also, and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3057">ʿArab</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a40" target="#n40" n="40"/> and
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2800">Izla</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a41" target="#n41" n="41"/> 
                  and the other districts and dwelt there.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a42" target="#n42" n="42"/> And, when they had set up
                  many places, and built many <pb n="622"/>
                        <pb n="420"/>monasteries, they found a
                  little opportunity and were drawn by love of the coffins of their spiritual
                  fathers, and they came back again and arrived, and again entered the same convents
                  after a space of twenty-three years<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a43" target="#n43" n="43"/>
                  that they completed, and for the second time also. And, when they had yet again
                  found them quite completely knocked to pieces and demolished and destroyed, and
                  when they had again been involved in much labour and no small expense in setting
                  them up, and had built them and set them up, then again a storm (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χειμών</foreign>) of persecution rose up against them, and they
                  were again expelled from them a third time, when they had not been allowed to
                  complete even two more years in them,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a44" target="#n44" n="44"/> and 
                  thereafter return<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a45" target="#n45" n="45"/> to the
                  southern region of the desert and of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3057">ʿArab</placeName> and of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2800">Izla</placeName>, and of all the country
                  round the city of Dara and go down and be scattered over the places and the
                  monasteries for the purpose of habitation, while even so they habitually showed
                  strength and prowess, down to the end of the life of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName> the king, at which
                  also we have now made the end of this history, which is the year eight hundred and
                     seventy-seven<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a46" target="#n46" n="46"/> according to the
                  era of the Greeks, so that the time of the persecution of these convents besides
                     <pb n="623"/>
                        <pb n="421"/>all <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2774">the East</placeName> is no less than forty-five years, and others<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a47" target="#n47" n="47"/> even more; so that even to the
                  present time at which we are committing these things to writing they are under the
                  same persecution, we for our part having completed these things in the royal city
                  at the stated time, having been under persecution together with them from
                  beginning to end, and being so even to the present time. And these things we have
                  set down concerning these brave conflicts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>)
                  and great combats, which themselves also do not fall far short of spiritual
                  heroism, the beginning of which dated from the year eight hundred and
                     thirty-two,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a48" target="#n48" n="48"/> down to the present
                  day which is the year eight hundred and seventy-eight.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a49" target="#n49" n="49"/>
                    </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-35">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-35.1" n="3"> The history of the great and admirable <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1934">community</persName> of the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1934">holy convents of the Amidenes</persName>,
                  who distinguished themselves in the great conflicts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of persecution, is ended. </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 405, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>521.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 405, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>This lost work is mentioned in the <title>Eccl. Hist.</title> (Land, p. 249,
               208), and since it related the descent of Ephraim to the East (p. 294), cannot have
               been written earlier than 537, which is about 30 years before 566 (see Introd., p.
               VI).</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 405, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 406, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>At p. 214 the number is given as 750.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 406, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>This sentence is confused and incorrect, but the meaning is clear.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 406, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 214, 260.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 406, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>521-6.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 406, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 407, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 84.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 407, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 407, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 407, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 407, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. the canonical hours.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 408, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. 1, 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 408, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>V. D. and L. wrongly <hi rend="singleQuotes">nocturna</hi>. Nocturns and
               matins have been mentioned above. Only matins, sext, vespers, and nocturns seem to
               have been common services. From ch. 17 (p. 254) and ch. 29 it seems clear that there
               was no common service between vespers and nocturns, and from the ch. 29 (p. 363) it
               seems unlikley that there was any between matins and sext.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 409, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Eph., V, 4.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 410, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See p.204, n. 1. As they had supper after vespers (p. 251), 7 and 8 P.M. can
               hardly be meant.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 410, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Our author forgets how he began this long sentence and completes the sense
               another way.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 411, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 411, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n21" target="#a21" n="21">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 411, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ch. 15.</note>
                <note xml:id="n22" target="#a22" n="22">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 412, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Acts, IX, 15.</note>
                <note xml:id="n23" target="#a23" n="23">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 413, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 62, n. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n24" target="#a24" n="24">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 414, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Lit. <hi rend="singleQuotes">blessing</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n25" target="#a25" n="25">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 415, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n26" target="#a26" n="26">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 416, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>We should perhaps understand that there were usually 50
                  <foreign>hebdomadarii</foreign> in each monastery, and that in the combined
               convent 20 out of each 50 were taken.</note>
                <note xml:id="n27" target="#a27" n="27">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 416, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>521-6.</note>
                <note xml:id="n28" target="#a28" n="28">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 416, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Often used by the Syrians in place of <foreign xml:lang="grc">έπαρχία</foreign>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n29" target="#a29" n="29">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 417, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. <hi rend="singleQuotes">Altar</hi>, for which I adopt V. D. and L.'s
               emendation; cf. 58 (f. 134 V'b). Clearly the <title>
                        <foreign>dioecesis
                     Orientis</foreign>
                    </title> is not meant, nor the eastern part of it, but a
               district lying E. of Amida.</note>
                <note xml:id="n30" target="#a30" n="30">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 417, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Syr. <hi rend="singleQuotes">Hamimtha</hi>. Cf. p. 224.</note>
                <note xml:id="n31" target="#a31" n="31">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 417, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Amm. Marc., XVIII, IX, 1; "Josh. Styl.', XXXIV; Geog. Cypr., 921.</note>
                <note xml:id="n32" target="#a32" n="32">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 417, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>It is clear from the term of 9 1/2 years given below that this should be 4
               1/2; see Dyakonov, p. 29, n. 160.</note>
                <note xml:id="n33" target="#a33" n="33">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 417, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>End of 530. See Introd., p. IV.</note>
                <note xml:id="n34" target="#a34" n="34">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 418, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This must be wrong. The descent of Ephraim was in 536/7 (see Introd., p.
               IV), and therefore the expulsion cannot have been later. The sum 2 1/2 + 7 1/2
               however is about right, and the error perh. arose from placing the return at the
               beginning of Justinian's reign, which began in Aug. 527.</note>
                <note xml:id="n35" target="#a35" n="35">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 418, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. <hi rend="singleQuotes">hill of the sycamores</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n36" target="#a36" n="36">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 418, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. <hi rend="singleQuotes">the trench</hi>; cf. Amm. Marc., XVIII, IX, 2
               ('Gumathena'). It lay on the E. bank of the Euphrates.</note>
                <note xml:id="n37" target="#a37" n="37">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 418, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Clearly wrong, perh. an error for '3 months'; see p. 419, n. 1, and
               Dyakonov, p. 30, n. 166.</note>
                <note xml:id="n38" target="#a38" n="38">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 419, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>536/7. The persecution began with the descent of Ephraim, and we should
               probably understand the extension to this district to be here meant.</note>
                <note xml:id="n39" target="#a39" n="39">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 419, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>These events are also related in the Eccl. Hist. (Land, p. 294).</note>
                <note xml:id="n40" target="#a40" n="40">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 419, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 382. n. 3.</note>
                <note xml:id="n41" target="#a41" n="41">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 419, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>
                    <hi rend="singleQuotes">Izala mons</hi>; see Amm. Marc., XVIII, VI, 12; XIX,
               IX, 4; Theoph. Sim., I, XIII, 4; Theoph. Sim.; I, XIII, 4, et passim. It was the
               range lying N. of Dara.</note>
                <note xml:id="n42" target="#a42" n="42">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 419, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>J. oddly omits Claudias, where he settled hiimself. See ch. 58 (f. 130 r'a,
               135 r' b).</note>
                <note xml:id="n43" target="#a43" n="43">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 420, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This brings us to 559; but according to 'Zach Rh.,' XII, 6, the monks were
               in Amida in 553.</note>
                <note xml:id="n44" target="#a44" n="44">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 420, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>This would be 561; but see n. 1.</note>
                <note xml:id="n45" target="#a45" n="45">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 420, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n46" target="#a46" n="46">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 420, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>565/6.</note>
                <note xml:id="n47" target="#a47" n="47">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 421, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n48" target="#a48" n="48">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 421, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>521.</note>
                <note xml:id="n49" target="#a49" n="49">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 421, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>567. See Introd., p. VII.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
