<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/828">Mari the Solitary</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/827"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/829"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/828 -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-36" n="36">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-36">
                    <head type="main">Next the Thirty-Sixth<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> History,
                  Of Father <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1875">Mare</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> the Solitary, and The Rest Moreover
                  of the Blessed Men Who Are Laid With Him in The Sepulchre of the Strangers
                  Belonging to the <persName>Monastery of the Syrians</persName> At <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2845">Sycae</placeName> Beyond the Water Above
                  the House of Mar Mama.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/>
                    </head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-36.1" n="1"> Whereas therefore we find in ancient traditions that men
                  of ancient times set themselves earnestly and diligently to make memorials of the
                  performance of various things that were performed before their times and in their
                  days, insomuch that in the course of the times down to the present time they have
                  now reached us even in our own days, which are all that are recorded severally in
                  the Holy Scriptures, firstly, in order that the power and miracles and actions of
                  God wrought through them and in their days might be known to everyone for his own
                  glory, secondly, for a memorial and remembrance of the righteousness of the same
                  just and righteous men, who at different times endeavoured to please God and do
                  his will, thirdly again, that those who should afterwards read and receive it
                  through the <pb n="625"/>
                        <pb n="423"/>writings might be imitators of their
                  practices, and eager to run the course of religion like them, since then, as we
                  said before, we ourselves observed all these things, we considered it to be a
                  matter of right and religion now also to make a record of the upright men and
                  strenuous workers of religion, our fathers and brothers, who like bright stars
                  shone by their practices all the time of their lives, and earned the privilege of
                  being gathered together by a good ending and laid in this place, in this holy
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2868">convent of us
                     Syrians</placeName> above the house of the holy <persName>Mar Mama</persName>,
                  which by the help of the grace of God was at this time erected through the
                  instrumentality of our meanness;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/>
                  the head and first of whom is the great man of God <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1875">Mare</persName> who was named by everyone
                     <quote>the solitary</quote>, and by others<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/>
                        <quote>he of his patches</quote>, on account of the pieces of unsightly and
                  ill-matched rags of hair and of wool out of which he had put together his clothing
                  and covering<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> and sewn them together
                  in ill-matched fashion. This saint then was by birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from the country of the Amidenes,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> 
                  that is from Ingilene from a village 
                  called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2753">Beth Marka</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> 
                  which is indeed in our neighbourhood, <pb n="626"/>
                        <pb n="424"/>and, while this man was a layman, and was
                  powerful of stature and of more than ordinary strength, he became also a son of
                  the covenant<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> in the church of his
                  village. And, when he had completed about thirty years, even as many were advising
                  him and his parents that he ought to form an alliance, and when his parents were
                  making preparations for the wedding function, and the day arrived on which they
                  were to celebrate the wedding, suddenly Grace, which had secretly seen that he was
                  to be <quote>a chosen vessel</quote>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> for 
                  the glory of his Lord, dawned in his heart and on his mind, and he resolved
                  instead of bodily communion, to which many accidents are attached and against
                  which is set the dissolution of death, to pursue spiritual communion, bearing his
                  Lord's gentle and light yoke<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> upon
                  his neck, and placing his cross upon his shoulder and going after him. And so he
                  rose in the middle of the night and prayed to the Lord to direct his way that he
                  might go after him, and grant him the privilege of doing his will; and he directed
                  his way to the great man of God, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1980">Paul the anchorite</persName>, who was also a performer of mighty works and
                  miracles, a record of whose history <pb n="627"/>
                        <pb n="425"/>we have also
                  introduced at small proportion and in defective fashion into the histories which
                  precede this.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> When then the blessed
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1875">Mare</persName> reached this
                  man, and presented to him a request to grant him the privilege of living with him
                  and receiving training from him, he received him on his promising him repentance
                  toward God, having given him much instruction in the ordinances and labours of
                  monasticism. And so he remained with him five years, imitating his divine
                  practices, and decreeing for himself severe labours of fasting and prayer and
                  protracted recitation of service, and constant vigil, so that he gave himself rest
                  for one hour or two only for the sake of the demands of nature, and through the
                  whole extent of the night he performed a constant series of inclinations and
                  genuflexions with prayer, and besides these things barefootedness and austerity
                  and abstinence, and humility and sorrow, and tears. And by all these things he
                  used to train himself in religion, and subdue his body and bring it into
                  subjection with sorrow and repentance, insomuch that many were surprised at his
                  labours, and even that holy old man himself, when he saw the immoderate severity
                  of his practices, would strongly reprove him, and admonish him not to exceed the
                     <pb n="628"/>
                        <pb n="426"/>bounds of moderation in his dealing with his body; a
                  thing which he also repeated to us ourselves, when we once came to the holy old
                  man in order to be blessed by him and receive his prayer, and to visit the blessed
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1875">Mare</persName> also, concerning
                  the severity of his practices how he exceeded the bounds of moderation in his
                  dealing with his body, insomuch that in the hardness of winter, when snow was
                  lying about a man's stature high, he would go out to the mountains without an
                  outer garment, having nothing on his feet below or above, and thus he would cut
                  wood and make great loads, and thus he would carry them, cleaving the snow and
                  sinking into it, so much so that blood would flow and drop from the whole of the
                  flesh of his feet, and even so he would not pay attention to them. And, when we
                  learned from the holy man about such severity, inasmuch as we were acquainted with
                  him from his childhood<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> and with the
                  family (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1875">Mare</persName>, we used to admonish him
                  earnestly to accomodate himself to the will of his spiritual father. But he fell
                  on his face weeping and saying, <quote>Forgive me, my fathers; the body has not
                     received what the contumacy of its arrogant behaviour against the soul
                     deserves, and I have not yet done to it <pb n="629"/>
                            <pb n="427"/>anything
                     adequate to my sins and the vices in my soul which arise from the body; but I
                     am contriving means to bring it into subjection and subdue it, that even now it
                     may cease injuring my soul</quote>, with many similar things which he would
                  repeat to us with affliction and with tears; so that, when we were hearing them,
                  we were surprised at the earnestness of his will and the affliction of his mind.
                  But, when he had completed five years with that blessed man, since he was still
                  being constantly pestered by his parents and by his kin (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>), for this reason he determined to remove completely from
                  parents and kin (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) and from all
                  acquaintances, insomuch that, having asked for prayer and release from the blessed
                  man his master, he set out on his journey and departed from all the countries of
                     <placeName>Syria</placeName>, and came to the countries of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/715">Egypt</placeName> and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2847">Thebais</placeName>; and thenceforth he
                  used to go to and fro in the desert of the saints, and. he would betake himself to
                  certain great men and solitaries, and ask for their prayers, and eagerly observe
                  their practices, and set himself to imitate their labours with all his soul,
                  insomuch that after these things he gave himself to the life of a recluse in one
                  of the deserts; and thus he thenceforth went on distinguishing himself <pb n="630"/>
                        <pb n="428"/>by laborious practices for a long period of time. And, when he
                  had completed about 15 years in this conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>), a great disturbance arose in the city of Alexandria on
                  account of the faith,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> insomuch that
                  many were expelled and driven from their places, men who would not consent to
                  conform to the <placeName>Chalcedonian communion</placeName>. And they came even
                  to the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1875">Mare</persName>
                  himself; and, when they had pressed him greatly and he did not acquiesce in their
                  communion, they drove him also out and expelled him from his cell. And from such a
                  reason as this he was seized by a vehement desire to go up to <placeName xml:lang="grc">Constantinople</placeName>, so that he 
                  applied<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> himself to dealing a severe reproof
                  to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">the king</persName> and
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">queen</persName>; and he went up
                  and reached the royal city. But with regard to the blessed man's entry into the
                  presence of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">the king</persName> and
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">queen</persName>, and the rough
                  character of his meeting with them, and the insulting words which he addressed to
                  them, and his audacity and his contemptuous conduct moreover to them of this we
                  have not thought it well to make a written record<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> in the history of his life not only on account <pb n="631"/>
                        <pb n="429"/>of their violence,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> and the insults and the contemptuous conduct which he used toward the
                  rulers of the world, but further also because perhaps, even if they had been
                  written, the difficulty of believing among the hearers would be very great and not
                  small, that these things could easily be said not only to kings, the holders of
                  the power of this world, but even also to contemptible and mean persons. But, when
                  he sternly rebuked the royal pair as we have said with<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/> such freedom (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>) and sternness, which he had indeed possessed from his
                  boyhood, they as by the grace of God accepted it from him humbly and with fear
                  without violent action, as from a great man and a perfect solitary, especially
                  because they saw the freedom (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>) of his
                  speech, that he spoke and rebuked and reproved courageously and without fear, not
                  being frightened by the crown or alarmed by the purple, and they said, <quote>This
                     man is in truth a spiritual philosopher</quote>; his dress being as we
                  described it above, hideous through the patching together of unsightly and
                  ill-matched rags differing from one another, and fastenings whereby they were
                  joined together by unsightly cords of hair and of wool, insomuch that <pb n="632"/>
                        <pb n="430"/>every aperture (?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/> made by a fastening of his garments covered more than two or three fingers'
                  lengths, insomuch that no mean poor man in the world was anywhere to be seen who
                  was clothed in them or perhaps would ever consent to be clothed in them, not even
                  if he had nothing to cover his nakedness. But, when the victorious king observed
                  these things, he greatly wondered at him and gave him a promise that he would do
                  for him whatever he commanded; and yet more the believing <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">queen</persName> held him as a great and
                  righteous man, and continued entreating him to remain with her in her palace
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>), that he might speak to her words
                  of profit. And, while she on her side was making this request of him upon her
                     face,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/> he on the other hand
                  answered her with stern reproofs. And, when she saw that he would not comply with
                  her wishes, she quietly ordered her own treasurer (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σακελλάριος</foreign>) to bring her<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a21" target="#n21" n="21"/> a hundredweight (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κεντηνάριον</foreign>) of
                  gold, thinking that by this she would soften the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1875">Mare</persName> and make him yield. And,
                  when it came and she offered it him bound up, and began entreating him to accept
                  it and divide it between the poor and his needs, then after gazing sternly at it
                  he grasped the bag (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μαρσύπιον</foreign>) containing the
                     hundred-<pb n="633"/>
                        <pb n="431"/>weight (<foreign xml:lang="grc">xevτnváρtov</foreign>) in one hand, and hurled it and threw it no small
                  distance, so that all the chamberlains and everyone who saw it were seized with
                  great astonishment, to think that he was so powerful and of such well-knit frame,
                  as we stated at the beginning, and since he had flung<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a22" target="#n22" n="22"/> it to a distance just as if it were something full of
                  light apples, saying to her, <quote>
                            <quote>Thy money go to perdition with
                        thee</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a23" target="#n23" n="23"/> because through
                     this you wish to tempt me and mock me</quote>. And after answering her with
                  many other stern words which we refrain from recording he left her and went out;
                  and she remained in distress and fear, and she and all her chamberlains as well
                  were wondering at the blessed man's bodily strength, how he thought nothing of
                  throwing a weight of a hundred pounds (<foreign xml:lang="grc">λίτρα</foreign>) of
                  gold to such a distance, insomuch that the story was heard over the whole palace
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>) and over the whole of this city,
                  and was spoken of with astonishment by many persons. When the blessed man was
                  passing along a street of the city, his eyes were fixed on the ground, since he
                  had determined in his mind never to see the face of men in it. And he left it; and
                  so he went over to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2845">Sycae</placeName> beyond the water,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a24" target="#n24" n="24"/> and climbed the mountain to the north-west of it, where <pb n="634"/>
                        <pb n="432"/>there are also graves; and there he resided and performed the
                  labour of his practices, satisfying his needs with wild herbs. But the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">queen</persName>, because she was a
                  believer and knew that she had distressed him in the matter of the hundredweight
                  of gold (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κεντηνάριον</foreign>), made careful search for
                  him; and on learning that he had left the city and was dwelling on the other side
                  among the mountains sent some of her most distinguished chamberlains to entreat
                  him to forgive her, and as a favour to herself to receive from her something that
                  his needs required, whatever he wished. And, having taken much trouble and with
                  difficulty discovered him, because he used to move from place to place, they
                  delivered an earnest request to him as they had been ordered, and, absolutely
                  refusing to grant their request, he sent her a message through them, <quote>Think
                     not that you possess anything which God's bondmen need, except religion if it
                     exists in you</quote>. And, when those who were sent came back again and she
                  learned where he was, she sent yet again; and thenceforth they used to pester the
                  blessed man every day; and he was compelled to remove to other places; and again
                  they would find it out and discover him. And thenceforth many persons used to
                  repair to him to receive his prayer; and they were specially astonished at seeing
                  his <pb n="635"/>
                        <pb n="433"/>unsightly clothing. And he asked and palm-leaves,
                  were brought to him, out of which he supplied his needs by the work of his hands,
                  since he absolutely refused to allow anything to enter his mouth except from the
                  labour of his hands. And, if he was prevented from working with his hands on
                  account of those who came to and fro to him, he would go two and three days, and
                  sometimes even a whole week, and then taste bread, except wild herbs;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a25" target="#n25" n="25"/> and sometimes he would feed on the
                  berries of the bushes, and sometimes on the nuts of the trees. But in the
                  winter-time he was compelled to put up a hut for himself on one of these heights,
                  and shelter himself in it from the severity of the winter. And, while he was thus
                  dwelling peacefully on these mountains, Satan the hater of good things did not
                  overlook it and leave him untried, but he set up robbers (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ληστής</foreign>) against him, ten men, who, having seen the chamberlains and
                  the other great senators (<foreign xml:lang="grc">συγχλητικός</foreign>) coming to
                  and fro to the blessed man, thought that he was receiving gold and storing it in
                  his hut; and so in the middle of the night they fell upon him and surrounded him,
                  and they flung out their hands to <pb n="636"/>
                        <pb n="434"/>seize him and bind
                  him. But he, being stronger than they, threw their hands of him as if they were
                  sick and tortured (?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a26" target="#n26" n="26"/> men, and he
                  went on entreating them, saying, <quote>Nay, my sons, do not lose your soul. Why
                     do you seek me the poor man?</quote> But they on their side said to him:
                     <quote>Unless you give us the gold which the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">queen</persName> is sending you, we will
                     kill you at once.</quote> But he returned them answer, saying: <quote>Take it,
                     my sons, that to me no gold has ever (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ποτέ</foreign>)
                     been sent by the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">queen</persName>, or by others. And, if I desired gold, I should not be
                     residing here</quote>. When he had said these words, one came back with a club
                  and gave him a severe blow, and they all surrounded him, having also drawn their
                  swords. And, when he saw that they had set themselves to kill him, and he did not
                  mollify them by entreating them with gentle words, he looked straight at the one
                  who was holding the club, and seized and dragged the club out of his hand; and he
                  seized his hair with one hand, and threw him on his face. And another ran up to
                  smite him with the sword, and he on his side smote him with the club, and stopped
                  him; and his sword fell and he took hold of him, and threw him on the top of his
                  companion, and the third, and the fourth. When <pb n="637"/>
                        <pb n="435"/>the
                  others saw it they began to run away, and he ran after them; and he overtook three
                  more of them; and of every man whom he smote with the club he made himself master;
                  and thus he mastered seven of them. And he returned and bound the seven of them,
                  and set them in a row, and he collected their swords and their clubs, and placed
                  them together on one side; and he sat down and jeered at them saying: <quote>I
                     begged you, my sons, saying, <quote>Leave me alone</quote>, and <quote>Why do
                        you seek the poor man?</quote> And I was distressed that you did not comply
                     with my request. And now, my sons, rest and be quiet till the morning</quote>.
                  And, lying as they were bound and disgraced, they went on adjuring him to release
                  them and to be merciful to them, and not to deliver them up. But he on his side
                  went on jeering at their valour, and saying to them: <quote>Learn never again to
                     trust to your valour, and do not at any time (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ποτέ</foreign>) despise and look down upon a poor man</quote>. And, when he
                  had been admonishing them till the morning, those also who came to him saw them,
                  and they went on threatening to deliver them up to the prefect (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ύπαρχος</foreign>). But he on his side would not consent, but
                  released them and sent them away with much advice and admonition; but their clubs
                  and their swords he took from them. But three of them ran away and escaped <pb n="638"/>
                        <pb n="436"/>from his hands. When these things had thus fallen out,
                  and it had become known to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">the
                     king</persName> and the prefect (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ύπαρχος</foreign>) and
                  the rest of the senators (<foreign xml:lang="grc">συγκλητικός</foreign>), these
                  wondered at him and spoke much about him. Moreover there came a chamberlain also
                  as well; and on seeing the swords and the clubs and learning about the rest he was
                  surprised; and he took the swords and the clubs, and brought them in and showed
                  them to the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">queen</persName> and
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">the king</persName>; and on
                  seeing them they said: <quote>Here besides power of prayer power of arm was also
                     required</quote>. And, when he had for many years<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a27" target="#n27" n="27"/> been. dwelling on these mountains in this way and
                  distinguishing himself by excellent practices, he was hard pressed by his bodily
                  requirements through the fact that the work of his hands was not sufficient for
                  his requirements and for hospitality to poor brothers, and further that he had
                  determined in his mind never to support himself on the labour and sweat, that is
                  on the sins, of others.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a28" target="#n28" n="28"/> And, while
                  he was going about on these mountains and among the villas (<foreign xml:lang="grc">προάστειον</foreign>), he saw a villa<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a29" target="#n29" n="29"/> suited for a life of retreat, and he considered that,
                  if he performed spiritual employment in it, it would <pb n="639"/>
                        <pb n="437"/>suit him for manual labour also as well and for the employment of providing for
                  his necessary requirements. And so he spoke to one of the chamberlains,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a30" target="#n30" n="30"/> and he bought it from another
                  chamberlain for live pounds (<foreign xml:lang="grc">λίτρα</foreign>) of gold,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a31" target="#n31" n="31"/> and thenceforth he used to sow and
                  reap in it, and supply his own private needs and those of those of the other
                  people who used to visit him, and of the poor. And, when he had completed five
                  years in it, while many persons among the magnates and others used to visit him,
                  there happened the beginning of the great plague in the year eight hundred and
                     fifty-three;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a32" target="#n32" n="32"/> and, while he was
                  practising mighty spiritual labours, and subduing his body and bringing it into
                     subjection<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a33" target="#n33" n="33"/> by tilling the ground
                  for his necessary bodily requirements, and was reproving and admonishing and
                  teaching all who visited him by the spiritual teaching of the divine scriptures,
                  and stoutly always reproving <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">the
                     king</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">queen</persName> with great freedom (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>) without fear, and everyone marvelled at his teaching and
                  at his deeds and at his words, and at the stoutness of his soul in addition to
                  that of his body and in addition to his thoughts,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a34" target="#n34" n="34"/> then by the sudden destruction ot the plague, as <pb n="640"/>
                        <pb n="438"/>has been stated above, everyone was in perturbation and
                  doubt and confusion, insomuch that the blessed man passed his time in affliction
                  and great sorrow, and occupied himself with constant prayer and petition to God,
                  while he asked of God, and a revelation was made to him about his own personal
                  departure also after a short time. Then he sent a pressing message to the chief
                  men of the palace (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>), asking them to
                  send him craftsmen and supplies that he might make a tomb for strangers and also
                  for himself. And, when the craftsmen and the supplies had been sent to him, and
                  men to superintend the work, in a few days he built these two great houses, the
                  strangers' tombs, and completed porticoes, and built a <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2816">martyrs' chapel</placeName>martyrs' chapel
                  also as well between them, and he also made a coffin (?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a35" target="#n35" n="35"/> for himself, in which he was privileged to be
                     laid.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a36" target="#n36" n="36"/> But, when he had completed
                  the work, and knew that the day was at hand that had been told him in the
                  revelation about his end, then, the coffin (?) being open which he had prepared
                  for himself to be laid in it, while he was kneeling and praying on behalf of the
                  whole world of men, on the third day he yielded up his spirit. And, this having
                     <pb n="641"/>
                        <pb n="439"/>been made known to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">the king</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">queen</persName>, with great zeal they sent
                  some of the leading and eminent men of the palace (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>), chamberlains and senators (<foreign xml:lang="grc">συγχλητικός</foreign>) and bishops and elergymen and many monks, and thus they
                  buried the blessed man's body with a great procession. We have recorded these few
                  things out of many for the sake of a memorial and in order to gain his blessing
                  and his prayers, having passed over many of his labours and of his practices on
                  account of the length of the history. </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-36">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-36.1" n="2"> The history of father <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1875">Mare</persName> the solitary 
                  is ended.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a37" target="#n37" n="37"/>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 422, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Perh. really 37th; see Introd., p XI.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 422, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>See
               p. 187, n. 1, text, n. 3 above and p. 426, n. 3, 11.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 422, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>See
               p. 298, n. 2, p. 387, n. 3, and p. 431, n. 3.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 423, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See
               ch. 38 fin. and H. E., II, 41.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 423, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sic
               syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 423, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>See
               p. 319, n. 2, and n. on ch. 49.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 423, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Sc.
               the province of Mesopotamia, of which Amida was capital.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 423, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>B.
               'Zbina' (marg. 'Mzbana') = bought.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 424, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>I.e. took minor orders. Cf. p. 241.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 424, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>Acts, IX, 15.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 424, n.
               3</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., XI, 30.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 425, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Ch. 6.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 426, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Perhaps we should read (<hi rend="singleQuotes">our childhood</hi>);
               see p. 428, n. 1.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 428, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>This must refer to the events of 536, which dates his stay in Egypt
               circ. 521-36, his life with Paul circ. 516-21, and his birth circ. 486; but I cannot
               reconcile this with J. having known him from his childhood. 15 years must be too
               much, for in 521 J. was a boy of 14 in the convent of Maro (see Introd.).</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 428, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>We require rather <hi rend="singleQuotes">might apply</hi>; but the
               text cannot be otherwise rendered.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 428, n.
               3</orig>
                    </choice>The Syr. is hardly grammatical, but the sense is clear.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 429, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>The sense shows that the violence of the insults is meant, but acc.
               to the grammar it would be easier to refer it to the king and queen.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 429, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>Mss. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 430, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>should mean 'fork' or 'tongs'. This meaning perh. is that the rags
               parted from one another in the shape of a fork.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 430, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>B <hi rend="singleQuotes">request of him for these
               things</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n21" target="#a21" n="21">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 430, n.
               3</orig>
                    </choice>A <hi rend="singleQuotes">him</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n22" target="#a22" n="22">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 431, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>is not otherwise known, but the meaning is clear.</note>
                <note xml:id="n23" target="#a23" n="23">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 431, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>Acts, VIII, 20.</note>
                <note xml:id="n24" target="#a24" n="24">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 431, n.
               3</orig>
                    </choice>This passage shows the meaning of to be as above; see p. 387, n. 2
               (cf. also p. 432, l. 5).</note>
                <note xml:id="n25" target="#a25" n="25">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 433, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic. syr. The meaning appy. is that during the week he ate herbs
               only.</note>
                <note xml:id="n26" target="#a26" n="26">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 434, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>This seems to be corrupt, but both mss. have it.</note>
                <note xml:id="n27" target="#a27" n="27">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 436, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>As he died in 542/3 (p. 437, 438) and came to Constantinople nor
               earlier than 536 (p. 428, n. 1), if he really lived 5 years in the villa (pg. 437),
               he cannot have been more than one year on the mountains.</note>
                <note xml:id="n28" target="#a28" n="28">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 436, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>Cf. p. 175.</note>
                <note xml:id="n29" target="#a29" n="29">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 436, n.
               3</orig>
                    </choice>V. D. and L. render <hi rend="singleQuotes">hanc villam</hi>, and
               infer that J. was writing in the villa; but is only the weak antecedent.</note>
                <note xml:id="n30" target="#a30" n="30">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 437, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>From II. E., II, 41, it seems probable that this was Callinicus,
               afterwards praep. sacri cubiculi: see p. 438, n. 2 (Dyakonov, p. 85).</note>
                <note xml:id="n31" target="#a31" n="31">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 437, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>Circ. £ 225 = fr. 5625.</note>
                <note xml:id="n32" target="#a32" n="32">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 437, n.
               3</orig>
                    </choice>542.</note>
                <note xml:id="n33" target="#a33" n="33">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 437, n.
               4</orig>
                    </choice>I Cor., IX, 27</note>
                <note xml:id="n34" target="#a34" n="34">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 437, n.
               5</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n35" target="#a35" n="35">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 438, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>The word is here masc., but below is fem.</note>
                <note xml:id="n36" target="#a36" n="36">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 438, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>Since nothing is said about obtaining the land for the cemetery, we
               may infer that it was in the ground of the villa; and, since the cemetery is
               described as belonging to the monastery of the Syrians (p. 222), the monastery was
               probably on the site of the villa; but that M. himself made it a monastery (Dyakonov,
               p. 83) I see little evidence (see Introd., p. XI).</note>
                <note xml:id="n37" target="#a37" n="37">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 439, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Ch. 37 is missing; see Introd., p. VII, IX ff.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
