<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/829">Aaron</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/828"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/830"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/829 -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-38" n="38">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-38">
               <head type="main">Next the Thirty-Eighth History, of the Excellent Blessed Man the Holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1533">Aaron</persName> the Presbyter, and the
                  Rest of the Presbyters and Deacons Who Were Afterwards Laid in the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2816">Sepulchre</placeName> That Was Built by The
                  Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1875">Mare</persName>
                  <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>
               </head>
               <ab xml:id="section-38.1" n="1"> This excellent blessed man therefore <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1533">Aaron</persName> the presbyter was by his
                  birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from the country of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2743">Armenia</placeName>; but from his childhood
                  he had left <pb n="642"/>
                  <pb n="440"/>his country and had also made himself alien
                  to his kin (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) and his acquaintances, and he
                  chose for himself to pass the days of his life in a monastic convent in retreat
                  and religion, from the early age of his youth. And besides the fact that
                  simplicity and humility were also implanted in him by his nature, since he had
                  devoted himself to religion, he chose for himself marvellous practices of
                  excellence, and taught himself meekness and obedience, and acquired true love,
                  having bound himself under the yoke of labours, vigils and fasts and constant
                  prayers without wearying; and, even as he resembled his namesake <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1533">Aaron</persName> in name and in character,
                  so, when he had attained to the order of the priesthood, he would recite the
                  service yet more with all integrity and devoutness with fear and many tears, after
                  he had at first for a long time refused to perform the service, contending and
                  saying, <quote>I am not worthy to approach God's holy altar</quote>; and, when we
                  and others had been insistently demanding of him to perform the service of the
                  priesthood, in order that he might not transgress against the rule of obedience,
                  he would go through this with sorrow and fear, while he also used to subdue his
                  body and bring it into subjection<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/>
                  by the bodily labours of agriculture, in the vineyard and the garden, and the
                  reception of strangers, and all the other tasks inside the monastery, so much so
                  that late in the evening when he <pb n="643"/>
                  <pb n="441"/>came of necessity to
                  rest his body, he could scarcely turn his body round, from weariness and also from
                  the labour of standing at the service. But sometimes he would stand on a
                  standing-post<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> at night, and
                  sometimes he would sit on a chair (<foreign xml:lang="grc">θρόνος</foreign>), so
                  that he completely refrained from bed and rug, or<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> to give rest to his body so as to lie upon his side,
                  until he was smitten by sore diseases and advanced old age, and then he was forced
                  to lie upon a rug laid on a plank, while even so he in no way gave up the great
                  purpose of spiritual labours. And during all the period of thirty years that we
                  dwelt together, some in the eastern countries, and some, viz. most of them, in the
                  western in the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/586">royal
                     city</placeName>, and further in many persecutions, it was never seen that this
                  strenuous worker showed negligence in the tilling of <persName>Christ</persName>'s
                  vineyard from the morning of the beginning of his life down to the evening. of the
                  end of his days, nor, when he fell into extreme old age and a combination of
                  diseases, did he shrink from divine labours. Once he fell under the severe pain of
                  a gangrene that was formed in his loins; and in this way he bore this distress
                  with great devoutness, until his loin was eaten up, and was cut away and vanished
                  down to the root of it, and his trouble began to <pb n="644"/>
                  <pb n="442"/>pass
                  inside him. And we, seeing him distressed by a sore disease and grievously
                  lacerated in secret, would ask of him to tell us what his trouble was; and he,
                  until his affliction became intense, stoutly endured, being constant in prayer and
                  filling his mouth with thanksgiving and the praise of God. But at last when the
                  passing of water from him was stopped he was forced, and so he consented to reveal
                  and make known his trouble, when the whole of his loin was found to have been
                  eaten away and consumed, so that the physicians contrived to make a tube of lead
                  and place it to pass his water, while they also applied plasters and drugs to him.
                  And so the ulcer was healed; and after the testing of this trial he lived yet
                  eighteen years, giving thanks to God; and the leaden tube was also in position for
                  the purpose of passing his water. And so, after we had together through God's help
                  in association with some of our other brethren set up this monastic place, he
                  attained to an admirable and righteous ending, on a day in the month of the 1st
                  Theshrin, on the twenty-second of it, in the year eight<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> hundred and seventy-two; and he was laid in the
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2816">sepulchre</placeName> that was
                  built by the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1875">Mare</persName>. And these things we have recorded in few words for a
                  remembrance <pb n="645"/>
                  <pb n="443"/>and memorial of the strenuous worker of
                  <persName>Christ</persName>, about the matters connected with his beautiful
                  mode of life of which we are witnesses. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-38">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-38.1" n="2"> The history of the excellent blessed man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1533">Aaron</persName> the presbyter is ended.
               </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 439, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>This clearly refers to the following chapters.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 440, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>I Cor., IX, 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 441, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Cf. p. 410.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 441, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Sic syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 442, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ms. <hi rend="singleQuotes">nine</hi>. The date is 22 Oct., 560.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
