<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/831">Abraham the Priest</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/830"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/832"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/831 -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-40" n="40">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-40">
               <head type="main">Next the Fortieth History Concerning the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1554">Abraham</persName> the Old Man the
                  Presbyter, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3270">Zwtʾ</persName>
                  Moreover the Presbyter His Bodily Son, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3204">Daniel</persName> the Deacon Sister's
                  Son.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>
               </head>
               <ab xml:id="section-40.1" n="1"> This blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1554">Abraham</persName> therefore, the old man,
                  was by birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from the district of
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/493">Sophanene</placeName>, from a
                  village called such-and-such.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> This
                  man, <pb n="648"/>
                  <pb n="446"/>having at a certain time come to the royal city,
                  betook himself to us; and, having been received by us as a stranger, on the second
                  day he cast himself down weeping and entreating to be received by us, and admitted
                  to the monastic order (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τάγμα</foreign>). And we on our
                  side, observing the burden of his old age, thought that his request was a pretext
                  and not genuine, and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> we continued
                  closely examining him, that he might let us know the true reason of his coming to
                  the royal city, and if he had any fact to tell us about his intention, and we
                  would not fail in anything that we could do to help him. And he, having cast
                  himself upon his face and weeping, continued swearing to us <quote>I have no
                     concern in this world, except to repent for my sins, and if may be admitted to
                     the monastic habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>), that in it I may
                     serve and please God during this remnant of life which he has appointed for
                     me</quote>. And, after much conversation had been held with him concerning
                  these things, we allowed him to make trial of his own self, while we also on our
                  part observed his perseverance. And, when he had thus completed two years, being
                  constant in fasting and prayer and constant vigil by night, and humility and
                  obedience, while he was also always entreating to be admitted to <pb n="649"/>
                  <pb n="447"/>the order and the beloved habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) of monasticism, so also upon many testimonies and admonitions
                  he was admitted to the monastic habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>).
                  And, while he was accomplishing the labour of his practices every day with many
                  tears and much earnestness and humility, and when he had reached the period of
                  five years after his training, he was on account of his marvellous modes of life
                  by constraint and much compulsion admitted to ordination to the presbyterate. But
                  after a short time his bodily son also whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3270">Zwtʾ</persName>, and his brother's son
                  whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3204">Daniel</persName>
                  from <placeName>Syria</placeName> came to him, having learned about his modes of
                  life, and that he had been admitted to the monastic habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>). And, when they saw him thus lahouring in the practices of
                  religion, God opened their own heart also as well, and they began to request that
                  they also as well might be admitted to the honoured monastic habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>). And while he himself from that time continued
                  giving them much admonition and correction and teaching, he was presenting a
                  petition on their behalf that they might be received. And, this having also been
                  done in order to gratify him, they also as well were taught<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> the devout monastic habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>), living a whole-heartod and obedient life, with all
                  earnestness and religion. After a period of some years they also were <pb n="650"/>
                  <pb n="448"/>admitted to the rank of the diaconate; and thenceforth for many
                  years they earnestly and whole-heartedly and obediently occupied themselves with
                  us in the work of the ministry in the district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2747">Asia</placeName> in converting men from the
                  deceitfulness of paganism, gratifying our soul every day by their earnestness and
                  whole-heartedness and diligence, with the old man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1554">Abraham</persName> and the devout
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1533">Aaron</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1853">Leontius</persName> the presbyters, with
                  all the other strenuous workers their other brothers, of whom also too we shall
                  one after another make record, each one of whom worked and laboured strenuously in
                  his time without weariness in the householder's vineyard,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> that is in the great salvation which God's grace
                  wrought in our times, consisting in the conversion of many thousands from the
                  worship of fiends and the ceremonies of idolatry to the fear of God. While then we
                  were engaged in the same ministry in the districts of
                  <placeName>Caria</placeName>, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3204">Daniel</persName> the deacon ended his course in the same ministry, seeing
                  wonderful visions, and it having been revealed to him that he would be carried
                  away to the blissful country; and, having fallen asleep, he was laid in the
                  monastery called that of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2782">Gordiana</placeName> hard by <placeName>the city of Antioch</placeName> in
                  <placeName>Caria</placeName>. And, when we returned to the royal city, the
                  blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1554">Abraham</persName> himself
                  also ended the course of his life-practices in a <pb n="651"/>
                  <pb n="449"/>good
                  old age; and he was laid with his blessed spiritual brothers <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1533">Aaron</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1853">Leontius</persName>. And the blessed
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3270">Zwtʾ</persName> was afterwards
                  admitted to the honour of the presbyterate, and he took over the charge of the
                  whole convent and all its belongings with great diligence and much
                  single-mindedness, insomuch that he laboured at the completion and restoration of
                  the building of the martyrs' chapel of this monastery<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> and wearied himself excessively beyond his strength,
                  together with all the rest of our brothers, and by their means it was completed,
                  when we ourselves had gone back again, and were engaged in the work of the
                  ministry in the same districts of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2747">Asia</placeName>. And, when after the space of a year and a half we came back,
                  and saw the product of his labours and his industry, we were astonished and gave
                  thanks to God, though for fear of pride we did not tell him openly (?).<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> At the same time he also too was
                  brought to the consummation of death, and gained the privilege of being laid by
                  the bones of his father the holy old man. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-40">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-40.1" n="2"> It is ended. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 445, n.
                     1</orig>
               </choice>Below he is called brother's son.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 445, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Or
               <hi rend="singleQuotes">Flht</hi>. The reading is doubtful.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 446, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ms.
               om.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 447, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sic
               syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 448, n.
                     1</orig>
               </choice>Matth., XX, 1-16. It is not stated in ch. 38 that Aaron took part in
               the conversion of the pagans.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 449, n.
                     1</orig>
               </choice>Probably that built by Mare (p. 438).</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 449, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>The
               ms. is unintelligible, but a change of one letter gives the above sense.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
