<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/832">Bassianus, Romanus, and Simeon</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/831"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/833"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/832 -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-41" n="41">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-41">
               <head type="main">Next the Forty-First History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1630">Bassian</persName> the Solitary, And
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2040">Romanus</persName> the Presbyter
                  and Visitor of the Great Convent of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/233">Thel 'Adda'</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> and of
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2093">Simeon</persName> the
                  Archimandrite,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> Who Are Laid in
                  the Sepulchre With These Holy Old Men.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/>
               </head>
               <ab xml:id="section-41.1" n="1"> To describe the rest of the practices and asceticism and
                  manner of life in the desert of this blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1630">Bassian</persName> the presbyter and
                  solitary, things which we have not seen nor heard, seemed to us superfluous; but,
                  when for a short time we had received the privilege of intercourse with the great
                  blessed man of God, in his labour and his speech and the affliction of his tears
                  and his teaching, while he mourned and wept first for his disturbance and his
                  ejection from the desert, which (he said) was brought about through the violence
                  and contentious conduct of other solitaries, then afterwards also, when we were
                  making inquiries of him with regard to the affliction shown by his many floods of
                  tears and constant sighs, he showed greater distress by grievous <pb n="653"/>
                  <pb n="451"/>sobs, saying, <quote>Who then (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρα</foreign>),
                     pray, is there even if he were a man possessing a heart of stone who would not
                     weep over the delusion and captivity and destruction of the race (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) of men? For lo! everyone is running against
                     himself contrary to religion, and everyone is with all his strength intent upon
                     evil things with naught to hinder, and we all behave ourselves like men without
                     God, and like deaf animals without law (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμος</foreign>) and without fear of the dreadful judgment to come, and
                     everyone is of his own will casting himself into the pit of destruction unto
                     destruction; and by all this destruction of Adam's race a festival has been
                     created for Satan and joy for the fiends who are carrying away the race
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) of Adam that was fashioned in love
                     and after its deviation was rescued; and now lo! the hosts of darkness are
                     mocking at its destruction, and rejoice to be carrying many to participate in
                     the torment of their destruction. In regard of these things, our father, who
                     would not weep, who would not be afflicted, who would not wail, who would not
                     make mourning like a jackal, and lamentation like a jackal's whelp, since the
                     force of error and destruction has borne away men who are bought by the blood
                     of God and rescued by his cross?</quote>. While the blessed man was repeating
                  these things and more than them in his <pb n="654"/>
                  <pb n="452"/>affliction, all
                  who heard him were marvelling; and, despising all this confused life, they also as
                  well were being brought to afflictions and tears with him, everyone marvelling at
                  the blessed man's labour and affliction and teaching. While he was doing and
                  teaching these things, a revelation was made to him concerning his end and his
                  departure after a few days, while he said, <quote>Pray also for the miserable
                     sinner, for at the end of twenty days I shall depart from the body</quote>,
                  having also adjured my meanness, <quote>Bury this my sinful body in your
                     monastery, and pray for me</quote>. When we had been saying these many things,
                  and that sabbath-day<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> was at hand,
                  he rose and prayed and offered the oblation, and gave it to many, having received
                  it also himself, and bade farewell to all. And during the night he became ill, and
                  on the twentieth day he fell asleep; and so we carried him in a procession over
                  the water to our monastery<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/>
                  according to his injunction; and his holy body was buried and laid in the same
                  tomb according to his injunction; by whose prayers together with those of all the
                  saints who please God may all we sinners who provoke our Creator be admitted to
                  mercy. Yea and Amen! And the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2040">Romanus</persName> who also was a great
                  and whole-hearted old man, <pb n="655"/>
                  <pb n="453"/>who was
                  <foreign>apocrisiarius</foreign> of the great convent of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/233">Thel 'Adda</placeName>, who himself also as
                  well lived in the same house of a certain great and believing man in which the
                  blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1630">Bassian</persName> also
                  fell asleep, was also afterwards himself too brought to the departure from the
                  bodily life, and himself also was laid in the same grave with the rest of the
                  blessed men. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-41">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-41.1" n="2"> The history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1630">Bassian</persName> the solitary and
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2040">Romanus</persName> the presbyter
                  is ended. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 450, n.
                     1</orig>
               </choice>Near Antioch (Wright, CBM., p. 498).</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 450, n.
                     2</orig>
               </choice>There is nothing about Simeon in the ch., nor is he mentioned in the
               subscription. See Introd., p. VII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 450, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>In
               B the title is: <hi rend="singleQuotes">A history concerning the blessed B. the
                  solitary by the same Mar John of Asia</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 452, n.
                     1</orig>
               </choice>I.e., the day on which he was to go to his rest.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 452, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>See
               p. 431, n. 3.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
