<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/836">Isaac</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/835"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/837"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/836 -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-45" n="45">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-45">
               <head type="main">Next the Forty-Fifth<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> History, of
                  a Perfect and Excellent Blessed Man Whose Name Was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1788">Isaac</persName>.</head>
               <ab xml:id="section-45.1" n="1"> As therefore it is written that <quote>a city that is
                     built upon a mountain cannot be hid</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> so also the light of the excellent manner of life of
                  perfect men who <pb n="669"/>
                  <pb n="467"/>have employed themselves in works of
                  excellence cannot be concealed. This blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1788">Isaac</persName> therefore was by his
                  birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/67">Dara</placeName>, and he had also a <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3690">wife</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3692">children</persName> and a house, and the
                  office of a <foreign>protector</foreign>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> while he was constantly occupied in fasting and prayer and constant
                  vigil, and in perpetual alms, so that out of the fervour of divine zeal he left
                  house and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3690">wife</persName> and
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3692">children</persName> as it is
                  written<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> for the sake of the hope
                  of the promise of eternal life, and departed, and came to the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/586">royal city</placeName>. And, having entered
                  the ministering office<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> (<foreign xml:lang="grc">διακονία</foreign>) of those who bathe the sick at night, and
                  laboured with them in the labour and service of the house of God, he began to be
                  known and honoured by many. And, being constantly occupied in practices of
                  asceticism and so on, he secretly formed the plan of engaging in another spiritual
                  employment; and so he secretly went out to one of the hospitals (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ξενοδόχας</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> that was a little way from the city and hired himself out in it as a
                  sick-attendant. And he took off all his clothes and sold them and gave to the
                  poor; and he bought some hempen sackcloth and clothed himself in it. And thus he
                  was henceforth a diligent attendant on the sick, since the affair of the sick
                  openly gave him an opportunity and an <pb n="670"/>
                  <pb n="468"/>outlet for his
                  secret manner of life, for his watching and vigilance and the recitation of
                  service by night, he being vigilant and regular and diligent and standing before
                  the sick, and busying himself about ministering to them and relieving them, so
                  that all to whom he ministered blessed him, and continually prayed for him; but
                  the other sick-attendants with the superintendent (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ξενοδοχάριος</foreign>) and all who were with him marvelled and wondered at
                  the diligence and watching and fasting of the vigilant and diligent blessed man
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1788">Isaac</persName>. But his
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3690">wife</persName>, having learned
                  that he had gone to the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/586">royal
                     city</placeName>, herself also too quickly went out after him, and she went
                  about for a long time seeking him, insomuch that she learned from others that he
                  was attending on the sick in such-and-such a hospital (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ξενοδόχας</foreign>). And, when she went and asked about him and he heard
                  about it, he hid himself from her for a long time, while she lay in wait and went
                  up and down to see him, and was quite unable to do so. But at last he sent her a
                  message: <quote>Go away from here, do not lie in wait and go up and down. You
                     cannot see my face now; but go away now and wait, keeping quiet; and at the end
                     of two months you shall come and see me</quote>. Having therefore received his
                  word and put confidence in his truthfulness, knowing indeed that he would <pb n="671"/>
                  <pb n="469"/>not break his word, she withdrew and went away and sat
                  quiet until the end of two months; and after that time, having gone with
                  confidence to see him in the morning, she found that he was dead, and had been
                  laid on a bench (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχαμίον</foreign>), and wrapt in a sheet;
                  and that woman by her wailing and lamentation and weeping declared the truth of
                  the miracle, and the foreknowledge and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> that in the exercise of discretion and humility for God's sake, and not
                  as a man in need, he had submitted to minister to the sick. And so everyone who
                  heard of it was astonished, and a great number of people. hastened to accompany
                  the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1788">Isaac</persName> to the
                  grave; and thus his body was buried with a great procession and much honour,
                  everyone marvelling and wondering at him and serving God. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-45">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-45.1" n="2"> The history of the perfect blessed man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1788">Isaac</persName> is ended. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 466, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ms. om.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 466, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Matth., V, 24.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 467, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>The protectores were a division of the household cavalry (Babut in
               <title>Rev. Hist.</title>, CXIV, p. 225; CXVI, p. 225); but in this case the post
               was appy. honorary.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 467, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Matth., XIX, 29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 467, n. 3</orig>
               </choice> Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">deaconry</hi>, i.e. a house established by the
               church for the care of the sick and poor under the superintendence of the deacons.
               Cf. p. 473 and H.E., II, 13, 15, and see Ducange, s. V. <foreign xml:lang="grc">diconia</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 467, n. 4</orig>
               </choice>
               <foreign xml:lang="grc">ξενοδόχη</foreign> = <foreign xml:lang="grc">ξενοδοχείον</foreign> is not found in Greek writers.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 469, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ms. om.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
