<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/837">Paul of Antioch</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/836"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/838"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/837 -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-46" n="46">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-46">
               <head type="main">Next the Forty-Sixth History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1977">Paul</persName>, Who Was From the City of
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>
               </head>
               <ab xml:id="section-46.1" n="1"> It is therefore no small thing that the memory of the
                  history of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1977">Paul</persName> also the
                  divine man and strenuous worker, who worked in his Lord's vineyard <pb n="672"/>
                  <pb n="470"/>from morning till evening without growing weary, should be
                  omitted from the order of those who have been inserted in this spiritual company.
                  This great and earnest <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1977">Paul</persName> therefore was by his birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>; and he was earnest and fervent in religious zeal from his
                  boyhood, so that from the greatness of his zeal he became stern and harsh, and a
                  rebuker of those who approached religious work sluggishly in any manner; and the
                  object of his zeal was to carry poor and old and sick persons by night, and he
                  would take them and bathe and anoint them, and mend and change the clothes of
                  those who were in need, and take them and give them to drink each one according to
                  what was suited for him, and he would give small coins as was suited for each one
                  of them. And thus before daybreak in company with others who shared his enthusiasm
                  with him he would carry him,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> and
                  would go and lay him in his place (and he used to do this not to men only but also
                  to women) for a long time; so that in consequence of this he by his zeal
                  instigated many persons to share his labour, after teaching everyone from his
                  house and from the produce of his labour to carry in his hand every day and bring
                  for the use of the poor and sick needy persons according to his power, so that
                  accordingly many of them became enthusiastic and used secretly to hasten <pb n="673"/>
                  <pb n="471"/>to this labour. For many even of the great and eminent
                  men of the city, having put off their apparel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) and clothed themselves in poor men's apparel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) and hoods that concealed their heads and faces,
                  would thus put straps on their necks and carry the chairs of the sick and poor,
                  and old men and women, and perform all the ministration to them, while in their
                  earnest zeal they gladly spent money for each man according to his state in life
                  to make provision for them. But <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1977">Paul</persName> the earnest in spiritual things, having instituted and
                  organized this ministration to the poor in his city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>, and seen that it was
                  being carried out by many persons with earnest zeal, withdrew and departed to the
                  other great cities, stirring zeal and enthusiasm in many, and organizing and
                  instituting this ministration in all cities through certain earnest and Christian
                  men who concerned themselves about their lives' salvation, and earnestly
                  endeavoured to gain the inheritance of eternal life. When this strenuous worker
                  had been teaching and rousing enthusiasm, and instituting the work of this
                  ministration to the poor in any one city, and had passed one year or two or more,
                  and saw that his work had been instituted and organized in that city, his zealous
                  plan would next draw him <pb n="674"/>
                  <pb n="472"/>to another city; and so
                  accordingly he acted in this way and instituted the work of this ministration not
                  in eastern cities only,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> but also in
                  many western cities too. When accordingly [....]<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> that he was not able and sufficient himself in person
                  to repair to every city, he used accordingly to send others, and rouse the
                  citizens, and advise and instigate them to take up this work, so that this great
                  and holy work, which is more pleasing to God than all labours, grew and increased,
                  and was instituted in every place and city, through the zealous enthusiasm of the
                  man of God. When he had organized and built up and instituted this ministration in
                  many cities, he in his zeal repaired to the royal city also besides, insomuch that
                  in a short time he succeeded in beginning and gaining distinction and extending it
                  there, and instigating many of the great and eminent men to become
                  fellow-labourers and partners in his ministration, so that consequently his
                  ministration was manifestly extended and increased and magnified, there being no
                  rest or intermission all the night and in the day, so that he relieved and fed and
                  refreshed not only the poor and maimed and sick and lame and blind and old <pb n="675"/>
                  <pb n="473"/>in the royal city, but also in all the suburbs beyond the
                  water in all quarters of the same city besides, and also in all the cities round,
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/622">Chalcedon</placeName> and
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/502">Nicomedia</placeName>, and
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/439">Cyzicus</placeName> and
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2835">Prusias</placeName>
                  <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2790">Heraclea</placeName>, and as far as the
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/503">sea of Pontus</placeName>, while
                  he also bought clothing and brought it out and distributed it and gave it to many
                  from any source from which it fell into his hands, while he also provided relief
                  and refreshment with every kind of bathing for the poor and the strangers who were
                  present. And so this man went on gaining distinction and showing prowess in the
                  Lord's work in the royal city for many years, while not neglecting to send money
                  to other cities round <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2845">Sycae</placeName>
                  <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> also for the
                  expenses of that ministration, which he had planted and instituted in them. And
                  accordingly many emulated his zeal and his earnestness and imitated it, so that
                  other deaconries (<foreign xml:lang="grc">διακονίας</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> were established not for men only
                  but also for women and great and lowly in ardent zeal hastened to minister, and to
                  take part by means of gifts. And so the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1977">Paul</persName> ended the course of his
                  practices in the same royal city, bearing good testimony [....]<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> only <pb n="676"/>
                  <pb n="474"/>of
                  dry bones and skin laid over them outside like wood; and thus his whole body was
                  dried up from the labour and abstinence and watching, his prayer also accompanying
                  his action in all cities in the east and in the west, and especially in the royal
                  city, while many consequently clothed themselves in his zeal and added something
                  to this ministration, until it grew and increased and expanded everywhere, and
                  every day an addition was made to God's glory and the relief of the poor. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-46">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-46.1" n="2"> The history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1977">Paul</persName>, who was from the city of
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>, is ended.
               </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 469, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>See
               II. E., II, 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 470, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sic
               syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 472, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ms.
               om.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 472, n.
                     2</orig>
               </choice>Some words have fallen out.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 473, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ms.
               <hi rend="singleQuotes">fryqy</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 473, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>The
               suburb beyond the Golden Horn, now Galata and Pera; see p. 27 and p. 431. We are
               perh. to understand that he was living in the Syrian monastery.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 473, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>See
               p. 467, n. 3, and H.E., II, 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 473, n.
                     4</orig>
               </choice>Some words have fallen out.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
