<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/838">The Refugees of Constantinople</title>
            <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/837"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/839"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/838 -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-47" n="47">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-47">
               <head type="main">Next the Fourty-Seventh History, Concerning the Holy Comunnities Which
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">Theodora</persName> the Queen
                  Gathered Together in Constantinople, Communities from Every Place in the Royal
                  City Which Were Gathered Together in the Royal Mansion Called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2793">That of Hormisdas</placeName> by the
                  Believing Queen <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">Theodora</persName>
                  Whose Soul Is at Rest.</head>
               <ab xml:id="section-47.1" n="1"> On the subject therefore of the community of blessed men
                  which was <pb type="vol" n="677"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="475"/>gathered together in the royal city by the
                  believing queen at the time of the persecution, out of many peoples and various
                  local tongues, we wish to leave a record at short length; and the history of it is
                  sufficient to cause discerning men to marvel at it, since it was indeed composed
                  of many blessed men who did not fall short of the number of five hundred, and
                  with<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> great and venerable old
                  men; and the congregation of persecuted saints was so widely extended that<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> it shone with many who had under the
                  constraint of the persecution come down from columns and been ejected from places
                  of seclusion, and been expelled from districts, and their congregation was
                  rendered illustrious by great and distinguished heads of convents from all
                  quarters of the east and of the west, and <placeName>Syria</placeName> and
                  <placeName>Armenia</placeName>, <placeName>Cappadocia</placeName> and
                  <placeName>Cilicia</placeName>, <placeName>Isauria</placeName> and
                  <placeName>Lycaonia</placeName>, and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2746">Asia</placeName> and
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> and <placeName>Byzantium</placeName>,
                  countries which beyond others burned with zeal for the faith, while one might
                  consequently go into the palace
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>) itself called that of
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2793">Hormisdas</placeName>, as into a great and marvellous desert of solitaries, and
                  marvel at their numbers, and wonder at their venerable appearance, and the same
                  men's honoured old age, and be affected by the crucifixion of their bodies and
                  their practices of standing and the same men's spiritual songs which were heard
                  <pb type="vol" n="678"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="476"/>from all sides, and at their marvellous canticles and
                  their melancholy voices which were performed and attered in all the chambers and
                  courts (vcrsic) and cells and halls (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τρίχλινος</foreign>)
                  of that palace (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>), and they were ranged
                  in order and full in every place, and they were crowded and packed and their cells
                  were full, as well as every chamber and room in that place; while one might see in
                  each of the great halls (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τρίχλινος</foreign>) that they
                  were filled by rows of planks, for by the care of the queen cells had been made
                  and provided for the old and great and honoured men among them, and some of the
                  stylites and recluses and solitaries, besides all the quantity of cells that were
                  in all the quarters of that palace (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>),
                  and besides the great community which in one chamber had as it were the
                  organization of one convent and one service, and an archimandrite and a steward,
                  and servitors<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/>
                  <!-- eb, There is indeed a footnote here, however, there is not attached footnote on the bottom of the page. -->
                  and a table together, and were continually governed according to the whole perfect
                  organization of a convent; while all the other halls (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τρίχλινος</foreign>) besides, as we have stated above, were full of the
                  blessed men's cells and booths, some of wood and some of curtains, and some of
                  matting and so on, while severe labours and protracted fasts and constant vigils
                  and perpetual prayers, as well as celebrations and descents of <pb type="vol" n="679"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="477"/>the Spirit in every place were being carried on, while altars were
                  fixed up everywhere, so that in consequence not only<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> did the believing people run to the amazing sight, and
                  see and marvel and be astonished and wonder at these spiritual congregations, and
                  run to each one of these saints to be blessed and to be assisted by their prayers,
                  but even some of those who did not belong to their communion would run to that
                  amazing community about which they had heard, and see and marvel and be astonished
                  and dumbfounded and edified, and would give thanks to God, and in consequence a
                  great number of the people of the city like a full river turned aside to these
                  holy communities, and flowed on and overflowed at all times; insomuch that many of
                  the participators with the synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, which was a
                  cause of scandal and of the persecution of the blessed men, when they saw this
                  marvellous community, and learned the causes of the persecution of it, had their
                  mind filled with affliction and contrition, and renounced the
                  <persName>Chalcedonian communion</persName>, and asked for communion with them,
                  and thus many were added to the believers; while the believing queen also would
                  regularly once in every two or three days come down to them to be blessed by them,
                  being amazed at <pb type="vol" n="680"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="478"/>or very carelesly composed, and the
                  emendations are doubtful. their community and their practices, and admiring their
                  honoured old age, and going round among them and making obeisance to them, and
                  being regularly blessed by each one of them, while she provided the expenses
                  required for them liberally in every thing; while the king also, who was ranged
                  against them on account of <placeName>the synod of Chalcedon</placeName>,
                  marvelled at their congregation, and himself also was attached to many of them and
                  trusted them, and was constantly received and blessed by them. And thus this great
                  community became illustrious by a variety of practices all the days of the blessed
                  queen's life, while even after her death<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> she laid an injunction upon the king about it, and it was preserved,
                  and all the lifetime of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName> the king he looked after them and honoured them, and
                  supported the remnant of them, even to the present time which is the year eight
                  hundred and seventy-seven,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> that is
                  the remnant that was left of it to the present time (but it is the same); while
                  our meanness also from the beginning of the collection of this community and
                  before it was completely collected, and even down to this time at which we have in
                  it set down the record that tells of it (since for a considerable time we were
                  with it also in the same royal city at that time) <pb type="vol" n="681"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="479"/>was<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> with it first on account
                  of the persecution, and at the end which is the rest of all this long time, which
                  passes thirty years,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> on account of
                  the conversion from the error of paganism, which as by the dispensation and
                  assistance of God's grace was performed in the districts of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2746">Asia</placeName> by the instrumentality of
                  our meanness, so that eighty thousand were converted and rescued from paganism,
                  and ninety-eight churches and twelve monasteries, and seven other churches
                  transformed from Jewish synagogues were founded in these four provinces (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ύπαρχίας</foreign>),<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/>
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2746">Asia</placeName>, <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2764">Caria</placeName>, <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2833">Phrygia</placeName>, and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2811">Lydia</placeName>. These things we have
                  recorded for the glory of God, and, in case anyone should find fault or be
                  offended on account of the length of our stay in the royal city, by way of
                  explanation.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/>
               </ab>
               <ab xml:id="section-47.2" n="2"> It would not be irrelevant to set down also a record of
                  the loving care of God that was shown to this community from the beginning even to
                  the end. Since, as we said before, a great congregation amounting to thousands in
                  number used to assemble in the presence of the blessed men for the sake of their
                  blessings and their prayers, and to have the privilege of receiving the <pb type="vol" n="682"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="480"/>oblation consecrated hy them in one of the great halls
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τρίχλινος</foreign>), inside which there was also a
                  martyrs' chapel, one day, when a great crowd was assembled and it was filled from
                  end to end, on account of the great weight of the people suddenly at the time of
                  the celebration that chamber broke in and fell, thousands of people going down
                  with it. And, when shrieking and terror and panic suddenly arose, so that the
                  sound of the shrieking was heard a long distance, as far as the great palace
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>), and a sudden report went about
                  <quote>Many thousands of those who do not assent to the synod have been
                     killed</quote>, then indeed the descent of God's mercifulness descended,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> and was made manifest upon these
                  multitudes by the prayers of the saints themselves, so that not one soul among
                  them perished, and there was not a hurt on the body of any of them, although many
                  fell on the top of one another, among them women carrying their children; and thus
                  they all rose from that fall, and it was only from the terror and panic that some
                  of them received a shock. And they came out thanking and praising and blessing God
                  who saved them from death, and all who saw them wondered at this great miracle of
                  deliverance from death which had happened to them; while this story filled the
                  king and <pb type="vol" n="683"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="481"/>queen and the magnates also, and the rest of
                  the people throughout the city with astonishment, and called forth praise and
                  thanksgiving to God, and rendered the community of the blessed men itself
                  honourable in the eyes of everyone, so that at last the king sent, and made the
                  hall (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τρίχλινος</foreign>) itself that fell a portico. And
                  a second miracle which God wrought in the place where this holy community was
                  happened as follows. </ab>
               <ab xml:id="section-47.3" n="3"> After the death of the believing <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">Theodora</persName> the queen, when this
                  community had also lost some of its earlier numbers, the adversaries were stirred
                  up with envy against it, and induced the king to eject them from the former place,
                  and remove them to another place belonging to the crown called the house of
                  Urbicus.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> And, while a few of the
                  holy old men were in these cells, the adversaries introduced some women with their
                  husbands, and others who were not chaste, and filled the place where the blessed
                  men lived, where the sacrament and the service of God used to be performed; and,
                  whereas these men thought to defile the saints' dwelling, God purified it by a
                  sudden fire, in that fire fell and burnt the whole of that place, only <pb type="vol" n="684"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="482"/>a small portion of it escaping, while the fire also caught some
                  of these women themselves and burnt them. And so at last it was given to the
                  martyrs' chapel of the holy Mar <persName>Sergius</persName>, and a monastery was
                  built on that spot; and it remains to the present time to the glory of God, and
                  for the purpose of the confession of his name, and to fulfil that which is
                  written, <quote>The Lord knoweth his own and is known by his own</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/>
               </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-47">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-47.1" n="4"> The history concerning the communities which <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">Theodora</persName> the queen gathered
                  together in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> is ended. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 475, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sic syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 475, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">because</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 476, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>See p. 62, n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 477, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ms. om.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 478, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>28 June, 548.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 478, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>565/6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 479, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ms. om. The sentence is either much confused or very corrupt.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 479, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>This must be reckoned from his first visit in 535; see Introd., p. IV. He
               cannot mean that he was living in the palace of Horomisdas all this time, for we know
               that he lived in the monastery at Sycae, but only that he was one of the Monophysite
               community in CP. See Introd., p. VI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 479, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>See p. 416, n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 479, n. 4</orig>
               </choice>The sentence is ungrammatical.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 480, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sic syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 481, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Rather Urbicius.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 482, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>II Tim., II, 10 (?).</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
