<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/842">Qashish</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/841"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/843"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/842 -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-51" n="51">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-51">
               <head type="main">Next the Fifty-First History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2032">Kashish</persName> Bishop of the Island of
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1529">Chios</placeName>.</head>
               <ab xml:id="section-51.1" n="1"> Since therefore in one of the previous histories also we
                  made mention of the subject of the history of the great blessed man of God our
                  father <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2032">Kashish</persName> the
                  bishop,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> when he was indeed still
                  in the life in the body with us, we did not think it right even after his decease
                  also to withhold the treasure full of spiritual riches of his great modes of life
                  and of his honoured labours. This saint therefore was by birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from a village called that of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2865">ʿAina da Frakha</placeName>
                  <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> which is beyond <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2825">Nirba d Škwš</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> and, while he was still a
                  little boy, he was called by God's grace, and left his kin (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) and his parents, and went out, and entered our
                  holy convent of the house of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John</persName> in the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName> and received instruction there, while we ourselves also
                  besides were in the same convent at an early period of age; and we came to the
                  convent at the same time when about fifteen years old; and thenceforth we were
                  trained together in labour and in the reading of the holy Scriptures in brotherly
                  fashion; insomuch that together we endured and supported thirty <pb n="160"/>
                  <pb n="506"/>years of chasing from one district to another with all our holy
                  fathers and spiritual brothers, and the holy convents throughout the East; so that
                  for such reasons we were led to the western districts on a long peregrination,
                  while that saint did not cease running along the great road of righteousness, nor
                  diminish the labour of his marvellous great practices; but at last he was seized
                  by the keen impulse of the excellent life, so that in love of peregrination and at
                  a distance from acquaintances he extended his own travels to the remote countries
                  of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/715">Egypt</placeName> and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2847">Thebais</placeName> and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2673">Greece</placeName> and the whole of
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2797">Illyricum</placeName>, and even
                  as far as <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/641">Rome</placeName> and the
                  other countries; insomuch that he changed the monastic habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) for lay attire, in order that he might not on
                  account of the habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) be venerated or
                  honoured by any man, but as an ordinary poor man he went about everywhere among
                  poor ordinary needy men; and consequently he suffered blows and distresses in a
                  laborious, distressing, severe, and hard life of peregrination, especially in
                  consequence of the fact that he had determined in himself not to receive charity
                  from anyone and not to reap any enjoyment whatever from the labour of others,
                  except from the work of his hands, for he used to make baskets (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σπυρίδα</foreign>) and pairs of bellows, and handsome tiaras
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">καμελαυκία</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> of various <pb n="161"/>
                  <pb n="507"/>colours, which he
                  had learned in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/715">Egypt</placeName>.
                  Thus wherever he was settled he worked; and he would make things not only for his
                  own special need, but where he could find material for his trade he would also
                  give the rest of his earnings to the strangers and the poor who were at hand. But
                  in the other places where it was impossible to carry on his trade he was in great
                  straits; so that, as he would relate, his sustenance often came from wild herbs,
                  or from the fruit of the trees of the desert. But, when we heard these things from
                  him, we used to marvel and wonder at the fortitude and heroism of the strenuous
                  worker, how great his strength was to bear trials and to endure these grievous and
                  severe mischances. When he had completed about thirteen years in these conflicts
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of peregrination, and in wearisome
                  travelling through the upper countries, he was constrained by love of the
                  brotherhood that was with us to embark upon a ship, and he came and arrived at
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1529">Chios</placeName> an island of
                  the sea from the upper countries; and, when he had received the privilege of
                  worshipping the coffin of the blessed Isidore the great martyr, and had remained
                  there some days, that island pleased him, and he took up his residence in it;
                  since many believers were indeed to be found in it at the time of the persecution,
                  on account of a hospital (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ξενοδόχη</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> which <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">Theodora</persName> the queen had made in
                  it (and she established monks there, <pb n="162"/>
                  <pb n="508"/>and many banished
                  bishops resided in it from time to time), while he had now indeed also reached the
                  feebleness of old age<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> and many
                  diseases, for which reason also especially he was led to seek the rest of
                  quietude. And thenceforth, while he was enjoying the quietude of the residence in
                  that island, he diligently performed the labour of his practices, and he employed
                  himself in his handiwork on a large scale, inasmuch as material (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ύλη</foreign>) was to be found in the date-palm leaves from the
                  Alexandrine ships which touched there.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> While he was performing these tasks in this way, and working and
                  labouring, he used to sell his handiwork; and retaining a small portion for his
                  needs, he would spend all his earnings, and distribute them to the poor and the
                  lame and the maimed and the blind and the sick, so that, when he had completed
                  about five years in the island, while everyone was marvelling at his labour and
                  his practices and his abstinence and his asceticism, then many believers in the
                  place asked him to be their chief and spiritual pastor; so that, when the blessed
                  <persName>James</persName>, whose history has been recorded above, brought two
                  other bishops with him, and crossed to the island from the districts of
                  <placeName>Asia</placeName>, <pb n="163"/>
                  <pb n="509"/>he seized him by force,
                  and ordained him bishop of the believers of the same island,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> while he lamented and fled and refused; and he did not
                  thus escape; but, although he had been a presbyter many years before, he was then
                  forced to shave his hair which he had left in lay fashion (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>); so that, when this became known to everyone, they marvelled
                  at him all the more. Having completed a short time, he crossed to us also in the
                  countries of <placeName>Asia</placeName>, and also laboured earnestly and
                  zealously with us for a considerable time in the work of the ministry of
                  converting men from paganism, while much comfort and consolation was also brought
                  about for us by his devoutness and his venerable old age and the laboriousness of
                  his practices, while we also never again separated from one another in our old
                  age, just as we had not done so in the time of our youth; but, after we had been
                  carrying on the work of the ministry for about one year, that time we came
                  together to the royal city, while the blessed man also ended the work of his
                  ministry in the same island in which he had been summoned to the bishopric, and
                  removed to the quietude of the monastery which by the power of God we had erected
                  by the holy <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2814">Mar Mama</placeName>
                  beyond the water<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> and resided there
                  and rested, and he enjoyed the quiet restfulness of the place. And, when he had in
                  this way been carrying <pb n="164"/>
                  <pb n="510"/>out the labour of his practices
                  unto a space of three years, he ended the course of his practices; and he fell
                  asleep and his holy body was buried and laid in this same monastery; by whose
                  prayers with those of all the saints who pleased the Lord may we all find grace in
                  the day of judgment, and may the monastery which received his coffin, with the
                  other churches and monasteries which he erected in the name of the Lord God of the
                  ages,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> be established to the
                  glory of the Holy Trinity unto the end. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-51">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-51.1" n="2"> The history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2032">Kashish</persName> bishop of the island of
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1529">Chios</placeName> is ended.
               </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 505, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ch.
               39.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 505, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Sc.
               <hi rend="singleQuotes">spring of the temple</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 505, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>Sc.
               <hi rend="singleQuotes">summit</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 506, n.
                     1</orig>
               </choice>
               <foreign xml:lang="grc">κατασκευή σπυρίδος άντί πίλου τή κεφαλή
                  τιθεμένη</foreign> (Cedr., I, p. 297); appy. a kind of straw hat (V.D. and
               L.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 507, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>See
               p. 467, n. 4</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 508, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>J.
               has told us above that K. was above the same age as himself and that they entered the
               monastery when about 15 (522/3; see Introd., p. IV). Now, since K. started on his
               peregrinations with J., who settled in CP. in 540 (see Introd., p. V), this can
               hardly have been later than that year, and he therefore settled in Chios at latest in
               553, when he was about 45 (Dyakonov, p. 81, 82). J. lived over 30 years
               longer.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 508, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>See
               p. 190.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 509, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>See
               p. 504.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 509, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>See
               p. 298, n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 510, n.
                     1</orig>
               </choice>Sc. in Asia; see p. 479. As he was alive when ch. 39 was written, he
               must be presumed to have died in 566 and come to CP. in 563.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
