<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/843">Theophilus and Mary</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/842"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/844"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/843 -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-52" n="52">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-52">
                    <head type="main">Next the Fifty-Second History, of Certain Great and Holy Persons Children of
                  Eminent Men of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>,
                  Who Despised the World and All That Is in It and Lived a Holy Life in It in
                  Poverty of Spirit in an Assumed Garb (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>)</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-52.1" n="1"> It did not seem to be a right thing to withhold this
                  spiritual traffic also <pb n="165"/>
                        <pb n="511"/>besides and the great abundance
                  of massed profits which spring from many persons to all who are desirous of the
                  good traffic that is concerned with their lives and rejoice in the double
                  spiritual profits which will arise from the persons (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>) whose marvellous likenesses we are about though obscurely
                  to trace by means of our contemptible words, by no means stating more than what we
                  received by report and accurately learned from <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3225">God's bondman</persName> who saw and was
                  in close contact with these same holy persons (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>) and learned the rest from them in secret and imparted it
                  to me by repetition, who was a fellow-resident with us for eight years till the
                  end of his life, who for seven years went out in quest of the same persons
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>) of whom he had been deprived and
                  from whom he had been separated. This perfect saint therefore belonged to a
                  distinguished family (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from the city of
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName> in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1452">Mesopotamia</placeName>, wearing the habit
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) of a clergymnn, and his name was
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3225">John</persName>. This man
                  therefore during the whole of the residence with us in the royal city<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> we always saw shedding copious tears
                  and sobbing, so that, when we questioned him closely as to the reason of these <pb n="166"/>
                        <pb n="512"/>things, and especially with adjurations, he would weep
                  bitterly, saying, <quote>What have I to say to you? for I, unhappy man that I am,
                     suffered a spiritual loss, and to-day it is now a space of seven years that I
                     have been going out and going round the peoples and the countries and the
                     cities, and I have not succeeded in finding it, insomuch that it was on this
                     quest that I came to this royal city</quote>. When we questioned him as to that
                  loss, he would tell us the story, weeping and saying, <quote>Lo! in the sight ok
                     God I say, my brethren, that I will not lie to you in telling the astounding
                     story of what I saw and heard in certain perfect persons and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> from them. When I was in the city
                     of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName> nine years
                        ago,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> and was constantly
                     devoting myself to reciting the service and to vigil in the holy church, I used
                     to see a <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2121">young man of handsome
                        appearance</persName> as in the garb (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) of a mime-actor (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μίμος</foreign>),
                     and with him moreover a <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3021">young
                        girl</persName> whose beauty cannot be portrayed and whose appearance was
                     comely and marvellous accompanied him in the garb (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) of a courtezan (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πόρνη</foreign>),
                     and they used to go about the city in that assumed garb (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) in order to deceive the spectators, lest
                     anyone should perceive and know what they were, and they used constantly to
                     perform <pb n="167"/>
                            <pb n="513"/>drolleries (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παιγνίδια</foreign>) and buffooneries, being constantly in the courts of
                     the church like strangers, jesting at the clergymen and everyone, and being
                     boxed on their heads by everyone as mime-actors (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μίμος</foreign>), while at all hours of the day a large number of people
                     surrounded them, chiefly on account of their marvellous appearance, and the
                     comeliness of their faces (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>), joking
                     and playing with them, and giving them slaps (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κόσσους</foreign>) on their heads, but at nights men were not able to find
                     out and learn where they slept, so that many of the froward men, having been by
                     the appearance of the young woman's face (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>) ardently smitten and kindled with the passion of desire
                     for her, while they also made plans to fulfil their desire in the darkness of
                     night and commit fornication with her, wearied themselves and kept awake and
                     watchful and went round all the streets of the city and its corners (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γωνία</foreign>) to find her, and they were not able to do
                     so; so that many of the distinguished men, having been smitten with passion,
                     and being ardently inflamed with desire for her, begged the governor (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ήγεμών</foreign>) of the city to arrest her and set her in
                     the street, which he indeed did immediately, and he sent and seized her to
                     force her to stand in the street, so that when the man dressed like a
                     mime-actor (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μίμος</foreign>) who was with her saw it he
                     wailed <pb n="168"/>
                            <pb n="514"/>with a loud voice, and ran crying <quote>She
                        is my wife, and I do not wish her to stand in the street</quote>. But a
                     great and distinguished devout and God-fearing woman whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3202">Cosmo</persName>
                            <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> on learning it was distressed, and she seut and
                     took her from the governor's (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ήγεμών</foreign>) men and
                     brought her up to her house. And, when she also too saw her marvellous face
                        (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>) and that she was wearing the
                     garb (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) of a courtezan (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πόρνη</foreign>), she continued admonishing her, saying:
                        <quote>Wherefore, my <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3021">daughter</persName>, whose person is like a beautiful pearl, have you
                        fallen into the mire of fornication, and wherefore are you polluting and
                        staining your soul and impairing your beauty?</quote>, so that, when she on
                     her part heard these things, she continued weeping and saying : <quote>Yes,
                        madam, pray for me that God may draw me out of the mire of my
                     sins</quote>.</quote>
                    </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-52.2" n="2">
                        <quote>After these things they went back to their former habits, and that lady did
                     not learn what they were. And, while much was being said about them</quote>
                  (the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3225">John</persName> would
                  say), <quote>and no one succeeded in discovering or learning the resting-place
                     where they slept at nights, I myself as if by the grace of God discovered it by
                     my reasonings, inasmuch as I reasoned <quote>These <pb n="169"/>
                                <pb n="515"/>persons who in garb (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) appear to he
                        mime-actors (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μίμος</foreign>) are in actions
                        spiritual persons</quote>, and from that time I began to observe them, and
                     at evening time I posted myself behind them, keeping close opposite to them,
                     while they, in order that no one should observe them and find them out,
                     continued the whole evening until the whole city was being gathered in going
                     round many streets by a long course, going in by one street and coming out by
                     another, and crossing rough and dark places, so that I also followed after them
                     at a short distance, so that two or three hours of the night<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> were already past, and so, after
                     the city had become still, they directed their course to the line of the wall,
                     and mounted the wall, while I also was stealthily mounting after them. And,
                     keeping myself close to a pinnacle of the wall, I stood up, and I saw that both
                     placed themselves standing with their faces toward the east, and stretched out
                     their arms to heaven prayer in the form of a cross, and after a time they fell
                     upon their faces in prayer, and they stood up and again fell upon their faces
                     in prayer, and they stood up again and fell down and they went through the same
                     form for <pb n="170"/>
                            <pb n="516"/>a long time, and afterwards they sat down to
                     rest, and thus I on my part ran and fell on my face before them, adjuring them
                     by God the All-Ruler not to hide from me the truth as to what and whence they
                     were. And they on their side were alarmed and very greatly annoyed, saying,
                        <quote>Man, who are you and what do you want? And why do you want to prove
                        us here? And what do you want to learn from mime-actors (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μίμος</foreign>)?</quote> And, because I recognised the
                     trouble which their minds felt, as if they had already been laid bare, I gave
                     them a great and terrible oath, <quote>No men shall hear from my mouth about
                        you as long as you are in this city</quote>. Then they were a little
                     appeased, requiring at my hands that I should not be seen speaking with them by
                     day or honour them or greet them, and should not be prevented from slapping
                        (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κοσσίσαι</foreign>) them as mime-actors (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μίμος</foreign>) as they said. And I gave them this promise.
                     Then that man begged that young woman, saying to her, <quote>Now that this our
                        brother has found us out, because perhaps the Lord wished it so, since he
                        himself also has regard to his life together with his sister, for it is
                        twenty-four years that they have been living together, and he is supposed to
                        have taken her to wife, but both have been preserved <pb n="171"/>
                                <pb n="517"/>in the purity and holiness of virginity to the present time,
                        therefore speak with him, and be under no restraint</quote>. But I on
                     hearing these things was the more frightened and alarmed, and I knew that they
                     were in truth great spiritual persons and knowers of secrets. But the blessed
                     woman answered again, saying to him, <quote>Pardon me, my brother. The priority
                        is yours you speak</quote>. But he again enjoined her, saying, <quote>Speak
                        with him, my sister, without contention, and be under no restraint</quote>.
                     And so the bondmaid of Christ began with sighs and affliction to speak to me
                     about the world and about its deceitfulness, and about all its evil things and
                     the destruction of those who go astray in it, and again about its end and
                     dissolution, and about the future judgment, so that I and they spent all the
                     hours of that night in sobbing tears and with the word of life spoken by the
                     same blessed woman, for what proceeded from the mouth of that blessed woman was
                     a matter to cause awe-struck astonishment. Afterwards they dismissed me to go
                     down from that place, saying, <quote>Depart and go down, our brother, for we
                        also are going down while it is dark, lest anyone perceive or recognise
                        us</quote>. And so I begged them to allow me to go up to them by night
                     without <pb n="172"/>
                            <pb n="518"/>restraint; and, having strictly cautioned me,
                     they gave me permission. And so I went down from them, in fear and in great
                     joy, as they too went down to the court of the church, and when day broke they
                     were to be seen acting mimes before everyone. But on the second night I waited
                     for the hour, and went up again to them, and, having cast myself upon my face,
                     I continued entreating them not to conceal from me what they were, and what and
                     of what nature their service was, and what their names were and how the names
                     ran. They on their side say to me, <quote>Do you also give us your word that
                        you will keep truth to us to keep our matter secret, and not cause us
                        distress and give information about us, because we like being in this city
                        which is a city of Christians, and we on our part will thenceforth not hide
                        anything from you</quote>. And on my giving them my word as they required of
                     me they said to me: <quote>Know then first that our names are <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2121">Theophilus</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3021">Maria</persName>, and we are by our
                        birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName> the great, children
                        of men of eminence in the city, and we were both only children of our
                        parents; but how it was that by God's help we came to adopt this garb
                           (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) hear for your edification and
                        for God's glory. When I <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2121">Theophilus</persName> the sinner was a little lad of about fifteen
                        years, I was ordered by my father to take five horses and some slaves, and
                        go out to the village before daylight. And, when I on my side <pb n="173"/>
                                <pb n="519"/>had risen during the night to go down to our stable
                           (<foreign xml:lang="grc">στάβλον</foreign>) in which were many horses to
                        take some and go out as I had been ordered, and when I had arrived at the
                        door, I looked and saw alarming rays of light coming out from the chinks of
                        the door and from the windows; and, having seen it from a distance and been
                        frightened and thought that our stable (<foreign xml:lang="grc">στάβλον</foreign>) was on fire, I cried out. And I ran and looked
                        through the chinks of the door, and I saw a poor man standing on the horses'
                        dung on which he used to sleep with his hands stretched out to heaven, and
                        rays of light proceeding from his mouth and from each of his fingers, and
                        the whole building richly lighted. And, having seen and marvelled, I then
                        said to the slaves with me, <quote>Do (you)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> see that glorious light?</quote> And they
                        said <quote>We have not seen anything</quote>. And I cried to the stablemen
                           (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σταβλάριος</foreign>) to rise and open the door.
                        And, when that poor man heard my voice, he threw himself upon that dung, and
                        had already buried himself, since he was in fact naked, and was clad in rags
                        only, and he had begged the stablemen (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σταβλάριος</foreign>) on account of the severity (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άνάγκη</foreign>) of the cold of winter that he might come
                        in and bury himself in the horses' dung, in order that he might warm himself
                        in it and <pb n="174"/>
                                <pb n="520"/>sleep. But, when he heard our voice,
                        mine and that of the slaves, and threw himself down and drew in his hands,
                        then that great light was obscured, and darkness fell over the whole
                        building. And, the stablemen (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σταβλάριος</foreign>)
                        having run and kindled torch-lights and opened the door, I went in and ran
                        and fell at that poor man's feet trembling and beseeching and adjuring him
                        by God who made heaven and earth and all that is in them to let me know
                        whence he was, and what he was, while he on his side continued repelling me
                        and saying: <quote>Sir, pardon me, for I am a miserable poor man, and on
                           account of the severity (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άνάγκη</foreign>) of the
                           winter I had begged permission to come in at evening time and sleep and
                           warm myself in this dung; and from a poor man of this kind what can you
                           learn?</quote> And when I on my side had thrown myself at his feet and
                        was adjuring him, and they were all amazed at me, while I swore to him
                           <quote>I will not rise from this place and you shall inform me of the
                           truth</quote>, and when I continued to press him greatly and he saw that
                        I would not leave his feet he said to me, <quote>Dismiss your slaves and let
                           them withdraw and I will speak with you</quote>. And, when I had
                        dismissed the slaves and the stablemen (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σταβλάριος</foreign>) telling them to go outside, he began <pb n="175"/>
                                <pb n="521"/>to say, <quote>What, my son, did you see in me that you
                           were so insistent with me? And I said to him, <quote>A vision of rays of
                              fire proceeding from your mouth while you were praying</quote>. He on
                           his side said to me, <quote>It is not my son, who am anything of this
                              kind, but because God wishes for your salvation and wishes to bestow
                              this sight upon you it appeared to you in this way</quote>. But, when
                           I went on continuing to press him with terrible oaths that I would not
                           give any information or disclosure to men about him while he lived, then
                           he began to relate a story to me saying: <quote>Since God wished to
                              choose you, my son, that you may flee from the world and live a life
                              without care, listen. As for me, the sinner and poor man whom you see,
                              my name is <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3247">Procopius</persName>, and I am son of great and distinguished
                              people of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/641">Rome</placeName>. And, when my parents betrothed a wife to me, and
                              wished to hold a marriage-feast for me according to the worldly
                              custom, and when the preparations had been made, I for my part left
                              them and went on board ship, and by the guidance of God I arrived in
                              these eastern countries, having taken into consideration the evils of
                              the world and its distresses and temptations, and now lo! I have been
                              as you see me for no small number of years. And now, my son, hear from
                              me myself the poor man, and know what is in store for you. Lo! you are
                              the only child of your parents, and they betrothed a bride to you who
                              is also the only child of her parents. Know <pb n="176"/>
                                        <pb n="522"/>therefore that during this year the parents of both of you will die,
                              and both the properties (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ούσίας</foreign>)
                              will fall into your hands; and, if you wish to live a religious life
                              and without care and the ruin of sins which much real and personal
                              wealth brings to many, dispose of all your property (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ούσία</foreign>) and sell it and give to the poor
                              and needy, and free all your bondmen, and give them presents to
                              support and provide for them, and similarly dispose of the house and
                              the property (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ούσία</foreign>) also of the
                              young woman who was betrothed to you, since she will acquiesce in your
                              desire in whatever you say to her, and so take her and go out in an
                              assumed garb (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) and in strange
                              countries, hiding the great profit of excellence which you are
                              earning, lest it be snatched from you, that thus you may live the
                              spiritual life</quote>. But I for my part promised to carry out all
                           that he ordered, and I begged him not to deprive me of the sight of him,
                           and abandon me and depart. And the holy blessed man of God <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3247">Procopius</persName> made me a
                           promise, saying, <quote>This know, that, as long as you do not show me
                              the appearance (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>) of any
                              respect, or show that you have any regard for me, and leave me as I
                              am, that I may sleep in this dung, and are not constantly speaking
                              with me or approaching <pb n="177"/>
                                        <pb n="523"/>me before onlookers,
                              you shall see me as long as you observe these things. But, if you
                              practise any of these things toward me, you will not see me again in
                              this life.</quote> And so I used to observe times, and make obeisance
                           to him in secret places or outside the city, and receive consolation from
                           his spiritual admonition, until in the same year the parents of both of
                           us died, and we did everything as that saint ordered, even as my
                           spiritual sister acquiesced in my purpose in everything, since she too
                           received the privilege of the prayer and the sight and the blessing and
                           the admonition of that saint, and we went out in pursuit of the life
                           without care and have so continued to the present time, while neither of
                           us has been besmirched by carnal intercourse, and this has not been
                           revealed to anyone, and no other except you knows our secret, which we
                           think has happened for your profit. And now we ourselves say to you the
                           words of our holy father <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3247">Procopius</persName>, that, as long as you keep faith with us, and do
                           not look upon us before men except in the guise (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) of mime-actors (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μίμος</foreign>), under which we are concealing our traffic, lo! we
                           shall be in this city and you shall see us, but, if you show any other
                           behaviour toward us, know that you have been deprived of the <pb n="178"/>
                                    <pb n="524"/>sight of us in the body</quote>, which indeed
                        happened.</quote>
                        </quote>
                        <!-- The 2nd close quote not in Brooks but required by the sense -->
                  In this way therefore the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3225">John</persName> was repeating all these things in our presence with terrible
                  oaths by God without addition and without diminution, while he wept with sobs and
                  said: <quote>After I had been delighting myself in the conversation of the saints
                     for the period of about one year, and they had been great in my eyes as angels
                     of God, and I had not dared to make use of insult toward them as they desired,
                     they left me and departed from the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, and I never again
                     discovered where they went, and it is to-day seven years that I have been going
                     out seeking them, and have not again been able even to hear news of
                     them</quote>. We ourselves therefore from the descriptions of them and the time
                  of their disappearance which he repeated before us, when we directed our steps to
                  the desert of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/715">Egypt</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> gained the privilege of seeing them,
                  and of passing a night with them<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/>
                  outside the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/200">Thella</placeName>Thella,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> and
                  we enjoyed their holy conversation, while that young woman also said to us <pb n="179"/>
                        <pb n="525"/>three times, <quote>Fear not for the Lord is with you
                     wherever you go</quote>, and thus we departed from one another. </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-52">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-52.1" n="3"> The history of certain great and holy persons children of
                  eminent men of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>,
                  who despised the world and all that is in it and lived a holy life in it in
                  poverty of spirit in an assumed garb (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>), is
                  finished. </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 511, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>From this we should suppose that he did not tell the story till the end of
               his 8 years in CP.; yet from the words put in the narrator's mouth the story appears
               to have been told immediately after the 7 years' peregrinations.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 512, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 512, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>This must have been after the author left Amida (537), and was probably not
               much before 541 (see end of ch.).</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 514, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Dyakonov (p. 370) suggests that this may be the sister of Thomas the hermit
               (p. 197); see Introd.; p. X, n. 4.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 515, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Here again the hours seem to be reckoned from midnight, since the city can
               hardly have been quiet at 8 or 9 PM; see p. 204, n. 1.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 519, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 524, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>He seems to mean that he saw them before the above story was told him and
               from it identified them. His last visit to Egypt was in 541 (Introd., p. V), which
               would make the event fall while he was still in Amida, if he had already heard the
               narrative given 9 yrs. afterwards (p. 512). Moreover the ref. to the time he seems to
               imply that he saw them soon after they left Amida.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 524, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>If this is true, it is strange that he tells their story secondhand, and I
               suspect that the statement is made in order that he may not appear to depart from the
               rule of not relating lives of persons not personally known to him, though he may well
               have seen a couple whom he supposed to be the heroes of the story.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 524, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Constantina.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
