<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/848">Theodore Castrensis</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/847"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/10510"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/848 -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-57" n="57">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-57">
               <head type="main">Next the Fifty-Seventh History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2108">Theodore</persName> the Kings Chamberlain
                  and <foreign>Castrensis</foreign>, Who, While He Was in the Body, Practised A
                  Heavenly and Divine Mode of Life.</head>
               <ab xml:id="section-57.1" n="1"> This blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2108">Theodore</persName> therefore held a high
                  office in the royal palace (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>), having
                  previously been in the service of a great man before God (and he was great among
                  men also) whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2558">Mishael</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> who also
                  was further the king's <foreign>praepositus</foreign>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> a Christian and merciful and ascetic man, and was
                  moreover perfect in all spiritual things, insomuch that he underwent exile
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>) for the sake of the truth of the
                  right faith, that he might not communicate with the <persName>synod of
                     <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>
                  </persName>, insomuch that he spent a
                  considerable number of years in the exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>), and so was at last invited, and came in, and was restored
                  to his place, and completed his time,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> and retired, having lived many years in all religious habits, while like an
                  ordinary <pb n="201"/>
                  <pb n="547"/>man he used to work and labour with his hands
                  at carpentering and building and carving, and sell and give to the poor, besides
                  all the rest of his wealth, while he lived an ordinary and poor life, down to
                  extreme old age, and thus departed from the world bearing great and noble
                  testimony. This man then the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2108">Theodore</persName> imitated with another
                  brother of his whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3224">John</persName>, so that they were both chamberlains of the king, while living
                  in fasting and constant prayers, and sorrow and tears and works of charity, both
                  luring the life of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2558">Mishael</persName> and also after his death for many years. And, because the
                  blessed man was feeble and sickly of body, and the more so from watching and
                  fasting and abstinence, he asked king <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName>, who was also edified
                  by him and loved him and in whose eyes he was honoured, that he might retire as
                  <foreign>castrensis</foreign>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/>
                  in order that he might escape and retire from the turmoil of the palace (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>), and settle down in quietude, and devote
                  himself to the practice of religion only; insomuch that the king assented to his
                  request and carried out his desire, and ordered him to retire as
                  <foreign>castrensis</foreign>, because he,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> serves two years only<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> many offices being subordinate <pb n="202"/>
                  <pb n="548"/>to him,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> and large
                  profits coming in to him, and in two years like the <foreign>praepositus</foreign>
                  he retires, and like him expends<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/>
                  much wealth. The illustrious blessed man therefore retired, and completed two
                  years; and he was released and retired with much gold and great wealth. And then
                  he began eagerly and joyfully to scatter that gold, and to sow all his wealth in
                  good soils which are the hands and bellies of the poor, since he would thenceforth
                  load two of his confidential servants<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> during the night, and himself put on a cape and cover his head, and would go
                  out and distribute it all night with his own hands, not trusting any man, giving
                  the poor not two or three darics only, but sometimes even ten, and sometimes
                  eight, and six and seven, while consequently the poor of the city were not enough
                  for him, but he used also to go out to the suburbs beyond the sea on all sides,
                  crossing and scattering his wealth profusely and without stint; so that in the
                  space of one year he scattered more than fifteen or twenty hundredweights
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κεντηνάριον</foreign>),<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> until he had used up all the gold. And his slaves and
                  all who were attached to him <pb n="203"/>
                  <pb n="549"/>began to murmur and find
                  fault with him, so that they received us and many others with many complaints
                  against him, inasmuch as we had been habitually in his company from the beginning;
                  so that, when we saw that his soul was thus intoxicated with the fervour of divine
                  love, and no worldly property was regarded by him, and while we and everyone were
                  wondering at the disposition and zeal of the man of God, we used to say to him
                  <quote>It is written <quote>First teach them to show charity among those of
                        their household</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/>
                     Beware lest by feeding a large number of people you strip these quite bare and
                     dissipate it on others</quote>. But the blessed man would say, <quote>This is
                        our boast before God, that I and they may be thought worthy to receive the
                        command (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έντολή</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> and then die. These do not know the thing that is
                        helpful. We trust that what is given away will be preserved in the heavenly
                        storehouse in the treasury of God, <quote>where thieves do not break through
                           nor steal</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> For who
                        then (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρα</foreign>) can guarantee me life till the
                        evening? And, if it has happened that the end overtake me and this which has
                        been committed to me remain after me, who will tell me into whose hands it will
                        come? <pb n="204"/>
                        <pb n="550"/>and perhaps those who find it will spend it on
                        harlots, and I shall be called to answer for it.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> And if, sir, you advise me so, I will now do your
                        bidding</quote>. Then he freed his slaves, and gave gifts to them, and to the
                  freeborn who were attached to him, saying, <quote>See, be no longer grudging, and
                     do not murmur</quote>; so that, seeing the man's disposition and zeal, we
                  abstained from going on to address further words to him on these matters. </ab>
               <ab xml:id="section-57.2" n="2"> After therefore he had used up all his gold, he often
                  threw a hundred-weight (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κεντηνάριον</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> upon us also<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> that we might take it and distribute it with him; so
                  that, when we refused to take it, in the fervour of his love he would send it to
                  the regions of <placeName>Asia</placeName> and throw it upon us perforce. And
                  thenceforth he began to sell his silver and his valuable clothes, and give to the
                  poor, with such thoroughness and liberality that eventually nothing was left for
                  him except a few necessaries. And thenceforth he began to live sparingly and those
                  with him, though they were still murmuring against him and finding fault with him.
                  But he said to them several times, <quote>You do not think the things of God but
                     those of men,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> and you concern
                     yourselves about <pb n="205"/>
                     <pb n="551"/>your belly and your purses; and you
                     do not know that we gave away the whole of what was given us by God that he may
                     give us many times as much, and we may not be called to account for it through
                     administering it badly.</quote> But, after he had come to want, and was
                  rejoicing and delighting himself, king <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName> heard of it, and he
                  sent and called for him, and continued upbraiding him for having thus suddenly
                  dissipated his property completely; and he gave him a bounty of a thousand darics
                  every year. But the excellent man out of the very bounty itself used to perform
                  acts of bounty, while he rejoiced and exulted that he had been thought worthy to
                  receive bounty. And so thenceforward he lived in a villa called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2841">Sema</placeName> (?), where <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2558">Mishael</persName> whose soul is at rest
                  was laid, being constantly occupied in fasting and prayer, and much watching, and
                  living a life devoted to all religious habits, and he would not consent to recline
                  upon a couch (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άκούβιτον</foreign>) like a great man, and
                  eat, but used to sit like a poor man, while we and many others were reclining, and
                  begging him to do the same, and he would not comply, saying, <quote>It is
                     prescribed for us to enter by the narrow gate, and that we should not walk in
                     the way that is broad that leads to destruction<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/>
                  </quote>. And thus this man of God began and ended
                  in this brave conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>), while he had now
                  <pb n="206"/>
                  <pb n="552"/>become dried and shrivelled from the labours of
                  asceticism, and the whole of his body had become like dry wood. And thus he ended
                  his life in that same villa, and was laid above the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2558">Mishael</persName>. But his brother
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3224">John</persName>, who also
                  imitated his mode of life, lived a long time after him; and he also ended his
                  course in the practices of religion. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-57">
            <ab xml:id="trailer-57.1" n="3">The history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2108">Theodore</persName> the king's chamberlain
               and <foreign rend="italics">castrensis</foreign> is ended. </ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 546, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>For these words see text, n. 3. For M. see Sev., <title>Select
                  Letters</title>, I, 17; XI, I; <title>C. S. C. O.</title>, t. XXV (1), p. 15; Jo.
               Mal., <title>Exc. de Ins.</title> (ed. De Boor), 92. He may be the deacon of
               <title>Sel. Letters</title>, I, 63; III, 3; but, if so, one would expect J. to say
               that he took orders in his old age. If he is the M. of Jo. Ant., <title>Exc. de
                  Ins.</title> (ed De Boor), 43, he must have lived to most extreme old age.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 546, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Sc. <foreign xml:lang="la">sacri cubiculi.</foreign>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 546, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>See p. 547, l. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 547, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>This is a difficult phrase, which I understand as above. Appy. he wished to
               resign the chamberlainship and become <foreign xml:lang="la">castrensis</foreign>,
               because he could thenr retire altogether after 2 years (see n. 3). The <foreign xml:lang="la">castrensis</foreign> was a kind of purveyor to the court, originally
               the quartermaster of a camp (Pauly-Wissowa, s. V.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 547, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Sc. the <foreign xml:lang="la">castrensis</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 547, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>In <title>Cod. Just.</title>, XIII, XXV, I, this provision is laid down with
               regard to the chief <foreign xml:lang="la">castrensiani</foreign>, but it is hard to
               see how it can have applied to the <foreign xml:lang="la">castrensis</foreign>
               himself, still more to the <foreign xml:lang="la">praepositus</foreign>, a higher
               officer of state.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 548, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sc. the <foreign xml:lang="la">castrensiani</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 548, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>I cannot render in this context otherwise. Appy. the meaning is that large
               sums pass through his hands. V. D. and L.'s translation of all this passage bears no
               relation to the Syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 548, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>The word usually means <hi rend="singleQuotes">eunuchs</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 548, n. 4</orig>
               </choice>20 <foreign xml:lang="grc">κεντηνάρια</foreign> would be about £ 90.000 =
               fr. 2.269,800, an almost incredible sum.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 549, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>I Tim., V, 8 (?).</note>
            <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 549, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Cf. p. 75, l. ult. is perh. an emph. form of . Cf. (p. 285, l. 4, and p.
               620).</note>
            <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 549, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>Matth., VI, 20.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 550, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Cf. p. 285, l. 541, l. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 550, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Circ. £ 4500 = fr. 113.490.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 550, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>An obvious contradiction.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 550, n. 4</orig>
               </choice>Id., XVI, 23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 551, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Id., VII, 13.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
