<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/10510">History of the Monastery of John
                    Urtaya</title>
                <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/848"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/849"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/10510 -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-58" n="58">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-58">
                    <head type="main">Next the Fifty-Eighth History, Concerning the Original Foundation of The
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">Holy Convent</placeName> of the
                  House of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName>John at
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, and Who Were Its
                  Heads and Founders From the Beginning, i.e. From the Year Seven Hundred of
                     <persName>Alexander</persName>, and Down to the Year Eight Hundred And
                  Seventy-Eight of the Same.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>
                    </head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-58.1" n="1"> It did not therefore seem to us to be just and a fitting
                  thing that we should withold the good deposit which was committed to us by old men
                  our holy <pb type="vol" n="207"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="553"/>fathers concerning the original foundation of
                  this our <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">holy convent</placeName> of
                  the house of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName> at
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, and concerning
                  the great old men who were the founders and builders of it from the beginning; but
                  it seemed to us to be right and very proper that through this our narrative we
                  should hand down and transmit to the rest of its inmates the history concerning it
                  even as we received and truly and accurately learned it, as we received and
                  learned through tradition from three seniors advanced in years, who were inmates
                  of it from the time of its great earlier prosperity, that is especially from the
                  great senior Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName>
                  archpresbyter of this same <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, who had been an inmate of it for a long time, who himself
                  also as well received it from ancient seniors of protracted life who were before
                  him, who were inmates in it from its earliest foundation. But this blessed
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName> lived even in
                  our times, and down to the year eight hundred and fifty of
                     <persName>Alexander</persName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/>
                  and he gained distinction also in the conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of persecution; and he fell asleep and finished the course of
                  his great and divine practices in the second exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>) itself in the district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2769">Claudias</placeName>, in the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2795">monastery called that of the
                     Huts</placeName>, while the whole <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> also dwelt in it for about twelve years,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> and built it and set it up and made
                  plantations there. As then we received and <pb type="vol" n="208"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="554"/>learned from
                  these blessed men, that is in the first place from this blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName>, we record the history,
                  which he often related in our presence; which is as follows. Before this
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> was firmly
                  established, there were a few huts on its site, which were called (the informant
                  stated) those of Mar Afwrsm, who himself also gained distinction for a
                  considerable time in the conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of
                  seclusion. Then the blessed Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName>, by whose name the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> was called, came about
                  the year seven hundred,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> and made
                  another hut for himself a little distance from the earlier ones in the same place,
                  and shut himself up in it, who was also thought to be an <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Urtaya</placeName> and so called for some
                  such reason as this. Because (the informant stated) he was a zealous man and an
                     expounder<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> and a teacher, he used
                  to go in and out of the country of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Urtaye</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> warning and teaching and expounding and correcting
                  many, insomuch that he learned the language of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Urtaye</placeName>, so that for such a
                  reason he was thought to be and was called an <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Urtaya</placeName>, though by his birth
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) he was a Syrian. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-58.2" n="2"> While then the blessed man was winning distinction in the
                  labour of seclusion, and gaining renown and reverence from many, two other blessed
                     <pb type="vol" n="209"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="555"/>men came to him, and they also were renowned and
                  famous men, and teachers and firstrate scribes, one of whom was named <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName> and the other <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3227">Jonathan</persName>, who had been living
                  in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1528">the monastery of the
                     Edessenes</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> at
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, who
                     transcribed<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> many books, which by
                  virtue of their wills (<foreign xml:lang="grc">διαθήκας</foreign>) have been
                  handed down in the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> even down to the present day itself. And in consequence of
                  the blessed man's renown and in consequence of his beautiful manner of life the
                  blessed men <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName> and
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3227">Jonathan</persName> begged him
                  that they might be granted the privilege of living with him; and he accepted them,
                  and they took up their abode with him, while they also too with him and in his
                  company received more teaching and instruction in the labours of asceticism and
                  the teaching of religion. When then the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> had begun to advance and
                  progress, so much so that with all its belongings it in a great fashion attained
                  to a large increase in buildings and belongings and increase of the brotherhood up
                  to the number of fifty men, then the blessed Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName> ended the course of his
                  practices, and departed from the world, having left as his successor in the
                  government of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName>. But the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3227">Jonathan</persName> had removed from the
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> during the
                  blessed man's lifetime; and when he had fallen asleep he came back, and <pb type="vol" n="210"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="556"/>lived with the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName>, and they lived together
                  in brotherly and spiritual fashion, until the decease of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName>; so that, when this man
                  had made a great addition to the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, he also as well departed from the world; and over the
                  government of it after him he left the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3227">Jonathan</persName>. And this man again by
                  great knowledge and sound government brought about an increase in all the
                  belongings of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>; and afterwards he also as well departed from the life
                  here; and the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3217">Job</persName> was appointed to succeed him; and this man also governed
                  excellently and lawfully and spiritually all his days, and he departed from the
                  world of distresses to the country of joys; and the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName> was appointed to
                  succeed him at the head of the monastery, who was also a native of the city. This
                  man (the informants stated) had a house in the city, and an old mother, and
                  brothers and a considerable number of kinsmen<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>). And, when
                  he had been governing the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> excellently for a long time, unfounded ill-feeling was
                  stirred up against him (they stated) by certain members of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> who suspected of him
                  that he was secretly providing for his household and making them gifts from the
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>; and, while
                  he for his part defended himself from these charges on every point, they on their
                     <pb type="vol" n="211"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="557"/>side could not abandon such a suspicion, but (the
                  informants stated) by the operation of <persName>Satan</persName> contended the
                  more against him, so that afterwards (they stated) he himself also besides was
                  instigated by the impetuosity of anger, and gave up not only the headship and the
                  government of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, but even residence in it as well, having bound himself by
                  stern oaths not to reside in it longer, nor taste even water that belonged to it
                  as long as he lived. And so he left it, and went into the city and lived there in
                  retreat and devoutness in his house; while after a time (they stated) he used to
                  sigh and distress himself and weep with sobs, because he had been overreached by
                  the evil one and robbed of residence in his <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>; insomuch that at last
                  he would go out and visit it and look into it while they begged him to take food
                  in it, and he would not consent to taste anything whatever from the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>; but at last (they
                  stated) he used to make all the provision for his meals at home, even to cold and
                  hot water and herbs, and so he would bring it out from his house and eat it in the
                  monastery, while he sighed all the days of his life that he had been thus overcome
                  by passion. And his successor was a brave and valiant blessed man, whose own name
                  also was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName>, who
                  from the beginning of his government began to win distinction and show prowess and
                  gain renown on a great and extensive scale, <pb type="vol" n="212"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="558"/>while he
                  also in a short time greatly increased and extended the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, being also formidable
                  and severe and stern toward all the chief men and magnates of the city and of the
                  district; insomuch that his fame penetrated even to the king,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> and he was summoned by an order to
                  the royal city. and went up and was received with great honour, so that in
                  addition to great presents he gave him a village also as well for which he asked
                  in the district of <placeName>Ingilene</placeName> the name of which was
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2824">Narda</placeName>, for which he
                  had asked on account of the usefulness of its wooded heights and so on. But on
                  coming down from the royal city and seeing the spaciousness and magnitude of the
                  heights he cut off half of it and gave it to the monastery of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/358">the village of Zuknin</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> who had asked him for it, since he
                  indeed loved them as his brothers. And he began to raise his own <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> of the blessed Mar
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName> to the number of
                  four hundred men; and this <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> grew and increased in the blessed man's days beyond all
                  the convents round the city. And on account of the perfection of his character and
                  the sublimity of his mode of life great constraint was put upon him, and he was
                  made bishop in the land of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Urtaye</placeName> in the district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Anzetene</placeName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> and, when this happened, both he and all the members
                  of his <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> were
                  smitten with sorrow and distress, and they continued begging and entreating him to
                  appoint a head and governor for them in his <pb type="vol" n="213"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="559"/>place, while
                  he refused to do this, saying to them, <quote>Now that I for my part have been
                     deprived by my sins of residence with you, do you look out, and deliberate
                     among yourselves, and the man whom you know to be suited for you set over you
                     as head, lest eventually you find fault either with me or with someone
                     else</quote>. But they argued the more with him, saying, <quote>We will not
                     allow you, our father, to depart hence until you appoint a head for us in your
                     place</quote>. Again (the informant stated) he on his part answered them,
                  saying, <quote>If you insist that I shall set up a governor for you in my place,
                     think not that I shall make an appointment in the way that you suppose and
                     appoint men who are thinking about themselves; but whoever appears to me to be
                     fitting I will appoint for you. And beware lest in the end he be displeasing to
                     you and you murmur</quote>. And, as they again continued to press him in this
                  way, he gave orders and the bell sounded, and they all stood up for service. And,
                  having spoken at great length and given warning and instruction in his clear
                  speech, he gave orders and the archimandrite's hood and wand were brought, and
                  laid before the altar. Then (the informants stated) the blessed man turned and
                  looked behind him at the lines of the companies, and passed down the middle and
                  laid his hand on a certain old man who held a low place among the members of the
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, <pb type="vol" n="214"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="560"/>and drew him out, dragging him by force, and brought him before
                  the altar (whose name also was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName>), while he objected and wept and refused. And he on his
                  side made a prayer and took him and clad him in the hood of the archimandriteship,
                  and put the staff of the pastorate of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> in his hand, even as he
                  came from the occupation of shepherd of a flock, and from a village called Thella
                  d Mikhana,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> and all his life and
                  even after his death, and even to the present time in the same <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> he was called <quote>Mar
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName> the
                     shepherd</quote>. But the old man continued saying with sobs and with much
                  weeping, <quote>How is it, sir, that you appoint me a plain man (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ίδιώτης</foreign>) and a shepherd to govern such a <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> as this?</quote> But
                  the blessed man answered him, saying, <quote>Remember our Lord's saying to Peter
                     when he says, <quote>Henceforth thou shalt catch men to life</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> even as you now after being
                     shepherd of a dumb flock of animals shall carry out the duties of shepherd of a
                     rational flock of men</quote>. But those who were in high and prominent place,
                  and thought of themselves that<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> they
                  were wise and learned and teachers, and of whom each one was confident concerning
                  himself that it would be he who would be raised by force to the governorship, when
                  they saw that he had appointed an old man and a shepherd who held <pb type="vol" n="215"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="561"/>a low place to the governorship, showed displeasure and indignation
                  and found fault and began to murmur. And, when the blessed man saw it, he said to
                  them: <quote>You know, my sons, that for my part I at first committed the matter
                     to your discretion. But, now that you threw the burden upon me, I on my side
                     thought this old man fitter than all of you to administer the affairs of this
                        <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, while I
                     know also what I have done and whom I have appointed, a man whom I have seen
                     for a long time, and, while I observe all of you, and see that each concerns
                     himself only with himself and his gratification, see that this man is vigilant
                     and energetic and earnest, and eager to promote the interests of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>. And for all these
                     reasons it is to him that I have entrusted and am entrusting my place. And he
                     who obeys him, and receives and pleases him receives and pleases me; and he who
                     strives with him and opposes him is superfluous in this <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>
                        </quote>. When these
                  things had been carried out in this way, and the blessed bishop had given his
                  blessing and prayed and gone to the district to which he had been summoned, then
                  many stood forth in envy and bitter strife against the same blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName> saying, <quote>He set
                     as head over us a man who is a peasant and a shepherd holding a low
                     place</quote>. And so they made one company (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κοινήν</foreign>), and rose up in strife, and separated themselves; and sixty
                  men <pb type="vol" n="216"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="562"/>left the monastery in one body for such a reason as
                  this. And they went and occupied a site and built a monastery for themselves and a
                  well-known martyrs' chapel which exists even to the present time, in the
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2751">village called that of Beth Bar
                     ʿrubtha</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> But the
                  blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName> was
                  strengthened, and began to act with vigour and show firmness, and to display
                  proper energy in all the government of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, and great carefulness
                  for all its belongings, and for the canons and regulations and all the spiritual
                  ordinances in it, while he also began to walk in every point in the footsteps of
                  the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName> the
                  great his predecessor, in speech and in wisdom, and sound knowledge, and orderly
                  and honourable conduct, insomuch that he also as well gained great renown over the
                  whole <placeName>East</placeName>. But after a time came the blessed Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName> also besides who also
                  founded the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>
                  called after his name,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> having first
                  set up a standing-post for himself, and taken up his position on it. And, when he
                  began to build the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName> used to give him much
                  assistance, since, after the city-gates were shut, he would take a party of forty
                  and fifty men, and they would go and work with them, and give assistance all the
                  night, and thus they would return to the monastery in the morning; because (the
                  informant stated) <pb type="vol" n="217"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="563"/>when they were shepherds also they
                  used to feed the flocks together, so that (the informant stated) jesting with one
                  another they would say, <quote>Woe to us if God requires from us the stolen sheep
                     that we have eaten</quote>. And so (it was stated) the two heroic old men
                  distinguished themselves by great modes of life, together with all the other
                  convents their brethren. In the days of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName> the shepherd therefore
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2286">Kawad</persName> king of the
                     <persName>Persian</persName>s came against the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName> in the year eight hundred
                  and thirteen;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/> and he took it<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/> and carried off captives from it,
                  while he also razed the monastery too to the ground, and piled its wood and its
                  stones and its clay on to the <quote>mule</quote>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/> which he had set up against the city. The story of
                  these events was related to us<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a21" target="#n21" n="21"/> by
                  an old man with venerable white hair whom<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a22" target="#n22" n="22"/> once when we had set out to go into the desert of
                     <placeName>Egypt</placeName> we found in the country of Palestine beyond
                     <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> in a monastery called that of Mar
                     <persName>Thomas</persName> at Beth <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1508">Gubrin</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a23" target="#n23" n="23"/> so that, when we had first zealously directed our
                  course to the <placeName>city of Alexandria</placeName>, and had arrived at this
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a24" target="#n24" n="24"/> we found that venerable old man
                  sitting, though he was unable to <pb type="vol" n="218"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="564"/>see from age. But, when
                  we approached him to make obeisance to him and receive his blessing, he asked us
                  saying, <quote>Whence are you, my sons?</quote> And we on our side answered him,
                  saying, <quote>We are, sir, from the district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>
                        </quote>. When he on his
                  side heard the name of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, he was struck dumb and shed copious tears with sobs. And,
                  when that old man had been violently weeping and sobbing for a long time, he said
                  : <quote>If I ask you, my sons, do you know anything in the territory of
                        <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>?</quote>, and
                  we answered him, <quote>Be so good as to ask, sir; and what we know we will
                     say</quote>. But the old man asked us about this our own <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, saying, <quote>Is there
                     a monastery called that of the house of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName> on the north of the
                     city by the side of the wall and has it been built?</quote> And we said to him
                     <quote>Yes, sir. It has been built and it exists, and it is in fact from it
                     that we come</quote>. When the blessed man heard this, he yearned the more
                  toward us, while he also betook himself to showing emotion by weeping with many
                  sobs, saying, <quote>I, my sons, was an inmate of that monastery, from the days of
                     Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName> the great
                     who became a bishop, when I was a boy, when the numbers also amounted to four
                     hundred men. And, when <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2286">Kawad</persName> came to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, we fled and we all went inside and took up our abode in
                     the school (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχολή</foreign>) called <pb type="vol" n="219"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="565"/>that of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Urtaye</placeName> within the wall, about three hundred men, the rest
                     having been scattered and fled. And, when the city was taken and the
                        <persName>Persians</persName> came in and began to slaughter, we all stood
                     up sorrowing and weeping for the service of our death and of our lives' end,
                     slaughter being now set before our eyes. And, when the <persName>Persian
                        soldiers</persName> arrived, and they came in and saw long rows of men
                     standing, they began a fearful slaughter among us. And, having beheaded ninety
                     of us in one massacre while our eyes beheld it, they then ceased slaughtering;
                     and they took us and carried us away as captives, while they also made spoil of
                     all the belongings of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>. But, when the city was thrown open, God delivered us
                     and strengthened us and many of us escaped. And from that time I fled from all
                     that country; and I made a vow to God not to see it again</quote>. And so that
                  old man was piteously relating all these things to us with great emotion and many
                  tears; so that for a long time he was unable<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a25" target="#n25" n="25"/> on account of his sobs to relate them before us. And
                  again another old man of many days (and he too had venerable white hairs), who
                  during the same times of the prosperity of this <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> had been in his boyhood
                  an inmate in it, <pb type="vol" n="220"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="566"/>who was in the renowned <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1528">monastery of the Orientals at
                     Edessa</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a26" target="#n26" n="26"/> who was
                  called <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3239">Paul</persName> of
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/724">Arzen</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a27" target="#n27" n="27"/> who also departed from the world a
                  few years before during the persecution of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, used all his days in
                  the presence of many persons to tell about the prosperity of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a28" target="#n28" n="28"/> saying: <quote>Before the deportation by <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2286">Kawad</persName> we numbered four
                     hundred men in it; and so prosperous and extensive was the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> of the blessed Mar
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName>, that, since
                     their space was too much confined for the purposes of occupation by the same
                        <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, they
                     formed the plan of building for themselves a large house for a chapel. And so
                     the masons of the city applied themselves to hewing out metopes (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μέτωπα</foreign>); so that, when the blessed men wished to
                     convey them to the monastery after the gate (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πόρτα</foreign>) of the city was shut at dusk, they used to go out and
                     fetch them in one line from the monastery right up to the quarries (<foreign xml:lang="grc">λαοτομία</foreign>) themselves; and thus they would hand on
                     the stones and pass them from one to another, and they are passed down their
                     lines till they enter the precincts and are piled upon the building, and thus
                     that extensive building was built, though it was not completed on account of
                     the deportation by the <persName>Persians</persName> and the scattering of the
                     brotherhood; so that, since a heap (?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a29" target="#n29" n="29"/> remained after the <persName>Persians</persName>, a large <pb type="vol" n="221"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="567"/>portion of the monastery was quarried and built from
                     it; and the whole of the martyrs' chapel dedicated to <persName>Kyra
                        Maria</persName> was also built from it, and further much was also quarried
                     and brought in from it for the church and the city.</quote>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a30" target="#n30" n="30"/> And its kiln is still standing. But
                  this <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> was rebuilt
                  on a smaller scale, both in buildings and in the number of the brotherhood. But
                  the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName>, who
                  was also called <quote>the shepherd</quote>, ended the course of his practices,
                  and <quote>died in a good old age</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a31" target="#n31" n="31"/> And to succeed him in the government of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3200">Cosmas</persName> was appointed, who also
                  showed himself an excellent governor and head; and he governed during his days in
                  tranquillity and quiet, having lived the whole of the time of the reign of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2265">Anastasius</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a32" target="#n32" n="32"/>; and so he fell asleep in his
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> in peace<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a33" target="#n33" n="33"/> And to succeed him in the headship
                  and government of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3255">Sergius</persName> was appointed, who by his birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) came from the village of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2780">Gadara</placeName> which was in the north;
                  who in the first persecution that arose against the church<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a34" target="#n34" n="34"/> was the first to go out in banishment with all the
                  rest of the convents, and gained distinction in the conflicts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of persecution, <pb type="vol" n="222"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="568"/>and in
                  all the labours of monasticism, as well as in excellent government all the time of
                  his life. And he ended his course during the same persecution; and he died and was
                  buried in the monastery called that of Mar <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2813">Mama</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a35" target="#n35" n="35"/> But to succeed him a great blessed senior was
                  appointed whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3263">Symy</persName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a36" target="#n36" n="36"/>; who by his
                  birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) was a native of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/724">Arzen</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a37" target="#n37" n="37"/> who with his two predecessors <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3255">Sergius</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3200">Cosmas</persName> were<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a38" target="#n38" n="38"/> in our days, since we indeed in the
                  days of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3255">Sergius</persName> and the others who succeeded him received the privilege of
                  residing in the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>.
                  When then after the decease of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3255">Sergius</persName> they were urging the
                  blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3263">Symy</persName> to take up
                  the government, he continued objecting and refusing, saying, <quote>Allow me, my
                     brothers, to repent and make entreaty on account of my sins, because I have not
                     one day beyond three years and a half in the body</quote>. And, since not even
                  after his prophecy also (which was shown to be exact truth) did he escape, but
                  they constrained him and he took his place at the head with earnestness as it is
                     written<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a39" target="#n39" n="39"/> excellently and like a
                  teacher, expounding and admonishing day and night with service and with vigil,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a40" target="#n40" n="40"/> he would also at all times <pb type="vol" n="223"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="569"/>adjure and warn everyone to bestow care and earnestness
                  upon finding spiritual life, and many were in fact enlightened by his teaching,
                  and by his admonition were brought to open their hearts and to sorrow and tears,
                  wondering and giving thanks to God. But his prayer and the gift of revelations and
                  of prophecy was of such a kind that not only did he gain knowledge of his
                  departure beforehand and prophesy it, but even concerning many other things also,
                  insomuch that at the beginning he spoke and uttered many prophecies to our own
                  mean self also, of which we truthfully assert that none has fallen to the ground
                  or fallen short of the pronouncement uttered by him even down to this very day;
                  which we refrain from recording, lest we be thought to be desirous of displaying
                  great things about ourself. When therefore this man had completed the time which
                  he decreed for himself, some days before<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a41" target="#n41" n="41"/> he called and blessed and commanded and warned everyone, and so
                  according to the decree which he laid down he ended his course during the same
                  persecution in the country of the <placeName>East</placeName> in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2834">the monastery called that of the
                     Poplars</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a42" target="#n42" n="42"/> in which
                  also the whole community was residing. But after five years, when the recall from
                  banishment came, we ourselves were privileged to carry and convey his holy bones
                  into the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>
                        <pb type="vol" n="224"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="570"/>of the house of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName> itself.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a43" target="#n43" n="43"/> And to succeed him there was
                  appointed our blessed master and teacher from our boyhood, whose name was
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3183">Abba</persName>; who also was by
                  his birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from the district of
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/724">Arzen</placeName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a44" target="#n44" n="44"/> and he was reverend and imposing in
                  his speech and in his appearance. But after four years of his government occurred
                  the entry into the city-convents themselves at the beginning of the reign of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName> the king.
                  And, when we had completed about seven years and a half<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a45" target="#n45" n="45"/> in the convents themselves, the envy of those who
                  ruled the churches was aroused, and the persecution was renewed over the whole of
                  the <placeName>East</placeName>, through the descent of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2274">Ephraim</persName> patriarch of the city
                  of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2610">Antioch</placeName> to the
                     <placeName>East</placeName>; and all the convents were again expelled, and they
                  went together to the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2834">monastery</placeName> which they had previously built and took up their abode
                  in it, which was called that of the Poplars. And after a little time they were
                  expelled thence, and the convents were divided; and the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3183">Abba</persName> with all his <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> went away, and they went
                  into the steep towering mountains of the village called ʾbdhyr;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a46" target="#n46" n="46"/> and we took up our abode there in a
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2826">monastery called that of the
                     Nut</placeName>. And after three years<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a47" target="#n47" n="47"/> we left and went into the district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2769">Claudias</placeName>, and took up our abode
                  in the <pb type="vol" n="225"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="571"/>monastery of the Huts,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a48" target="#n48" n="48"/> which we also mentioned above in our history. And the
                  blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3183">Abba</persName>, having
                  been arrested and maltreated by the <persName>Synodites</persName>, fled and went
                  up to the royal city; and, when he had passed some time there with the concourse
                  of believers that had been gathered from every quarter by the believing queen
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">Theodora</persName>, and had a
                  great reception from her, and had been there five years, then it was his pleasure
                  to return to his <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, while the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> was still in the district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2769">Claudias</placeName>, and he ended his
                  course there <quote>in a good old age</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a49" target="#n49" n="49"/> so that, when after a space of three years we
                  ourselves too went down from the royal city, we took his holy bones also as well
                  and sent them to the city-convent itself.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a50" target="#n50" n="50"/> And to succeed him in the government of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName> was appointed, who by
                  his birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) was from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Anzetene</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a51" target="#n51" n="51"/> and was a great and earnest administrator in all the
                  spiritual and bodily affairs by which a <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> is maintained. And, when
                  this man had completed some years, he also as well fell asleep and was laid in the
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, since he had
                  gone for the purpose of visiting it, and fell asleep and was buried in his
                  monastery, as he desired and prayed.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a52" target="#n52" n="52"/> After him was appointed the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3255">Sergius</persName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, who comes of a
                  distinguished family from the city itself, called the <pb type="vol" n="226"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="572"/>house of Bar <persName>Deba</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a53" target="#n53" n="53"/> This man was placed by his parents in the same <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> from his childhood, and
                  he was brought up in it from the days of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3200">Cosmas</persName> the archimandrite, and
                  he gained distinction also in all the conflicts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of persecution from the beginning down to the present year,
                  which is the year eight hundred and seventy-seven, the year in which <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName> departed from the
                     world,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a54" target="#n54" n="54"/> having first been
                  buffeted in every place with all the old men his fathers who had lived since the
                  beginning of the persecution while he endured and remained firm. But at last, when
                  he was appointed to the headship of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, he increased in
                  strength and prowess and firmness, while he was more frequently driven from
                  district to district and from place to place, uttering thanks and praise at all
                  times; a man who, having been at first luxurious and delicate and smart as being a
                  citizen, and at last come to himself,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a55" target="#n55" n="55"/> and been smitten with remorse and brought himself into a religious frame of
                  mind, turned his face away from all visible things, and came to despise clean
                  clothes and delicious foods and unguents and so on, and clothed and covered<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a56" target="#n56" n="56"/> himself with garments of hair, and
                  embraced asceticism and abstinence, and fasting and services and protracted
                  prayers by day and night, and what is more admirable than all, the practice of
                  observing the divine commandments, having stored up in his mind the <pb type="vol" n="227"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="573"/>words of our Saviour who says, <quote>He who loveth me keepeth
                     my word</quote>, and again <quote>Let your speech be <quote>Yea, yea</quote>
                     and <quote>Nay, nay</quote>.</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a57" target="#n57" n="57"/> and so decided it for himself that an oath should never proceed from
                  his mouth. And he persevered and kept and maintained his resolution even down to
                  the present time also, since he is actually in the body even down to the present
                  time also during the persecution of his <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, as well as of all his
                  brethren the other <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> in the district of <placeName>Izla</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a58" target="#n58" n="58"/> in the same persecution, down to the
                  present time which is the year eight hundred and seventy-nine,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a59" target="#n59" n="59"/> from the year eight hundred and
                     thirty-two,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a60" target="#n60" n="60"/> which makes
                  forty-seven years from the beginning of the persecution of the same down to the
                  year stated above. </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-58">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-58.1" n="1"> The history of the original foundation of the holy
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> of the house
                  of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName> at
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, and who were its
                  heads and founders from the beginning is finished. </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 552, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>389-567.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 553, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>539.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 553, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>539-51; see p. 570 and note.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 554, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>389.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 554, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">interpreter</hi>, <hi rend="singleQuotes">linguist</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 554, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>I. e., Anzetene or part of it; see p 135, n. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 555, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 221 and p. 391.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 555, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">wrote</hi>; but the little <hi rend="singleQuotes">scribes</hi> points to the other meaning.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 556, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">distinguished kin</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 558, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Probably Zeno.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 558, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 37.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 558, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Syr. <hi rend="singleQuotes">Hanzit</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 560, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. <hi rend="singleQuotes">hill of the (irrigation) engine (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μηχανή</foreign>)</hi>. Cf. Oxyrthyncus Papyri, n'1831, 13;
               n'1913, 1. 'Zach. Rh.' (VII, 4) calls him <hi rend="singleQuotes">a Persian</hi>,
               i.e., a narrative of Persian territory.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 560, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Luke, V, 10.</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 560, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 562, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. <hi rend="singleQuotes">son of Friday</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 562, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>'Zach Rn.', VIII, 5. He is probably the S. of <hi rend="singleQuotes">Zach.</hi>, VII, 6, though his arrival is there placed after the Persian siege.
               His monastery is mentioned in ch. 39.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 563, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>501/2. It was really in 814 (502/3); see <hi rend="singleQuotes">Josh.
                  Styl.</hi>, XLIX, l.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 563, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>
                    <hi rend="singleQuotes">Zach. Rh.</hi> (VII, 4) says that it was taken
               through the drunkenness and carelessness of the monks of this monastery, and by the
               remark that the archimandrite was a Persian he seems to suggest treachery. Cf. <hi rend="singleQuotes">Josh.</hi>, LIII.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 563, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>A mound on which the besiegers stood in order to be level with the top of
               the wall. See <hi rend="singleQuotes">Zach.</hi>, VII, 3, and <hi rend="singleQuotes">Josh.</hi>, LIX.</note>
                <note xml:id="n21" target="#a21" n="21">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 563, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n22" target="#a22" n="22">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 563, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>Eleutheropolis, Arab. Bait Gibrin.</note>
                <note xml:id="n23" target="#a23" n="23">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 563, n. 6</orig>
                    </choice>I understand this to mean that he visited his convent on his return, but the
               sentence is very ambiguous. Since he came from Amida, his 1st visit in 534 is
               intended.</note>
                <note xml:id="n24" target="#a24" n="24">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 565, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. <hi rend="singleQuotes">able</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n25" target="#a25" n="25">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 566, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Cf. Land, p. 291.</note>
                <note xml:id="n26" target="#a26" n="26">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 566, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Arzanene, otherwise called Arzun (p. 145). This was in Persian
               territory.</note>
                <note xml:id="n27" target="#a27" n="27">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 566, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>521-30; see Introd., p. IV.</note>
                <note xml:id="n28" target="#a28" n="28">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 566, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Lit. <hi rend="singleQuotes">mountain</hi>, perh., a heap of debris like the
               Mons Testaceus at Rome.</note>
                <note xml:id="n29" target="#a29" n="29">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 567, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>It is not clear where Paul's words ends. The statement about the kiln is
               clearly J.'s, and perh. the whole story of the completion of the rebuilding is his,
               for P. probably left Amida at the time of the siege. Perh. J. with his usual
               carelessness has forgotten that he is reporting P.'s words.</note>
                <note xml:id="n30" target="#a30" n="30">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 567, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>I Chr., XXIX, 28.</note>
                <note xml:id="n31" target="#a31" n="31">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 567, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>491-518. He cannot have become archimandrite before 504, and the meaning can
               therefore only be that he survived Anastius.</note>
                <note xml:id="n32" target="#a32" n="32">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 567, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>
                    <hi rend="singleQuotes">Zach. Rh.</hi> (VIII, 5) erroneously names C. among
               the banished archimandrites.</note>
                <note xml:id="n33" target="#a33" n="33">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 567, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>521; see Introd., p. IV.</note>
                <note xml:id="n34" target="#a34" n="34">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 568, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om. The chronology in this ch. and ch. 35 makes it clear that the
               monastery of Mama is intended.</note>
                <note xml:id="n35" target="#a35" n="35">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 568, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Cf. <hi rend="singleQuotes">Zach. Rh.</hi>, VIII, 5, where he is placed
               among the banished archimandrites, while Sergius is omitted.</note>
                <note xml:id="n36" target="#a36" n="36">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 568, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 566, n. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n37" target="#a37" n="37">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 568, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n38" target="#a38" n="38">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 568, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>I do not know the source of the ref.</note>
                <note xml:id="n39" target="#a39" n="39">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 568, n. 6</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. <hi rend="singleQuotes">after it</hi> (meaninglessly), and in marg. in
               later hand <hi rend="singleQuotes">Abraham</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n40" target="#a40" n="40">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 569, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n41" target="#a41" n="41">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 569, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 417.</note>
                <note xml:id="n42" target="#a42" n="42">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 570, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Since we are told below that the return to Amida happened after 4 years of
               Abba's rule, the transition of the bones cannot have been conetmporaneous with it.
               The restoration having been in 530 (see Introd., p. IV), we get 522/3-526/7 as the
               date of Symy's archimandriteship.</note>
                <note xml:id="n43" target="#a43" n="43">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 570, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 566, n. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n44" target="#a44" n="44">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 570, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Since the descent of Ephraim was at the end of 536 or beginning of 537, the
               time cannot have exceeded 5 1/2 years (Dyakanov, p. 30, n. 166); see p. 418, n.
               1.</note>
                <note xml:id="n45" target="#a45" n="45">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 570, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 232.</note>
                <note xml:id="n46" target="#a46" n="46">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 570, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>Since Samuel died in the monastery of the Huts in 539 (p. 553), the date
               must be 539, not 540, 3 yrs. after the expulsion from Amida.</note>
                <note xml:id="n47" target="#a47" n="47">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 571, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 553.</note>
                <note xml:id="n48" target="#a48" n="48">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 571, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>I Chr., XXIX, 28.</note>
                <note xml:id="n49" target="#a49" n="49">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 571, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. at Amida. The date is probably 548.</note>
                <note xml:id="n50" target="#a50" n="50">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 571, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Syr <hi rend="singleQuotes">Hanzit</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n51" target="#a51" n="51">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 571, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>J. omits to state that the monks for a short time returned to Amida (p.
               420).</note>
                <note xml:id="n52" target="#a52" n="52">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 572, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. <hi rend="singleQuotes">son of a wolf</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n53" target="#a53" n="53">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 572, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>565/6.</note>
                <note xml:id="n54" target="#a54" n="54">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 572, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Luke, XV, 17; cf. p. 171.</note>
                <note xml:id="n55" target="#a55" n="55">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 572, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 319, n. 2; p. 489, n. 3.</note>
                <note xml:id="n56" target="#a56" n="56">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 573, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>John, XIV, 23; Matth., V, 37.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
