<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/792">Fathers</title>
            <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): 
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <note type="license">
                        used under a Creative Commons Attribution license 
                        <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/793"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks. Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-0" n="0">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-0">
               <ab xml:id="section-0.1" n="1">
                  When we considered the words of our Saviour and Redeemer <persName>Jesus</persName> in
                  his preaching to his saints which he said, <quote>Let your light so shine before
                     men, that they may see your good deeds, and glorify your Father who is in
                     heaven</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> it seemed to us that this is not disagreeable to his will, that
                  the light of the deeds and of the triumphs of <persName>his holy disciples</persName> should at all
                  times arise and be made known and appear among men, as indeed the
                  sense of his holy saying declares; and for this reason, although we may
                  seen to be presuming to set foot in things that are too great for us, by the
                  power of his saying and the hope of his gift we have been encouraged to
                  approach the task of compiling histories concerning their ways of life and
                  their brave triumphs and the characters of their good deeds, that, we
                  may draw, though obscurely, by means the vile and common pigments of
                  <pb type="vol" n="2"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="2"/>our poor words, the pattern of their likenesses for posterity, [and] leave it
                  in the memorial of our writings; so that, when they read and see their good
                  deeds and marvellous ways of life, by this means we opine that two beneficial 
                  results will be produced, one that when they see their good deeds
                  they may also glorify their Father who is in heaven as it is written, and the
                  second again, that, when the light of the narratives of their ways of life
                  shines upon souls entangled in the vanities of this world and darkened by
                  error, they may be enlightened by the light of their triumphs and be eager
                  to imitate them, and to receive their patterns in themselves, in order that
                  they may attain to their crowns, and hear with them the life-fraught call that
                  says <quote>Come enter, ye blessed of my Fathers</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> 
                  For these reasons therefore,
                  since I dreaded even to hear the apostolic saying that condemns the man
                  who knows what is good and does it not by the sentence of 
                  sin,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> I determined 
                  not to conceal and cover with silence the great and marvellous virtues
                  that I have seen and known and clearly learned in heroic and divine persons,
                  and I am confident of bearing true witness without fear and without hesitation; 
                  having first formed this resolution in my mind, that, though I hear
                  <pb type="vol" n="3"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="3"/>that a few days ago and now also there have been and indeed are in the
                  districts round us heroic and brave men, for my rart except those of whom
                  I have been an eye-witness in every one of their actions for a long time and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/>
                  a witness of the truth of them I will in no case commit any the of to the
                  memorial of my handwriting,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> actions to the truth of which besides myself
                  all the other men of our time are also witnesses, actions that were wrought
                  in those men heroic in their ways of life, with every one of whom I was in
                  intercourse from my childhood down to their own end; of whom some fell
                  asleep some time ago, and some during this time, and some are still illustrious 
                  in the body, men who have power to perform apostolic signs, since
                  to each one of them according to the blessed apostle's saying gifts are 
                  distributed and given,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> to this miracles, to that great ways of life without
                  signs, to another beauty of heart and purity, to another ready sorrow and
                  copious tears, to another self-denial and perfect pilgrim life, in addition
                  to the other distributions of gifts, consisting in the beauties that each
                  one of them severally used to depict upon his person. These marvel<pb type="vol" n="4"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="4"/>lous and 
                  divine beauties therefore I have set myself to bring to the
                  record of narratives, while the spiritual beauties and great triumphs 
                  themselves, without the interposition of elegant language, are related by their
                  natural simplicity of heart with which as is written they glorified God,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/>
                  and we record the active manifestation of the ways of life of every one of
                  them without ornate diction and artificial combinations of words, rejecting
                  and dismissing all worldly elegance outside the circle of these admirable
                  and divine beauties, lest by it we soil their holy images; which have no
                  need whatever of beauty and adornment lying outside their circle, as neither
                  has the Giver of their beauties himself, since indeed they are not lacking
                  in anything, which also enrich and enlighten others by their beauties. We
                  begin therefore from this point to draw the picture of each one of <persName>these
                     saints</persName> by relating his history through the help of their prayers and 
                  confidence in their petitions on our behalf, and hope in the gift of him who
                  strengthened them, that is, as far as our small strength is capable of 
                  attaining, through the strength that arises from grace; and at the head of this
                  divine company we get this great old man whom a high place at table in the
                  heavenly life, where each is in <persName>Christ Jesus</persName>, well befits.
               </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 1, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Matth., V, 16</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 2, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Matth., XXV, 34</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 2, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>James, IV, 17</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 3, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ms. om.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 3, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>This statement cannot be taken literally. He gives an account of Abraham of Kalesh (ch. 4) who died before he was born.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 4, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ps. CXIX, 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 3, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>I Cor., XII, 10</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
