<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/794">Zeʿora</title>
                <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): 
                     <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license">
                        used under a Creative Commons Attribution license 
                        <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/793"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/795"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks. Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/794.xml -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-2" n="2">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-2">
                    <head type="main">Next the Second History, Of the Divine Blessed Man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName>.</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-2.1" n="1">
                  [...] and a spring broke forth and came out in abundance, many times more so than
                  <pb type="vol" n="19"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="19"/>that which existed before. And, when the blessed man saw it, he rejoiced
                  and thanked God who had done his will; and at once the same night he
                  departed to his master, having charged the brother who was with him not
                  to reveal this to men during his life, as he also did not inform his master.
                  But, when the news was received that the blessed man had gone down to
                  the spring in the evening, in the morning many persons gathered together
                  in order to go and be blessed by him; and they see the spring flowing in
                  a copious and rich stream, and their lands and gardens inundated with
                  water, and they ran to the city; and they informed the bishop of this. And
                  the news was received throughout the city; and the bishop with the judge
                  and the whole city directed their steps to the place; and when they saw it
                  they marvelled and gave thanks, and praised God who does the will of them
                  that fear him. And they called that fountain <hi rend="singleQuotes">Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName>'s spring</hi> to this
                  day; and it is even actually so called to the present time.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> This was the
                  first act of power which the prayer of this divine master produced in his own
                  disciple.
               </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-2.2" n="2">
                  Again once the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3640">mighty hosts of the Huns</persName> came forth,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> and those blessed
                  men were in a fortress; and, when it was thought that they had passed by,
                  <pb type="vol" n="20"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="20"/>the blessed man sent him to go down and inspect the monastery. And, as
                  he was going down, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3640">the host of the Huns</persName> came upon him on the way, while
                  he was carrying his cross and walking, and repeating the service. And
                  at once one of them ran and drew his sword, and raised his hand for the
                  purpose of smiting the blessed man; and he on his side raised his hand
                  against him and said to him : <quote>Ho! move it no farther</quote>. And the hand of
                  that <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3639">barbarian</persName> was impeded and moved no farther, while he retained his
                  sword and his hand was thus raised, until the whole of the host had
                  passed; and he was released and he also as well went away, while none of
                  them had hurt him, and so, trusting in God, he also went to his monastery.
               </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-2.3" n="3">
                  After the term of years that the blessed man lived, when he had taken
                  his rest and gone to (his) Lord, the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName>, wlio was in truth a small
                  man (<persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">zʿura</persName>) in his stature and in his mind was higher than the high, made a
                  column for himself, and went up and stood upon it, while thence forth the
                  deeds of power and healings of his master were performed through him.
                  For, [after] he had gone up on to the column, and it was accordingly no
                  longer in his power to grasp paralysed persons with his hands and bend them
                  and cure the sick, they used to give him water and he used to pronounce
                  a blessing, and wherever it fell a cure was not long in following. But,
                  when he had completed a term of years upon the column, the synodite
                  <pb type="vol" n="21"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="21"/>persecutors came to him; and, since they did not find in his disposition a
                  chance of making him communicate with them, they brought him down
                  from the column; and, when he had come down, he was moved with zeal
                  saying, <quote>I will not rest till I go up to him who holds the royal authority,
                     and testify to him before our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> concerning the persecution
                     of the whole church, and concerning the distresses and the mockery of the
                     saints in every place</quote>.
               </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-2.4" n="4">
                  With this zeal the blessed man armed himself and with trust in his Lord
                  also, and he arose and took <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3642">ten of his disciples</persName>, and journeyed to the royal
                  city itself and arrived there, letters from the adversaries having also preceded
                  the blessed man by no small number of days, which gave information as to
                  his going up, by dispensation of providence, in the same manner in which
                  things were also effected through <persName>Ahab</persName> without his knowledge, for, while
                  he himself was turning over his plans for killing the zealous <persName>Elijah</persName> the great
                  man, sending as of his own motion his envoys and his letters among foreign
                  peoples with regard to his death, he was being made to celebrate and display
                  the fact that he was able actually to bind the heaven so that no rain fell
                  upon the earth, and was by his envoys proclaiming his mighty act to the
                  <pb type="vol" n="22"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="22"/>kings of the peoples,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> who, while<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> they were unaware for what reason the
                  heaven was prevented from discharging rain, were learning from the enemies
                  themselves who was the cause of this, that he might become an object of
                  astonishment. So therefore letters preceded this illustrious man stating
                  concerning him, <quote>Lo! a disturber is coming there</quote>, and, <quote>If he enters
                     the city, he will turn the whole of it upside down</quote>; which prophecy itself
                  also they made after the manner of <persName>Caiaphas</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> as he did indeed in truth
                  turn many from their evil faith to the truth.
               </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-2.5" n="5">
                  But, when the authorities received information of the blessed man's
                  coming, they forthwith hastened to see him, in consequence of the alarming
                  report about him, while even the king hastily enjoined precaution (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άσφαλεία</foreign>)
                  upon his senators (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σύγκλητος</foreign>), and made a great assembly of bishops for the
                  purpose of contending in argument with the blessed man himself, since the
                  fear and terror of him had in consequence of the contents of the letters which
                  were supposed to be adverse fallen upon the king and the chief men as well
                  as the bishops, who thought that he had come up like the sea to smite
                  them by means of his clever words, not knowing that simple men and fishermen 
                  are not armed with these things, but with the hidden power of grace.
                  <pb type="vol" n="23"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="23"/>But, when the old man and all his company came in, and, the doctrines that
                  were condemned had been gently<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> expressed, those that were right were
                  again heroically expressed in sound language on behalf of the believers by
                  the blessed man with the frankness (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>) of his Lord and the confidence
                  that contends with death, while the spiritual old man carried out his procedure 
                  according to what it is written that the king of <placeName>Edom</placeName> commanded
                  and said, <quote>Ye shall not contend with great nor with small save with the
                     king of <placeName>Israel</placeName>
                        </quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> for he did not direct his contest with great nor with small,
                  but against him who roared as a lion, and looked whom he should devour,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/>
                  in that he sternly brought the whole measureless reproof against him personally, 
                  on account of all the persecution of God's church, concerning all
                  the blood that was shed in his days, concerning the introduction of this
                  accursed synod, and concerning many things, saying, <quote>All these things God
                     will require at your hands in the great day when he shall come, all the
                     distress of the Christians everywhere</quote>. When the king by reason of the
                  fear of him feared to lay a hand on the blessed man on account of the divine
                  frankness (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>) which he possessed, he was excited by his rage, and
                  <pb type="vol" n="24"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="24"/>clenched his fist (?) as tightly as he could in violent rage, and struck himself
                  upon the breast and said, <quote>You are apostates and corrupters, and the synod
                     is true, and I will not consent to hear these things against it from you any
                     more, and, if you were true men, God would show me a sign by your hands.
                     And he who anathematizes the synod contends with his life</quote>. On all this
                  commotion taking place great terror overwhelmed all the magnates; but the
                  blessed man, when he saw that he had decreed death against anyone who
                  anathematized the synod, was kindled with zeal and his heart became hot
                  within him as it is written, and fire seized his body,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> and immediately he
                  went straight against him, and said : <quote>The synod which divided <persName>Christ</persName> our
                     Lord is anathematized not only by us, but also by the angels of heaven.
                     And, since you seek a sign, by believers signs are not required; but the
                     Lord will not show you a sign outside you, but in your own self</quote>. And so
                  he<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> went out in violent rage, while threats were also being forged against
                  the blessed man. But after a day the sign for which he asked appeared in
                  him according to the blessed man's saying, in that he was smitten upon his
                  head, and his understanding was taken away; and a fearful swelling covered
                  him,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/>, until human shape was not recognised in him<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> insomuch that his wife,
                  <pb type="vol" n="25"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="25"/>who was very cunning, hid him secretly in the chamber, that it might not
                  be known to the city that he was already dead, and except two physicians
                  and two chamberlains she did not allow anyone to come in to him, while
                  she sent intercessors to the blessed man to ask him to come and for
                  him that he might recover, and he would at once make peace in the church.
                  And, this message having roused him, he went and saw him, and he was
                  sorry; and he said to him : <quote>Lo! the sign which you sought</quote>. And the
                  blessed man made a prayer, and the same hour his understanding returned
                  to him, and he recognised the old man and knew that it it had so happened to
                  him because he had set him at naught; and he went on entreating him to
                  pray for him that he might be healed, and he might do all that he ordered;
                  while the blessed man said to him : <quote>This happened to you, because you
                     tempted the Lord your God like an unbeliever, and sought a sign</quote>. And
                  thenceforth the dread of the blessed man fell upon him, and in fear he used
                  to assent to his requests in everything; only the state of the church he did
                  not set right, because the delinquencies of the <persName>Amorites</persName> were perhaps not
                  yet full; but he ceased that violence and these threats, while the power of
                  the old man's prayer thenceforward gave freedom of action (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>.) to all
                  <pb type="vol" n="26"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="26"/>the believers in every city and in every place, and they openly held assemblies, which<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> 
                  before his coming the threat of death was decreed, against
                  anyone who was discovered holding an assembly. And the fame of the
                  blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName> reached as far as <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/641">Rome</placeName>, while God continued to work signs
                  and deeds of power through him, and the whole city resorted to him, and
                  he was made protector of the poor as in his country, while many great affairs
                  were resolved by him before the king and all the senators (<foreign xml:lang="grc">συγκλητικοί</foreign>), while 
                  every day he was engaged in the same contest on behalf of the faith. After
                  the blessed man had been some time in the royal city, the man deserving
                  of evil memory who had at that time been made patriarch in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/641">Rome</placeName>, whose
                  name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3193">Agapetus</persName>, was summoned by some cause, and went down to the
                  royal city,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> a man who was a grievous blasphemer, in comparison of whose
                  blasphemies those of the followers of <persName>Paul</persName> of <placeName>Samosata</placeName> were very small;
                  who, if sentence from heaven had not overtaken him and suppressed his
                  blasphemies, was about to issue this order, that the name of the Blessed
                  <persName>Mary</persName> the<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> God-bearer should not be commemorated in the church at all,
                  <pb type="vol" n="27"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="27"/>nor her likeness be found depicted anywhere, while he presumptuously
                  promulgated his blasphemies, which did not retard for him the reward that
                  his labour deserved. This man therefore, having been magnificently received
                  by the king with much display, inasmuch as he was not aware of all the
                  evil of his mind, when he had come in, inasmuch as he was annoyed by the
                  reports of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName>, brought a complaint about him before the
                  king, saying, <quote>Wherefore is the <persName>Syrian</persName> deceiver who is here allowed by you
                     to turn the world to his deception<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/>
                        </quote>? But the king, inasmuch as he knew
                  well the old man's power, said to him, <quote>And what can I do to him? For he
                     is a stubborn man who does not fear men</quote>. But he, in order to show his
                  zeal in the case of the blessed man first, accused him saying, <quote>Let me do to
                     him so that he will submit, or be expelled from all the countries</quote>. And
                  the king gave him his will, saying, <quote>If you are stronger than he, do as you
                     wish</quote>.
               </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-2.6" n="6">
                  But this man in his arrogance without delay sent some of his own leading
                  men and the king's to the blessed man himself (a large villa at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2860">Sycae</placeName> on
                  the other side<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> had been given him by the queen, and he was staying there
                  <pb type="vol" n="28"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="28"/>with all <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3642">his disciples</persName>; for it was the first days of the fast), while the 
                  presumptuous man set himself against the blessed man by sending him a message
                  in these terms : <quote>The king and the patriarch<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/>have ordered that either you
                     come here, or I come there at once; and it is quite impossible for you to
                     remain longer in this country, unless you do the king's order and ours, and
                     make accord with us</quote>. When the blessed old man heard these things, he
                  jeered at his arrogance, telling them to say to him, <quote>We have a law (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμος</foreign>)
                     laid down for us by our true King, that we are not to receive anyone in these
                     holy days, nor make answers (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άπόκρισεις</foreign>); insomuch that our door is closed,
                     and accordingly we are not free to answer either you or the king. But
                     wait for us till the fifth day of the week when we shall open the door, and
                     after we have opened it what God knows to be right he will himself perform
                     between us. But for the present we will not voluntarily answer you; for if
                     you seek to act with violence you know</quote>. When that wretched man
                  learned these things, he was filled with violent rage, and ordered the
                  magister to take excubitors and irons and bring the blessed man across.
               </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-2.7" n="7">
                  When that man as he was ordered had taken the irons and embarked in a
                  <pb type="vol" n="29"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="29"/>cutter (<foreign xml:lang="grc">δρόμων</foreign>) with the military force and they had gone that he might
                  fetch the blessed man, when he was on the point of landing on the other
                  side, something like a wind took the cutter (<foreign xml:lang="grc">δρόμων</foreign>) and turned it back, and
                  it was on the city side whence he had started. And again a second time
                  they returned, and approached; and, when they were<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/> just about<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/>
                        <!-- eb, there are two "1" footnotes, so I have labeled this for "11" for now. Let me know what you want me to do with this part! --> to fix the
                  ladder (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχάλα</foreign>), it was as if a man grasped the boat (<foreign xml:lang="grc">καράβιον</foreign>), and with mighty
                  force placed it where it started.
               </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-2.8" n="8">
                  Again according to that which is written <quote>They knew not nor understood
                     that they were walking in darkness</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a21" target="#n21" n="21"/> he was enraged against the cutter-men
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">
                            <foreign xml:lang="grc">δρομωνάριος</foreign>
                        </foreign>) as if it was they who were lazy, and they proceeded to go on
                  board. And, as they were struggling and advanced little nearer, like what
                  is written again, <quote>The Lord was making war for <placeName>Israel</placeName>
                        </quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a22" target="#n22" n="22"/> there came
                  forth something like a flash of lightning and suddenly smote their boat
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">καράβιον</foreign>), and the bench was torn out of it from end to end, and it sprang
                  away and mounted upwards as far as the eye can see; and then that
                  wretched man understood that it was God's power which was contending
                  on behalf of the blessed man. And quickly with cries of lamentation they
                  escaped to shore; and they went and told these things to those who sent
                  them, and everyone was seized with wonder.
               </ab>
                    <pb type="vol" n="30"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="30"/>
                    <ab xml:id="section-2.9" n="9">
                  But, when that man had begun to promulgate his blasphemies openly,
                  and poured his gall into the ears of the king and the people of the heretics
                  who rejoiced that an instrument (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όργανον</foreign>) had been found for the spirit of
                  their blasphemies, and they had begun one and another to become drunk
                  on his foul dregs, and he was forging threats against the believers everywhere,
                  inasmuch as the fear of God was not before his eyes, then suddenly that
                  happened in his case which was once said in the case of the arrogance of
                  the <persName>Assyrian</persName>, <quote>Against whom hast thou opened thy mouth and lengthened
                     thy tongue, save against the Holy one of <placeName>Israel</placeName>
                        </quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a23" target="#n23" n="23"/> So therefore the Lord
                  smote this man in his tongue, and it grew long and protruded beyond his
                  mouth and came down to his breast, making a fearful sight with great swelling,
                  so that he was twice lanced in it, while terror and trepidation seized all
                  who saw him at the sight of him. And in this torment and manifest sentence
                  of requital for his blasphemy he lingered till the fifth day of the week<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a24" target="#n24" n="24"/>
                  which the blessed man fixed as the term and said, <quote>On the fifth day of the
                     week God will perform what he knows</quote>. And on the same day he who
                  <pb type="vol" n="31"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="31"/>had threatened the blessed man received his burial and perished,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a25" target="#n25" n="25"/> and fear
                  accompanied by shame seized all the partisans of that wretched man, and
                  joy reigned over the believers everywhere, while everyone was amazed at
                  the blessed man's words, how God wrought this miracle in him. When the
                  partisans of that wretched man could not by reason of their shame find what
                  to say, they devised a plan, saying, <quote>Whereas on the day which <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName>
                     decreed for the patriarch he died, he used enchantments against him, and he
                     died on that same day</quote>. And so these men were ashamed and God was
                  glorified, and the believers rejoiced; and even the blessed man himself would
                  confess that God had heard his voice, and had awoken with his sentence
                  against the blasphemer. For, when he heard the openness (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>) of his
                  blasphemies, he prayed and said, as he used to pray and say at all seasons,
                  <quote>
                            <quote>The Lord awaked like a sleeper and like a man who hath shaken off his
                        wine, and smote his enemies behind him</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a26" target="#n26" n="26"/> Lord behold the blasphemies
                     of presumption against thee, and <quote>Be not quiet nor silent, O God; since lo!
                        thine enemies make tumult, and they who hate thee have lifted up the head
                        <pb type="vol" n="32"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="32"/>against thy people</quote>
                            <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a27" target="#n27" n="27"/>
                        </quote>; besides the other things which the blessed man used
                  to repeat in his prayer and over his incense. And justice did indeed not
                  delay to show the power of his prayer in that blasphemer. And so everyone
                  was amazed at all the things that were done through the saint and at the
                  deeds of power wrought through his prayer, and gave thanks to God, and
                  especially at his labours and his petitions and his crying and his tears
                  night and day, so that not one hour ever passed from him without his
                  knocking at God's door. Even when he was sitting and speaking with: men,
                  because his mind was dwelling above in heaven among the angels, his tears
                  would suddenly gush forth perforce, while he did not wish to do this before
                  men, and sobs would spring up in him, and he would beat his two hands
                  upon his face, and rest his head upon his knees, and thus he would cry
                  loudly. And sometimes, when he was displaying the cheerful appearance of
                  laughter with his lips, in the middle of his speech at which he displayed the
                  appearance of laughing sobs overpowered him, insomuch that while speaking
                  with us he often did so, until by virtue of the freedom (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>) which I
                  <pb type="vol" n="33"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="33"/>enjoyed with him I went so far as to presume to say: <quote>Why is it, our
                     father, that in the midst of laughing you are thus suddenly saddened by
                     weeping? This tells us that your mind is not occupied with us.or in that
                     which you are saying to us, that sorrow thus suddenly seizes you</quote>. But
                  he would say to me, <quote>Know, my son, that I did not want to do this while
                     speaking, and my sins suddenly occur to my mind, and turn my joy to
                     distress</quote>. When I often entreated him between ourselves to tell me privily
                  his manner of life, even adjuring him by God to inform me, he would
                  again while weeping yield to constraint and say : <quote>When, my son, I am
                     constrained to speak among men, my mind looks at those above in heaven,
                     how their mouths cease not even for a short season from praises, and sobs
                     rise within me on account of myself, how I am neglecting to praise that
                     Creator who created me, and have ceased to make petitions for the forgiveness 
                     of my offences, and am sitting in intercourse with men; and this and
                     other things urges<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a28" target="#n28" n="28"/> me to cease speaking</quote>. And so I was amazed at this
                  <pb type="vol" n="34"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="34"/>saint's disposition, as well as at his humility and the kindness to strangers
                  and poor men of which his soul was full with great zeal, so that in consequence 
                  a multitude of the poor of the city and strangers from every place
                  flocked to him on account of the report of his charity, until eighty and
                  ninety and as many as a hundred tables were on some days prepared in
                  his monastery. And thereupon he made great cauldrons and appointed
                  men who were continually cooking and making bread; and in company
                  with many he would with his own hands make himself into an attendant
                  with cheerfulness and joy. While the blessed man was thus illustrious in
                  all things, and deeds of power and signs were every day wrought through
                  him, to narrate each one of which we have omitted since we are not sufficient, 
                  the whole city used already to flock to him, with the whole senate
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σύγκλητος</foreign>), and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a29" target="#n29" n="29"/> they who saw the great freedom of speech (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>), and
                  the rebuke of those who had the power of death and life after God, were
                  kept in great fear and dread of him, and everyone put great faith in him.
               </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-2.10" n="10">
                  Then all the heretics in the churches and monasteries were sorely dejected,
                  and they cried against the king every day in great assemblies: <quote>If the
                     <pb type="vol" n="35"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="35"/>
                            <persName>Syrian</persName> does not leave the city, it will be ruined</quote>, and the king and queen
                  when they saw it, in order that there might not be a sedition (<foreign xml:lang="grc">στάσις</foreign>) and evil
                  in the city, begged him to depart from the city limits, while the queen
                  prepared a place for the blessed man in a certain camp (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κάστρα</foreign>) in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1459">Thrace</placeName>
                  the name of which was <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2772">Dercus</placeName> thirty miles off, and so he set out thither,
                  while the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/784">Theodosius</persName> also the patriarch of Alexandria had been
                  established there; and thereafter the blessed men dwelt there together,
                  while that camp (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κάστρα</foreign>) thundered praise. And after some time again on
                  account of the inclemency of this place they withdrew to another; and after
                  some years the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName> finished his course and fell asleep in the same
                  place, his disciple <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3212">Hananya</persName> the presbyter who 'was next to him<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a30" target="#n30" n="30"/> having
                  left the place, who himself also had been trained with him during the lifetime
                  of his blessed master <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">Habib</persName> in the manner of life of both of them.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a31" target="#n31" n="31"/> In
                  these lines we have comprised the story of the holy old man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName>, dreading
                  ondemnation for the omissions of all his triumphs which we have omitted
                  and passed over for the reason that our time is not long enough for these to
                  relate them.
               </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-2">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-2.1" n="11">
                  The history of the divine man the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName> is ended.
               </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 19, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This clause is perhaps a scribe's addition as v. D. and L. suggest.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 19, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Probably in 515 (Marcell., <foreign xml:lang="la">sub anno</foreign>; Theoph., A. V. 0008).</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 22, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I Kings, VIII, 10.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 22, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 22, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>John, XI, 49, 50.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 23, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>There is perhaps some error here. If it is right, the intention must be to change the Chalcedonians with lukewarmness.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 23, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>I Kings, XXII, 31.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 23, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>I Pet., V, 8.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 24, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. XXXIX, 3, 4.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 24, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. Justinian.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 24, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Mich. (who repeats this passage from our text) <hi rend="singleQuotes">his face</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 24, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>This reminds us of Proc., <title>Hist. Arc.</title>, XII, 23, and in the story which there follows the monk perhaps Zʿura.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 26, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 26, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Feb.536. He came on a political mission from king Theodahat (<title>Lib. Pont.</title>).</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 26, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 27, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Mich. <hi rend="singleQuotes">by his sorceries</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 27, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. of the Golden Horn.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 28, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Menas.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 29, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 29, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n21" target="#a21" n="21">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 29, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. LXXXII, 5.</note>
                <note xml:id="n22" target="#a22" n="22">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 29, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Josh, X, 42.</note>
                <note xml:id="n23" target="#a23" n="23">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 30, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Is., LVII, 4.</note>
                <note xml:id="n24" target="#a24" n="24">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 30, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Mich. add. <hi rend="singleQuotes">of the mysteries</hi>,sc. on Maundy Thursday: but this does not agree with the statement that it was in the first days of Lent.</note>
                <note xml:id="n25" target="#a25" n="25">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 31, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>22 Apr. acc. to <title>Lib. Pont.</title>: but this was Tuesday, and not in Lent. As Easter was 23 Mar., and A. addressed a letter to Justinian 
               on 18 Mar. (Jaffe. <foreign xml:lang="la">sub anno</foreign>), if he died on Thurs. in Lent, it must have been 20 Mar.; but see p. 30, n. 2. Very prohabably whole story is baseless and the date given in <title>Lib. Pont.</title> right. <hi rend="singleQuotes">Zach. Rh.</hi>
               (IX 19) gives a similar account of his death but without mention of Z. or indication of date.</note>
                <note xml:id="n26" target="#a26" n="26">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 31, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. LXXVIII, 65, 66.</note>
                <note xml:id="n27" target="#a27" n="27">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 32, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. LXXXIII, 2-4.</note>
                <note xml:id="n28" target="#a28" n="28">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 33, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n29" target="#a29" n="29">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 34, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n30" target="#a30" n="30">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 35, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">succeed him</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n31" target="#a31" n="31">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 35, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 17.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
