<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/804">Mary and Euphemia</title>
                <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/803"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/805"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/804.xml -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-12" n="12">
                    <head type="main">Next the Twelfth History, of Two Holy Sisters, Who Were Called <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1880">Daughters of the Gazelle</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> and One Performed Her Task In
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, and the Other in
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/200">Thella Dmauzlath</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/>
                    </head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-12.1" n="1"> Inasmuch as we learn from the divine
                     <persName>Paul</persName> who says that in <persName>Christ Jesus</persName> is
                  no male nor female,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> it has seemed
                  good to us to introduce the history of persons also who were by nature females;
                  for the subject of their lives does <pb type="vol" n="167"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="167"/>not fall short of
                  the standard of the series of the histories of the saints; since neither is the
                  course of life of these persons lower than that of<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> the high path in which each one of these walked, but
                  their habits of life also are great, and surpass written narratives. These
                  virtuous blessed women then were sisters in the body, of whom one, the elder, was
                  called <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1880">Mary</persName>, and one
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3025">Euphemia</persName>. But this
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1880">Mary</persName> was a pure
                  virgin, and chose for herself from her childhood quietude and renuntiation and
                  great labours of fasting and much watching, and constant prayers, and exertion in
                  the way of charity or of pilgrimage. This woman therefore formed the plan of going
                  up to <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, and in the holy country in which the
                  dispensation for the sake of the salvation of all was carried out there to worship
                  and return to her employment.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> When
                  then she had gone up and prayed, she stood before the place called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2781">Golgotha</placeName>, and was lifted up
                  with ecstasy, and she remained standing there three days and three nights, while
                  men came and saw her; and the custodians wished to drive her away; and on seeing
                  that she was a feeble old woman, and further that she was standing in prayer they
                  let her <pb type="vol" n="168"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="168"/>alone. And from that time she used to sit there
                  in the temple, and again she continued going round and praying for three years,
                  without entering anyone's house or speaking with human beings. And she did not
                  sleep outside the church, or yet ask anything from human beings; but she would sit
                  among the poor and pass the night with them, in the church and wherever it might
                     be.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> And, if it chanced that
                  anyone came and gave charity in the place where she happened to be, she would
                  stretch out her hand and receive it; and, if the sum received by her reached
                  twenty <foreign>minae</foreign>, she would not afterwards accept anything more;
                  and, if she received more than twenty <foreign>minae</foreign>, she would give
                  them to someone else; but with these twenty she would buy bread for fifteen
                     <foreign>minae</foreign>, and herbs for two, and pulse for three; and so
                  whenever it happened to be she would take her food. But, if it chanced that no one
                  came to the place where she happened to be, she would sit in the same way, and for
                  three and four days, and as much as a week she would sit silent, with her mind
                  wrapt up in heaven. Usually her seat was in front of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2781">Golgotha</placeName>, while she sat with
                  her eyes raised, and looking <pb type="vol" n="169"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="169"/>in ecstatic wonder and
                  weeping, just as if she were looking at God fastened to the cross and standing
                  there, with the result that, while she sat there. in admiration every day, those
                  who saw her looked upon her as a mad woman, or as some old person who had become
                  silly; and thus she completed three years there in her praying. And afterwards
                  some persons who knew her and were well acquainted with her admirable modes of
                  life came thither and found her sitting before <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2781">Golgotha</placeName> with her eyes raised
                  and looking at it, and weeping with ecstatic wonder. And on seeing her they fell
                  down and made obeisance to her, and saluted her; but she was troubled, because she
                  did not wish that men should know her there. Then these persons told many about
                  the perfect modes of life of the blessed woman from her childhood down to her old
                  age, and many marvelled at her. And thenceforth those in whose eyes she had been
                  reckoned as a foolish old woman, and as if she sat there for the sake of charity
                  in order to live the bodily life, began to honour her as a great and holy woman,
                  entreating her to pray for them. But the blessed woman when she saw it, inasmuch
                  as she was struck with fear lest she should be honoured by men and lose her
                  labour, fled thence immediately, being distressed at her expulsion from the holy
                     <pb type="vol" n="170"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="170"/>place, inasmuch as she had intended to remain there
                  in that occupation all her lifetime. And so she departed, and went down again to
                     <placeName>the East</placeName>; and she determined that all her life she would
                  once every year offer worship in the place where God suffered. And thus she did,
                  travelling along that road in the season of extreme heat, and she did not taste
                  anything except every other day, while she carried nothing whatever except one
                  small basket (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σπυρίδα</foreign>), which she fastened to
                  her arm, and one salver; and thus she travelled. And she imposed this labour upon
                  herself every year all the days of her life, returning and applying herself to
                  constant prayers and supplications and tears, all the days of her quiet life; and
                  so she would when her time came again return and go up to
                     <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, and accomplish her vow and come back to her
                  usual habits, insomuch that great deeds of power were wrought by her presence, not
                  by her will and her words. But she herself shrank greatly from such things, and it
                  was not pleasing to her that anyone should say anything of the kind to her; and,
                  if anyone wished to press her, he did not see her again. For this devout woman
                  guarded herself carefully against pride <pb type="vol" n="171"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="171"/>and repressed
                  vain glory, lest she should lose her labour. But her sister <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3025">Euphemia</persName>, who was younger than
                  she, had in her childhood been united to a <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3610">husband</persName>, and had had one
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3232">daughter</persName>, who herself
                  also had been trained from a tender age in religion. But afterwards, since this
                  woman's <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3610">husband</persName> had
                  died, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3025">Euphemia</persName> herself
                  and her little daughter formed the household, insomuch that she thenceforward came
                  to herself<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> from the secular order
                  of life, and turned to the practices of her sister which she had been practising
                  for a long time, and lived in the order of devoutness and in the religious habit
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σκήμα</foreign>), while she also learned the psalms by
                  heart, and taught them to her daughter; for her daughter also had while she was a
                  child been splendidly trained in the psalms and in the Scriptures and in
                  handwriting. And from that time she appointed fixed hours for reciting service and
                  for the prayers, those of the night and those of the day; and, while observing her
                  sister's asceticism and the rest of her practices, she herself practised another
                  high and sublime order of life, while she in fact carried out both, the observance
                  of abstinence and the practice of relief of the distressed. But this admirable
                  woman decided in her mind not to introduce into her house other men's bread that
                  was not gained by the work of her hands; and, if it <pb type="vol" n="172"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="172"/>came
                  in, neither she her daughter tasted any of it. But, because they were fine and
                  excellent workwomen, they would weave two pounds only of goat's wool yarn for a
                     <foreign rend="italics">denarius</foreign>, which she received from great
                  ladies of the city and worked up, buying their small supply of provisions with
                  half of it, and assigning the other half to the relief of the poor and the sick
                  and the prisoners, while every day she would take cooked food and bread and wine
                  to every place where there was anyone in bonds or shut up in prison or anywhere
                  else, and again she would go round all the streets of the city, and wherever she
                  found a sick man or a cripple, or a blind man or an old man who could not stand,
                  she would sit by the side of each one of them and ask him, <quote>What, my
                     brother, do you wish? Would you like me to buy you some bread and herbs only?
                     Or do you perhaps wish for something else instead of this? or do you perhaps
                     wish me to go and buy you some fine wheaten bread?</quote> And, whatever the
                  man, whoever he might be, said, if her head-covering was in its place,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> she did not leave him till she had
                  satisfied him. And, if she had no coppers at hand, she would run to her house and
                  take some article of their furniture and go and pawn it, and thus she would <pb type="vol" n="173"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="173"/>satisfy that indigent man; and there could not be any
                  sick poor man among those lying in the streets who escaped her so that she did not
                  visit him either twice or once in the day, inasmuch as she was capable of running
                  about all day. But she would go round the courts of the houses and ask, <quote>Is
                     there here a needy orphan, or a poor old sick widow?</quote>. And so in the
                  case of everyone whom she found sick, according to the extent of her possessions
                  she would buy for him, fine wheaten bread and fruit, and wine for anyone for whom
                  she knew it to be proper, and would go round and distribute it to them. And, if it
                  happened that she had not by her wherewithal to satisfy any man whoever he might
                  be as was proper, nothing whatever would prevent her from at least bringing him
                  apples or pomegranates or fish or bread, and sitting by him and taking him by the
                  hand, and asking him <quote>What has afflicted you, my son?</quote>, admonishing
                  and saying, <quote>Be not dejected because you are in distress and have no
                     consolation. Blessed are you for the number of unending blessings that are
                     prepared for you in that world, in return for these distresses which are
                     passing by upon you. Look at <persName>Lazarus</persName>, how because he
                     endured and was patient and did not murmur he inherited the <pb type="vol" n="174"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="174"/>kingdom of heaven.</quote> And so the poor used to call her
                        <quote>
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3025">our comfort and our
                        visitor</persName>
                        </quote>. Blessed truly is that soul for the number of
                  souls that are laden with gratitude to her and with her bounties, like those of
                  the original <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3025">Tabitha</persName>,
                  and display them to God the all-seeing; and accordingly this woman was called
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3025">Tabitha</persName> all over the
                  city. And, when all the high-placed men and women of the city saw her
                  strenuousness and her zeal, and saw that she was distressed because she could not
                  visit the distressed in a liberal fashion, everyone who was earnest in seeking
                  what was for the good of his life used to entreat her to go and take everything
                  that she knew to be required by her for the relief of the afflicted and visit
                  them; and thus she was henceforth free from anxiety, because on both points she
                  was much distressed, one that she was unable to relieve the sick and needy out of
                  their small amount of labour, and another that she had not leisure to devote
                  herself to the employment which she had taken upon herself, the work of her hands,
                  except at night. And therefore her daughter laboured simple-mindedly and without
                  murmuring night and day, and she would say if any of her companions or anyone else
                  said to her, <quote>Your mother leaves you to <pb type="vol" n="175"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="175"/>work alone
                     all day</quote>, she on her part would say,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/>
                        <quote>My mother's labour is greater than all labours; and I receive strength from
                     God through her prayers.</quote> And therefore this blessed woman had a little
                  freedom from anxiety, since her daughter laboured for their own necessities, and
                  as far as they were able she supplied the needy, and she herself without much
                  solicitude carried out the ministration to the distressed and needy and afflicted
                  all the day, and alterwards she would further gather them together at her house
                  every day and relieve them out of their labour. And in consequence many would
                  entreat her to accept what was required for her own necessities and those of her
                  daughter, and she would not consent, saying, <quote>May the Lord save me from
                     eating the strength of human beings, and gratifying my body out of the toil of
                     others while it is strong enough to work, and receiving in my spirit the stains
                     of their sins</quote>. But, if anyone pressed her on the other side, she was
                  displeased and would say, <quote>A truce to this charity of yours, since you wish
                     to pollute me with the mire of your sins; my own blots are sufficient for me.
                     God puts strength in me and in that poor girl who is with me, both to work for
                     our necessities, and to <pb type="vol" n="176"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="176"/>minister to our brethren
                     according to our power.</quote> And so they never ate except from the proceeds
                  of their labour in their house, unless perhaps one of them might be constrained on
                  some occasion to perform an act of friendship<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> somewhere. But in this way they were continually
                  occupied in this labour; and moreover in fasting also and prayer, and the recital
                  of service; and, whenever the blessed woman was engaged outside in ministering to
                  the needy, she would perform her office (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κανών</foreign>)
                  in the street while going from one to another, and likewise also did her daughter
                  too at home as well, and at vespers, nocturns, and matins they recited service
                  together. While then this blessed woman was with all her power running in the line
                  of these great practices and in this perfect course of life, neither did she miss
                  the great benefit derived from another labour, in order that the saying of the
                  Lord to the man who had the five talents who said, <quote>He that hath to him
                     shall be given</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> might be
                  fulfilled; but, when the persecution took place, and all the convents round the
                  city were expelled from their places, and the adversaries occupied them, then that
                  blessed woman, like a harbour (<foreign xml:lang="grc">λιμήν</foreign>) which
                  receives ships from all <pb type="vol" n="177"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="177"/>sides that they may lie to and
                  be at peace in it, so herself also received and relieved the persecuted and
                  afflicted from every place; and, because there was no place for the convents to
                  enter away from the heretics, they were constrained to find quarters with her as
                  with a devout woman renowned for her manner of life. But she found means, and
                  hired spacious rooms; and one which was suited and adapted for the purpose and of
                  great size she turned into an imitation of a martyrs' chapel, with likenesses and
                  pictures, and chests,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> and
                  everything, while the oblation also and the Scriptures and everything that is
                  proper to a monastery were in it; and she prepared great mats also, and curtains
                  and rugs. And for herself and her daughter she made provision in a certain inner
                  chamber; and being a very wise woman she alone devoted herself to ministration
                  with the blessed men, and her daughter, because she was a child, she would keep in
                  security within by day and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> by
                  night, lest by the sight of her she should harm anyone, or be herself harmed by
                  anyone through the sight. And so from that time that martyrs' chapel harboured not
                  fewer than ten or fifteen, and as many as twenty, while with the labour of their
                  hands which they disposed of outside <pb type="vol" n="178"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="178"/>she would therefore
                  buy wheat and lentils and herbs, and make bread and cook lentils and herbs from
                  evening to evening, and thus she would relieve them, as many as came, while she
                  herself was occupied in her ministration the whole day, and moreover also the
                  blessed men too were ceaselessly remitting (?) matters to her.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> When accordingly they came to her
                  from all quarters on account of her love toward God, and the produce of their
                  labour was too small to provide for them, she was compelled, in order to relieve
                  their distresses, for their sake to accept what was necessary for them, while she
                  never joined them in tasting of it. And, if it happened that there were some
                  reverend men among them who constrained her to receive the blessing with them, she
                  would bring a triple portion<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> of her
                  bread and all that she required and set it before her, and so cat. But, if it
                  happened that strangers whom she knew to be in need and not known in the city
                  came, she would go out and go to some persons of high position, and make instant
                  demands of them, saying: <quote>A mighty matter it is that you do toward
                        <persName>Christ</persName>, whose property all your good things are. And
                     now lo! you are smearing off <pb type="vol" n="179"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="179"/>your superfluities on
                     him, and you think that your charity is great. <quote>Woe to you, rich men;
                        wail and weep for the calamities that are coming upon you</quote>
                            <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/>
                        </quote>. And in accordance with
                  the text <quote>The righteous is bold as a lion</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> so this zealous woman would boldly rebuke everyone
                  without fear of persons, insomuch that the high-placed men and women of the city
                  were afraid of her, and, as soon as she was going up to the threshold and they
                  heard that <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3025">Euphemia</persName> was
                  coming up, they would say, <quote>Woe to us; <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3025">Tabitha</persName> has come upon us to
                     smite us</quote>. And so therefore she would boldly take all that she wanted to
                  give to anyone who was in need, to the blessed guests or to sick widows and
                  orphans and needy persons, or perhaps sick men, and go down. But, if anyone was
                  recalcitrant and did not give cheerfully, she would make him rue the day by her
                  words, saying, <quote>Is it well that you thus sit yourself while slaves stand and
                     wait upon you, and enjoy a variety of tastes in dainty foods and in wines, and
                     of pure bread and splendid rugs, while God is knocked down in the street and
                     swarms with lice and faints from his hunger, and you do not fear him? and how
                     will you call upon him and he answer you, when you treat him with such
                     contempt? Or how will you <pb type="vol" n="180"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="180"/>ask forgiveness from him?
                     Or how can you expect him to deliver you from hell?</quote> And thus she would
                  pass judgment upon them, so that those who were secular (?) were a little offended
                  against her in accordance with the saying <quote>The fool loveth not one who
                     reproveth him</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/> But she
                  herself was so earnestly bent on relieving at all costs distressed and afflicted
                  souls who lacked human comfort and satisfying their needs that even the whole city
                  did not suffice for her business, but she would even go round the inns and roads
                  and habitations outside also and search, lest there should be any needy man or
                  stranger laid up sick in one of them, so that she in fact found many and relieved
                  them. And some she took into her house, and some she carried to superintendents of
                  hospitals, and gave charge concerning them, and it was chiefly on her account that
                  they were received and tended; for she was known to great and small in the city,
                  and everyone recognised her on seeing her even at a distance by her quick and
                  rapid walk, since she would walk in this way summer and winter in mud and snow and
                  frost without anything whatever on her feet, with her toes bruised and her nails
                  torn out and the <pb type="vol" n="181"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="181"/>blood flowing from her wounds, and she
                  would not consent even to treat them, while everyone was very sorry for her on
                  account of the state in which they saw her; for indeed we ourselves too would
                  often jest with her and say to her, <quote>Do not kill yourself in so cruel a way,
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3025">Tabitha</persName>
                        </quote>;
                  but she would say: <quote>When the end of a thing is corruption and the worm,
                     wherefore do we preserve it<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/>
                        </quote> And she was so energetic in her task that the mouth is too small to
                  tell the story of her great labour; for, just as her sister <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1880">Mary</persName> in the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/200">Thella</placeName> was celebrated for her
                  perfect practices of asceticism and quietude and renuntiation, so was this woman
                  also in the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>;
                  so that the fame of these sisters was spoken all over <placeName>the
                     East</placeName>, everyone being wrapt in wonder to think how each of them in
                  one peerless mode of life was strenuously applying herself to store up
                  righteousness. When then the blessed woman had completed a period of thirty years
                  more or less in such practices, and her house thundered night and day with the
                  praises of the <pb type="vol" n="182"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="182"/>saints from all quarters, Satan who is
                  always envious of good things did not neglect to stir up a trial against them, in
                  order to make them lose the benefit of their great and spiritual business and
                  deprive them of it. Then he stirred up against them the heretical envy of those
                  who held power in the church, cruelly and savagely and mercilessly, in that they
                  said, <quote>These women are disturbing this city, and the citizens fear and
                     honour them more than the bishops; since their house has been made a cave of
                        robbers,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/> and they receive and
                     shelter the deceivers</quote>. And they sent and arrested them and brought them
                  into the church, in order to make them communicants in their impiety. When they
                  had brought many inducements to bear upon them both in the way of threats and in
                  the way of blandishments and they did not yield, but the blessed woman in
                  confidence that fights with death even used vehement language, saying, <quote>As
                     for me, may the Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> deliver me from
                     communicating with those who divide him, and with those who proclaim a
                     quaternity in place of the Holy Trinity</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a21" target="#n21" n="21"/> and, when those who <pb type="vol" n="183"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="183"/>deserved
                  these words had heard them, they were seized with furious, vehement, passionate
                  indignation, and they ordered the blessed woman to be confined in the lowest
                  dungeon of the prison as a punishment for <quote>this audacity</quote>. And so she
                  was confined for thirty days in the dungeon, while the whole city entreated that
                  she might be released; and they bound themselves under a curse that she should not
                  come up thence till she received the oblation there. And, when she heard it, she
                  would mock at them, and say: <quote>Would that I might undergo sufferings in
                     return for the suffering of him who suffered for my sake on the cross. I am
                     glad to die here rather than to die in denial of my Lord and my God</quote>.
                  And, when they saw that it was impossible, and the whole city was grieved on her
                  account, they released her and expelled her from the whole city; which also Satan
                  had been contriving to bring about. And then all the poor of the city were
                  oppressed with sorrow and great aflliction, insomuch that<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a22" target="#n22" n="22"/> all the people of high position were distressed. But
                  they left, and went to her blessed sister <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1880">Mary</persName>, and it was their wish to
                  go up to <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>; and they went up and prayed, and
                  returned. And so these blessed women were buffeted by the trials (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of persecution for five years; and, having
                  received one another’s blessing, afterwards, thinking that the fury against <pb type="vol" n="184"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="184"/>them had perhaps abated, they returned to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName> and came in secretly, and
                  they resided in a certain <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3615">gentleman</persName>'s house. And, when it began to become known, and the
                  adversaries began to speak about them, those in whose house they were residing
                  were alarmed, and they besought them to depart, lest (as they said) their house
                  should be plundered. But the blessed woman was distressed; and she cried to God,
                  and said: <quote>My Lord, thy mercy knoweth that I have grown feeble, and there is
                     no more strength in me. It is sufficient for me</quote>. And the same night a
                  summons was sent forth for the blessed woman according to the request of her
                  prayer, and she fell into a sickness; and, while these people were troubled on her
                  account and in fear, she called them, and says to them: <quote>Be not dismayed, my
                     children; for I shall go out from among you<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a23" target="#n23" n="23"/> this week assuredly</quote>. But they did not
                  understand her words, to what departure she referred. And she called her daughter,
                  who was called <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3232">Maria</persName>,
                  and said to her: <quote>My daughter, be comforted in <persName>Christ</persName>,
                     and keep yourself in purity for the Lord your Lord to whom you were betrothed;
                     and be not distressed, for I am not deserting you (far be it from me, my
                     beloved); but I am committing you to the Child of my <pb type="vol" n="185"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="185"/>blessed Lady <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3232">Maria</persName>,
                     and to the holy one herself, that by her prayers you may be preserved, and may
                     become a temple for the indwelling of the Holy Spirit of God</quote>. And after
                  laying many charges upon her, and saying positively, <quote>I for my part am going
                     to <persName>Christ</persName>
                        </quote>, and committing her to the divine grace,
                  while speaking, she stretched out her hand, and made the sign over her in the name
                  of the Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>; and she extended herself and looked
                  toward heaven, and, while her eyes were raised toward heaven, her soul passed
                  away, while everyone was seized with amazement at her departure; and her daughter
                  remained alone solitary and bereaved. And on the next day but one after her
                  mother's departure, while she was in misery and was sitting in her grief, and she
                  also was near passing away from life, lo! a man came bearing a letter from the
                  blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1880">Mary</persName>, who had
                  passed from the world to God ten days before. And certain persons on it coming to
                  their knowledge prevented her niece from hearing it and her soul flitting from
                  sorrow, since her whole hope was now this, to go to her blessed aunt, and share
                  her manner of life until her end. And for this reason they prevented it, lest she
                  should hear the news and be overwhelmed with anguish. These saints therefore in
                     <pb type="vol" n="186"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="186"/>this way both finished their marvellous courses
                  together within eight days, each of them carrying the great load of her
                  merchandise. The blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1880">Mary</persName> completed sixty years in the course of sanctity from her birth
                  down to her departure, walking in the road of perfection, and labouring toward
                  God; while, as for the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3025">Euphemia</persName>, she too accomplished thirty-five years in this course of
                  perfection, thirty in ministering to the saints, and five in the afflictions and
                  the conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of persecution,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a24" target="#n24" n="24"/> that is of martyrdom for
                     <persName>Christ</persName>'s sake. And her blessed daughter yet remained,
                  strengthened by the power of her blessing and of her prayer, while she too
                  followed closely in the footsteps of these saints, and began after them to take up
                  the strict course of their practices. </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-12">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-12.1" n="2"> The history of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3025">Euphemia</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1880">Mary</persName> the sisters is ended.
               </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 166, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>The ref. is to Acts, IX, 36 (see p. 174); but, as the word is in the
               absolute (<foreign>tabya</foreign>), not the emphatic (Tabitha), it must not be
               rendered as a proper name.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 166, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Constantina.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 166, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Gal., III, 28.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 167, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 167, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. ascetic exercises.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 168, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I cannot reconcile this with the statement above that she never passed a
               night outside the church.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 171, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Luke, XV, 17.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 172, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. if her face was covered.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 174, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 176, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I.e. to accept hospitality (?).</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 176, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., XXV, 29.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 177, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Either for relics or for the sacred vessles.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 177, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>A om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 178, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Affairs of business or charity? Or render <hi rend="singleQuotes">were
                  sending things to her</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 178, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Three loaves? Or three times as much as she ate?</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 179, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>James, V, 1.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 179, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 180, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Prov., XV, 12.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 181, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This must have been while John was living in Amida, i.e., between 530 and
               537 (see Introd.), and the story is with his usual carelessness misplaced, for the
               monks were not in exile at that time, and the persecution mentioned must appy. be
               that of 537.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 182, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., XXI, 13.</note>
                <note xml:id="n21" target="#a21" n="21">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 182, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>A similar story is told by John in H.E., II, 39.</note>
                <note xml:id="n22" target="#a22" n="22">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 183, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">as also</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n23" target="#a23" n="23">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 184, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">your house</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n24" target="#a24" n="24">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 186, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>If <hi rend="singleQuotes">ministering to the saints</hi> is to be taken
               literally, the 30 years must be dated from the persecution, and, if that of 537 is
               meant (p. 181, n.), her death would fall later than the composition of the book, so
               that we would probably have another instance of careless writing..</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
