<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/807">Two Monks</title>
                <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/806"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/808"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/807.xml -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-15" n="15">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-15">
                    <head type="main">Next the Fifteenth History, of <persName>Two Brothers</persName> From the Self-
                  Same Community, at the Same Time of Persecution.</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-15.1" n="1"> Great caution therefore is required of us, my brethren,
                  to provide that we may escape from the craftiness of the evil one, and again, that
                  we may fear the divine words (especially men who are highly reputed for modes of
                  life or for knowledge), when they caution us and say: <quote>Let him that standeth
                     take heed lest he fall</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>
                  For the sake then of cautioning those who are running on the road of virtue, I
                  have determined to commit to record an act also that is well worthy to be an
                  object of great commiseration which the <pb type="vol" n="221"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="221"/>fiends did to
                  two brothers who were in truth running with all their strength in the way of
                  virtue, and whom the fiends made such a laughing-stock that the like was never
                  heard among men of older or of recent times. These blessed men therefore, that is
                  one of them especially, who was called <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1933">James</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> – this man employed himself in a marvellous way in the
                  same community in great practices of standing and of watching and of abstinence
                  and great quietude; and he came from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1528">the convent called that of the
                     Edessenes</placeName> adjoining <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2736">Amida</placeName> itself.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> And
                  this brother was so laborious and humble and meek that these seven hundred men<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> were all amazed at his labours, and
                  at his asceticism; so that I also was with him on the weekly duties,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> and particularly marvelled at his
                  gentleness and his quietude, and further at the way in which he crucified his body
                  by night and by day. This man then had many who for the purpose of imitating his
                  modes of life used to attach themselves to him and keep themselves close to him.
                  And, while he was of <pb type="vol" n="222"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="222"/>this character, as God himself
                  knows, possessed persons were found to come outside the gate, and wail before him,
                  and say: <quote>
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1933">James</persName>
                     drives us out, and it is he who expels us</quote>. When he and many besides
                  heard these things, they continued laughing at these demons, and saying:
                     <quote>See these evil beings, how they deceive and mock</quote>. Then the great
                  seniors who were there, inasmuch as they knew the craftiness of the demons,
                  commanded that they should be driven from the place. But they contended the more
                  and said, <quote>
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1933">James</persName>
                     bound us and brought us here; and we cannot depart before he releases
                     us</quote>, while they had not seen <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1933">James</persName> at all. Then they came
                  in, and say to him: <quote>Release these fiend-possessed persons that they may go
                     hence, since they are pestering us</quote>. But he crossed himself, and said:
                     <quote>What is it that you say, my brethren, since I do not understand
                     it?</quote> But they continued in the same way to press him to go out and make
                  the sign over them, saying: <quote>Perhaps these souls will receive
                     deliverance</quote>. While he on his side continued declining and repudiating
                  this proposal, they on the other hand continued to press bim the more to do this,
                     <quote>that they may only <pb type="vol" n="223"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="223"/>depart hence</quote>. And,
                  when under great pressure he went out, these persons saw him, and began to foam;
                  and he came up and made the sign over them, and immediately these persons were
                  healed from that hour, and they departed. And thenceforth a multitude used to
                  repair thither foaming, men and women, and boys and girls, and all ages; and from
                  that time he was under the necessity (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άνάγκη</foreign>) of
                  going out. But he on his side would go out to a certain small martyrs' chapel
                  outside the gate, and would fill it; and he would put them to silence and drive
                  them out one by one; and the persons from whom they came out no longer suffered
                  from them. And thus he would drive them out in countless numbers; and they would
                  come outside and cause annoyance, and cry out. And, if it was not in his power to
                  come out, he would send them an order to go and lie down in that martyrs' chapel
                  till he came out. And thus they would go away foaming, and would lie down there;
                  and, if he waited two days, none of them dared to stretch himself out or to remove
                  from the place till he came out. But, when the numbers of those who used to come
                  there and cause annoyance increased, there were agitations there against this
                  blessed man, both on the part of the inmates of his monastery <pb type="vol" n="224"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="224"/>and also on the part of others; and accordingly he wished to give up
                  this business, and could not, on account of the multitude who used to come. And in
                  consequence of such annoyances it became necessary (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άνάγκη</foreign>) for him to withdraw from the community; and so he withdrew
                  under the instigation (I believe) of the demons themselves, in company with the
                  other who was attached to him, and they set out, and went in the direction of
                     Hamimtha,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> to a certain village
                  called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2754">Beth Musika</placeName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> and they had a certain monastery
                  that was there given to them, and they resided in it. And in a similar way again
                  there also multitudes began to flock together to them; and then also the blessed
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1933">James</persName> would again
                  command them authoritatively, and by means of his word demons without number were
                  expelled. Then the evil one, who by means of his crafty tricks finds methods of
                  deceiving men, contrived a method of making a mockery of these blessed men. One
                  night, when the possessed persons were assembled there, there was also a certain
                  young woman there of whom he had taken possession, who was also of worldly
                     appearance.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> Her accordingly the
                  demons took, and they clothed <pb type="vol" n="225"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="225"/>her in awe-striking forms
                  of phantasmal<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> rays; and they led
                  her up and seated her on the bishops' throne (<foreign xml:lang="grc">θρόνος</foreign>), which is usually placed in the churches or in the chief
                  martyrs' chapels on the dais (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κατάστρωμα</foreign>) of the
                  altar. Then they filled the whole martyrs' chapel again with phantasmal<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> forms, as if forsooth they were
                  angels of God; and some of them flew away and entered the chapel<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> where the blessed men were sleeping;
                  and there also as well they emitted rays with the appearance of light, according
                  to the text <quote>maketh himself like an angel of light</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> And they roused the blessed men and
                  urged them to haste, hastily alarming them and saying, <quote>Take incense,
                     incense, and haste to the martyrs' chapel; for <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/624">the holy Mary the God-bearer</persName>
                     has been sent to you, with a great host of angels; and she has sent us for you,
                     come straightway</quote>. But the blessed men were terrified by the sight, not
                  perceiving the craftiness of the evil one; and they hurriedly took incense and
                  spices, and ran to the martyrs' chapel; and on entering they found the whole house
                  full of phantasmal<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> forms, in the
                  semblance forsooth of angels <pb type="vol" n="226"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="226"/>of brilliant light, and the
                  woman moreover sitting on the throne (<foreign xml:lang="grc">θρόνος</foreign>),
                  and a semblance of light flashing from her; and their wits were yet more taken
                  from them by reason of their agitation, and they fell on their faces. Then (it is
                  said) she that was sitting commanded them<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> to approach and raise them up; and the fiends approached and took hold
                  of their hands, and they say to them: <quote>Rise, for she has commanded you; and
                     approach, and make obeisance to her</quote>. And they on their part rose
                  smitten with fear and robbed of their wits by the sight; and they approached and
                  made obeisance on their faces, as if they supposed that they saw a genuine sight.
                  But that young woman, being unaware even herself of what had happened, spoke with
                  them (that is, the fiend spoke in her), and said to them: <quote>Come, approach
                     me, and fear not. I myself am <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/624">Mary the Mother of Christ</persName>; and my Son sent me to you, because he
                     saw your righteousness and your love toward him, and that you are perfect in
                     your modes of life; and he commanded me to ordain you, and that you should
                     receive the priesthood from me because of your virtuousness. But come approach
                     and receive it</quote>. But they, inasmuch as they supposed that they had in
                  truth been granted some heavenly privilege <pb type="vol" n="227"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="227"/>beyond other
                  men, approached, and bowed their heads; and she rose, and laid her hand upon the
                  heads of both of them, and said to them: <quote>You have both received from me the
                     presbyterate. You have been made presbyters, perform the functions of your
                     priesthood</quote>. When the fiends had done this, a sound of great laughter
                  was heard in the air (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άήρ</foreign>), since the demons
                  were saying, <quote>Those who used to drive us out have to-day become as they
                     supposed great</quote>. And at the same cry that girl was stripped of the
                  phantasms (<foreign xml:lang="grc">φαντασίας</foreign>), and it was found that it
                  was a girl who was a Greek who was sitting on the throne (<foreign xml:lang="grc">θρόνος</foreign>), and it was she who had done these things. When these men
                  saw what had happened to them and came to their senses, they continued beating on
                  their faces and saying: <quote>Woe to us! what has happened to us? Anything like
                     this deceit never happened to men before. What to do, we know not</quote>. But,
                  when they brought that young woman down from the throne (<foreign xml:lang="grc">θρόνος</foreign>), she continued laughing at them at the instigation of the
                  demon and saying: <quote>What has come to you? Why are you troubled?</quote> . But
                  they on their side resolved to find means of subjecting their case to the cure of
                  penitence; and they left that place, weeping and sobbing at what had <pb type="vol" n="228"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="228"/>happened to them, and they went down to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/762">Marde</placeName> to the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/50">John</persName> bishop of
                     <placeName>Thella</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/>
                  who ended his life in the conflicts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of
                  persecution for Christ's sake. And, when they informed him of the affair, even the
                  blessed man also marvelled at the wily, crafty artfulness of the rebellious evil
                  beings. But he received them, and laid upon them three years' penance, and then
                  they were to be admitted to communion. And from that time again they led even more
                  severe lives than before, with sorrow and tears, until they attained to their
                  former standing, and were admitted to the communion that is obtained by
                  absolution. These things which we have written we have not received through
                  hearsay, but they are all matters which were enacted in our knowledge and in our
                  presence and before our eyes,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> and
                  we have brought comparatively few of them to the record of writing on account of
                  the length of the narrative, that a man who is granted any gift may be especially
                  cautious against the craft of the adversary, who uses all artifices in plotting to
                  deceive. </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-15">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-15.1" n="2"> The history of <persName>two brothers</persName> from the
                  selſsame community at the same time of persecution is ended. </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 220, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I Cor., X, 12.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 221, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>The sentence is here broken off.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 221, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>B Marg. <hi rend="singleQuotes">All these are sons of Mar Eugenius the
                  Egyptian. Let him who reads pray for the sinner who restored it.</hi>
                </note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 221, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 214.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 221, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>The duties of the <foreign>hebdomadarii</foreign>; see p. 62, n. 2, and ch.
               35.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 224, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Hot spring or <hi rend="singleQuotes">hot bath</hi>; see 'Zach Rh.', XII,
               6.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 224, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>
                    <hi rend="singleQuotes">House of mosaic</hi>(?); cf. Theoph. Cont. p. 146,
               l. 7, where <foreign xml:lang="grc">μουσικός</foreign> has this meaning.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 224, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>This seems to mean <hi rend="singleQuotes">smartly dressed</hi>; cf. ch.
               44.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 225, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Of <foreign xml:lang="grc">φαντασία</foreign>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 225, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Lit. <hi rend="singleQuotes">house of service</hi>. i. e. the private chapel
               of monastery, different from the martyrs' chapel (<hi rend="singleQuotes">house of
                  martyrs</hi>). At p. 204 also we find monks sleeping in the chapel.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 225, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>II Cor., XI, 14.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 225, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Of <foreign xml:lang="grc">φαντασία</foreign>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 226, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. the demons.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 228, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Constantina. John's life is given below (ch. 24). See Severus, Selected
               Letters, V, 14, 15, from which it appears that he was not at Marde after 527 (see p.
               395 ad fin. and transl., p. 358, note).</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 228, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>I cannot reconcile this with the fact that the central event happened in a
               distant monastery. Moreover the word (text, p. 226, l. 3) indicates that the author
               is not speaking at first hand.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
