<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/810">A Monk who Left the Monastery</title>
            <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/809"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/811"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/810.xml -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-18" n="18">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-18">
               <head type="main">Next the Eighteenth History, of a Certain Brother Who Left A Convent Without
                  Being Released,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> and Betook Himself
                  to Another.</head>
               <ab xml:id="section-18.1" n="1"> If therefore I cover with silence a sentence that was
                  pronounced in a terrible story which I saw,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> which was enacted in the case of one of the blessed brothers, I do not
                  think that I also shall be freed from the sentence of blame that proceeds from
                  justice. When formerly the community of those who had been everywhere expelled on
                  account of the faith were celebrated, and the spiritual community of the diocese
                  of <placeName>Amida</placeName>, that of these greatbl convents, were gathered
                  together in great numbers in the village of <placeName>Ḥzyn</placeName> in
                  <placeName>Ṭyšfʾ</placeName>, as we have indeed recorded these matters in one
                  of the histories,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> and blessed men
                  from everywhere desired to join that spiritual unity, and the blessed men did not
                  keep their door shut, but received everyone, it happened that a certain <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1932">blessed man</persName>
                  <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> came thither, who by his habit
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) <pb type="vol" n="261"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="261"/>was an
                  anchorite, and this man desired to be received in one of the convents in
                  obedience,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> and remain. And on
                  his tendering this request to one of the blessed archimandrites he examined him as
                  to his monastic training, and if he were in any other obedience, or barred by any
                  impediment. But that <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1932">blessed
                     man</persName>
                  <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> on seeing the
                  thoroughness of that examination was afraid to confess that he had not been
                  released, lest he should fail to obtain what he desired and not be received; and
                  therefore he said that he had been released from his monastery, when he had not
                  been released; but as if by the grace of God, which knew the sentence that
                  threatened that wretched man, it<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/>
                  caused him to state the name of his monastery without falsehood.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> And thus he was received, and
                  entered the convent in obedience. At that time a great pestilence broke out;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> and, as commonly happened, many died
                  there from that community, insomuch that eighty-four men from the convents
                  themselves, besides guests, died there, and were laid in the grave. And after
                  twenty days the lot reached the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1932">blessed man</persName>
                  <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> who had
                  been received; and he was. <pb type="vol" n="262"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="262"/>suddenly smitten, and was
                  struck dumb, while his soul was convulsed and snorts proceeded from his throat,
                  and he was bereſt of his senses and was in torture, not being among the dead or
                  among the living. And, whereas it was the custom, when the end was overtaking a
                  man and he was in great pain, for five or ten to meet together, and set down
                  incense and make propitiation for him for the other transgressions, and, if he
                  were still in pain, they would bring the holy gospel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">εύαγγελιον</foreign>) and lay it upon him, and immediately he would be
                  released either to life or to death, this poor man, in order that the text,
                  <quote>The word of God is living and doeth all things, etc.</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> might be understood by actual facts,
                  gained no release when the blessed men met together and made petition and prayer
                  and much incense and many forms of propitiation. And the Lord of the world<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> even came and relics of the saints,
                  and there was no release, nor relaxation from that intense, terrible, painful
                  convulsion for ten days, insomuch that a hundred and twenty men were thus ranged
                  round him, and were standing and marvelling, and weeping and <pb type="vol" n="263"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="263"/>distressing themselves at the agitation of that soul, and at that
                  terrible and violent driving; and from distress and grief they sat thus round him
                  two and three days, marvelling and weeping, and not eating or drinking, and
                  despising all human life. But, when it had lasted ten days, Grace in accordance
                  with its mercy effected deliverance, that is, the release of that agitated soul,
                  when on the tenth day all the seniors had met together and had stationed
                  themselves round him with the Lord of the world,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> and prayers and petitions and copious tears, while all
                  who were standing there cried with affliction and said: <quote>Lord, great is thy
                     mercy. Sufficient is this torture for this man. Let thy mercy persuade thee on
                     his behalf, God who carest for thy creation</quote>. The. chief of the seniors,
                  while standing over him and weeping, was saying these words, while my wretchedness
                  also was standing and forming part of that sorrowful gathering and hearing him say
                  in the midst of his sobs: <quote>What to do to you, afflicted man, we know not, in
                     order to ask you <quote>Is it because<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> you are conscious in your soul of grievous delinquencies that you
                        are dying and departing from life, and only torture remains for you in the
                        bodily life?</quote>, and <pb type="vol" n="264"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="264"/>to say <quote>Is there
                        an impediment upon you and is your soul bound by it?</quote>. Who will
                     inform us of this, unless the abụndant mercy of your Creator have pity on
                     you?</quote>. Then again, as if by divine instigation, the other senior who was
                  standing at the other side of his bed said: <quote>I, sir, think that this
                     agitation of this soul is an impediment proceeding from the word of
                     God</quote>. And, when he had said this, like one who is suddenly struck by his
                  neighbour and roughly dragged out of deep sleep, he was smitten with stupefaction
                  and suddenly quivered and nodded his head once. And, everyone being astounded, the
                  senior again repeated: <quote>Is there an impediment upon you, agitated
                     one?</quote>, and Grace caused him again to nod his head once, while his eyes
                  dried up and there was nothing to show even that they existed. Then the blessed
                  men deliberated: <quote>Even if this man is already a dead man, yet the divine
                     grace has let us know that his soul is impeded by the word of God; and what
                     shall we do? If we were accepted as ourselves making the release in place of
                     the man who laid the bond, we have done so many times. But come now let us
                     fetch a man, and let us all stand sureties in him that, God willing, we will
                     send a petition to his archimandrite to release <pb type="vol" n="265"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="265"/>him.
                     Perhaps the merciful God will accept us, and release him from this
                     torture</quote>. And, when they had determined upon these things, a certain
                  deacon whose name was Addai rose, and came and knelt before his bed, and said:
                  <quote>If God be willing to grant me life till I go and make the release, I
                     will under the security of all my fathers take this soul's impediment upon
                     myself</quote>. And, as the words that came from the mouth of that <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1932">blessed man</persName> ended, then the
                  release and the departure of that soul from its body also took place; and there
                  was a great and terrible and mighty cry, while everyone was amazed and praised
                  God. And so the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1932">blessed
                     man</persName> exerted himself and travelled rapidly, and fulfilled his
                  promise; and on the tenth day that agitated man was buried, while all marvelled
                  and wondered at the things that had happened. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-18">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-18.1" n="2"> The history of a certain brother who left a monastery
                  without being released and betook himself to another is ended. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 260, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>BH <hi rend="singleQuotes">his rule (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κανών</foreign>) having been relaxed</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 260, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Sic syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 260, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>Ch. 14; cf. ch. 35. The date is 522-526 (See Introd.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 260, n. 4</orig>
               </choice>BH <hi rend="singleQuotes">brother</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 261, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>I.e. as an inmate, not as a guest.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 261, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>BH <hi rend="singleQuotes">brother</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 261, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>Sic syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 261, n. 4</orig>
               </choice>The rule had been lightened since Severus' time, when a monk was free to
               leave his monastery at any time (<title>Sel. Letters</title>, p. 451).</note>
            <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 261, n. 5</orig>
               </choice>This clearly cannot be the great plague of 542, but must be an earlier
               epidemic not otherwise known.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 262, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Hebr., IV, 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 262, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>The scribes of BH (or the scribe of the archetype of B and H) appy.
               understood this to mean the gospel (see p. 263, n.); but the consecreated elements
               must surely be intended.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 263, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>BH <hi rend="singleQuotes">gospel</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 263, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Ms. om.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
