<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/819">Susan</title>
                <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/818"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/820"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/819 -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-27" n="27">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-27">
                    <head type="main">Next the Twenty-Seventh<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> History,
                  of a Blessed Virgin of <persName>Christ</persName> Whose Name Was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2092">Susan</persName>.</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-27.1" n="1"> The strong power of <persName>Christ</persName> who is
                  God therefore, which is wont to be glorified and displayed in human weakness in
                  order that no flesh. may boast before him',<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> this strengthener of the weak is wont to display its operation not only
                  through men of great size or mighty strength, but also in weak, feeble, powerless
                  women, insomuch that it gives them such force and courage that they show mighty
                  valour in fight not only <hi rend="singleQuotes">with flesh and blood</hi> (or <pb type="vol" n="542"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="340"/>with insidious passions and the enticements of fleshly
                  lusts and so on), <quote>but against principalities (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρχας</foreign>) and authorities, and against the rulers of the world of
                     this darkness, and against evil spirits under heaven</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> so that against these they show
                  mighty prowess and mock at them as a mighty man mocks at a party of babes and
                  sucklings who make themselves ready and come to fight with him. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-27.2" n="2"> For this also was declared to us through the most wise
                  Paul in that he says: <quote>In <persName>Christ Jesus</persName> is no male nor
                     female, nor bond nor free</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> So therefore this holy woman valiant in <persName>Christ</persName>, in that
                  she astonished me by her appearance and speech and strength in God, did not seem
                  to me to be in any way out of place in the series of histories of the saints, with
                  whom she also is pressing to enter by the same narrow gate,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> as she has indeed already entered. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-27.3" n="3"> This blessed woman, as by inquiry we succeeded in
                  learning accurately from her, was by her birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/285">Arzun</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> of the
                  Persians. And, when this woman was a girl of eight, that is of high family
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>), from her <pb type="vol" n="543"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="341"/>very beginning the light of her life rose in her mind, until men marvelled at
                  her sorrow and modesty and devoutness; and her name given her by her <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3706">parents</persName>, as by way of prophecy,
                  was <quote>blessing</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> who
                  truly received a heavenly blessing. This virtuous woman formed the plan of going
                  and worshipping in the holy places in which the salvation of our life was
                  effected, and she continued asking her <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3706">parents</persName>' leave, and they would
                  laugh at her childhood and say: <quote>You have not yet learned to interpret,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> and do you wish to go to
                        <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/104">Jerusalem</placeName>?</quote>, but she on her part was silent and kept it in her
                     heart.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> And<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> in the same days she prayed and said: <quote>Lord, if
                     thou wishest for the life of my wretched soul, make thy way straight before
                        me<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> and provide an escort for
                     me, and save my soul from the stain of the hateful mire of this world</quote>.
                  Then the child, as she herself would repeat to us, when I pressed her much, placed
                  her soul in the Lord's hands and fled. And after traversing three or 
                  four<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> miles she found 
                        a large <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3658">party</persName> of 
                            women <pb type="vol" n="544"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="342"/>and men travelling along the road 
                        to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/104">Jerusalem</placeName>; and, having joined
                  them and made inquiries and learnt it, she rejoiced and would exult and praise
                  God, and would say: <quote>Blessed am I, for the Lord has vished for my salvation,
                     and has answered me according to my petition. And far be it from me henceforth
                     to return for the world or for kin (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>),
                     or for <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3706">parents</persName>, and
                     die. But I am going to him that led me, and he himself will be to me father<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> and brother, and Lord and Saviour
                     in both worlds</quote>. And thus she reachedmon <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/104">Jerusalem</placeName> with joy; and, when
                  she had worshipped there, and her <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3660">companions</persName> desired to go back, they continued requesting her to
                  return with them as being a countrywoman, saying, <quote>We will not leave you in
                     this country</quote>. But she separated from them, and they did not see her
                  again. And she made inquiries to find a monastery in which to live; and she
                  learned that there was a large <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3049">women's monastery</placeName> betwen <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/674">Ascalon</placeName> and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/87">Gaza</placeName>; and thither she directed
                  her steps; and she made her wish know to the portress. And, since that <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3049">monastery</placeName> was severe (?),<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> that old woman said to her:
                     <quote>You, my daughter, cannot live here, since you are a girl, and you cannot
                     bear <pb type="vol" n="545"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="343"/>burdens and labours; and moreover also your own
                     delicacy is unsuited for a monastery</quote>. But the devout woman because she
                  was a stranger and in a strange country was distressed; and she remained sitting
                  before the gate and weeping for seven days, while they tried to drive her away and
                  she did not move. Then, after they had learned that she was a stranger, they
                  received her; and she came in, while they looked down upon her tender years. And,
                  when they learned from what country to what country she had come, they would say
                  to her as if distressed over her, <quote>What profit was it to you, my daughter,
                     to come out and ruin your soul in the mire. of sin in this way? Who is there
                     whom, if he were to see that you are so young, and especially that you are
                     alone, Satan would not set upon you even against his will, to ruin you before
                     your day?</quote> But she, as the blessed women who were with her would relate
                  that they had originally learned from her, would say:<quote> For our Lord's sake
                     pray for me; since I hope in him to whom I have committed myself that he has
                     not suffered me to be ruined, and will not suffer me</quote>. And so (she said)
                  they gave thanks to God. But she from that time began to follow great modes of
                  life, and austere practices of labours and abstinence and devoutness, though they
                     <pb type="vol" n="546"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="344"/>tried to prevent her and used to smite her on account
                  of her childish age, that she might not apply herself to these things more than
                  all the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3662">sisters</persName>; and she
                  on her side would increase them the more; so that she would go for two and three
                  days at a time, and then eat lentils only, and she would keep a whole night's
                  vigil standing in a corner (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γωνία</foreign>); and no
                  single word from her mouth would be uttered to human beings all day unless it was
                  demanded, while none of her <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3660">companions</persName> saw her face openly or the whole of the inside of her
                  eye from the time that she entered that <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3049">monastery</placeName>, and no laughter came
                  out of her mouth. When they saw the blessed woman's ways of life, that in
                  proportion as they strove to prevent her on the ground of her tender years she on
                  her side went on adding to this serious demeanour for a year and two years, then
                  her that they had despised as a child they now regarded as a venerable woman; and
                  she herself had also changed her name before entering the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3049">monastery</placeName>, lest any of her kin
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) should come and make inquiries and
                  discover her; and she took the name of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2092">Susan</persName>. When she had been
                  practising these habits for about ten years, a persecution was set on foot against
                  their <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3049">monastery</placeName> to make
                  them either submit<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> or quit.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/>
                        <pb type="vol" n="547"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="345"/>Since it was a large and celebrated convent, the
                  majority of them were detained and conformed, and some were scattered this way and
                  that. But the blessed woman was pressed by two alternatives, one of removing from
                  the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3049">monastery</placeName>, and the
                  other of falling into the evil faith. Then she resolved to leave, and go into the
                  desert beyond <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>, and live there. And she left at once, while a great
                  division arose even among those who had submitted in that they said, <quote>Now
                     that <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2092">Susan</persName> has left,
                     neither will we stay</quote>. But of the leading women who had not conformed
                  five of them<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> attached themselves to
                  her, while she was prepared to go alone; and these would say to her : <quote>It is
                     impossible for us to be separated from you</quote>. But she, after she had been
                  compelled, revealed her intention to them, saying: <quote>Do not come with me;
                     since for my part, to put it shortly, if the Lord prosper me as he is wont to
                     do, I am going to the desert</quote>. But they also as well stated their
                  determination, <quote>We too will go with you to the desert</quote>. And, when
                  they refused to give way, they embarked on a ship and crossed to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>. And the blessed
                  woman heard a report of a place in the desert beyond <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2819">the house of Mar Menas</placeName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/> and she directed her steps thither,
                     <pb type="vol" n="548"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="346"/>it being about two miles from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2820">a village named Mendis</placeName>; which
                  finally became the abode of the blessed Syrians,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/> but took its beginning from the blessed woman.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/> And there was there a tower that had
                  been erected for protection against barbarians; and the other five also went in
                  with virtuous zeal, and they took up their abode in it. And one of them went in
                  and obtained material for work for them from that village; and thus they laboured
                  with their hands for their necessities and supported themselves; and God took care
                  of them, who saw their zeal and their trust in him. Now there was a cave outside
                  that tower in the desert that had been dug in the earth underneath; and once there
                  had been a certain blessed man in it. And, having passed beyond human habitation,
                  she was proceding further and going to and fro in the desert and praying; and on
                  her walk she went and discovered that cave; and immediately she threw herself
                  inside it without her <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3660">companions</persName> or anyone else being aware of it; and she took no food
                  or anything. And thenceforth like that which is written of Ishmael the son of
                  Abraham, that he lived in the desert of Paran and was there instructed <pb type="vol" n="549"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="347"/>in the bow,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a21" target="#n21" n="21"/> so it
                  would be fitting to say of this woman also that she lived in a cave in the desert,
                  and was instructed in struggles and acts of valour against powerful demons, who
                  show the power of their wickedness more especially in the desert. But her
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3660">companions</persName>, when a
                  day and two days passed and she did not come, sat night and day in bitter distress
                  and weeping, while they said, <quote>She in reliance upon whom we came hither has
                     deserted us and departed</quote>. And, when again about ten days had passed,
                  some persons from that village learned about it, and they came to the blessed
                  women to learn the facts. And, when they saw the sorrow and the weeping of the
                  blessed women, they thought, <quote>Has she perhaps gone down into the cave in the
                     desert?</quote> And, inasmuch as they knew the place, they set out and went to
                  that cave; and they looked in and saw the blessed woman lying on her face and
                  crying aloud; and they spoke to her. And she, inasmuch as she supposed that they
                  were the fiends, who had displayed fearful and horrible shapes before her there,
                  was not frightened out of crying in prayer. But they, when they saw that she did
                  not answer them, left her; and they went and informed her <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3660">companions</persName>; and so they all ran
                  to that cave; and they found the blessed woman in the same position, <pb type="vol" n="550"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="348"/>kneeling and praying; and with difficulty, when they had spoken
                  many words to her, was she brought to believe that it was they, since the day
                  before also demons had clothed themselves in their shapes and come to her to
                  dislodge her from that place. And they, while weeping, continued making this
                  entreaty to her, saying: <quote>You know that it was in reliance upon you after
                     our Lord that we came out to this desert; and now wherefore do you seek to
                     destroy all our souls, and be yourself alone saved? and know you not that we
                     without you cannot exist?</quote> But the valiant woman addressed them weeping
                  with her head bowed downwards : <quote>Leave me, my <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3662">sisters</persName>; and now I am with
                     you always; but, since the Lord has prepared this place for me in which I have
                     had the opportunity of being at peace, go and keep quiet; and every first day
                     of the week one of you shall come and see me whether I am alive or
                  dead</quote>. But they, in order that she might come with them, set upon her to
                  lift her up and were unable to do so. Again after these things they demanded from
                  her a sure promise, lest she should depart even from that place also and not let
                  them know; and she gave them the promise. And again they continued begging her
                  that they <pb type="vol" n="551"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="349"/>might make a little dish of lentils and bring
                  it her, inasmuch as it was now ten days that she had not tasted anything. But she
                  on her side refused even to hear of it, saying: <quote>You seek to concern
                     yourselves about my food, while I am lying flat on my face, and to make me eat
                     the sweat of your faces, far be it from me! But for the support of my body it
                     is enough that you bring me a jar of water on the first day of the week, and
                     one cake (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παξαμάς</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a22" target="#n22" n="22"/> of bread a day</quote>. And thus they did for her
                  for three years. But, after the fame of the blessed women had been heard
                  everywhere, and moreover where they lived, many persons would come to them from
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>, and from
                  the villages of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2810">Libya</placeName>,
                  and further afterwards a great old man, who also with his disciples, about ten of
                  them, was a neighbour of their monastery in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/698">Palestine</placeName>, and, when they had
                  been much persecuted, and driven from one place to another, when he learned where
                  these blessed women were, and also about the quietude and pleasantness of that
                  desert, set forth and directed his steps thither with his disciples, one of whom
                  was brother of her who had been made head of the same blessed women, who <pb type="vol" n="552"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="350"/>also was a man of marvellous modes of life, whose name
                  was Samuel; and the name of the old man himself was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3234">Maro</persName>; and the old man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3234">Maro</persName> was by birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) an Amidene, while his disciple Samuel with his
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3662">sister</persName> came from the
                  neighbourhood of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>.
                  And, when they arrived, the blessed women on their side received comfort from
                  their presence, and the men too rejoiced, and they gave thanks to the Lord that
                  they were gratified with the quiet of the desert. And thereupon they began to
                  plant a cell in that desert, and others moreover came thither, of some of whom a
                  record has been set down by us in one of the preceding histories.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a23" target="#n23" n="23"/> And that place was colonized, while
                  the blessed women also were among them. Accordingly they formed a plan of
                  preparing a separate place for them, in order not to give occasion for evil
                  speaking among persons outside; and on account of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2092">Susan</persName> they did not like to
                  speak lest she should be offended.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a24" target="#n24" n="24"/>
                  But she was occupied with the same thought, <quote>Now that God has brought his
                     bondmen to this place, neither is it possible for those of our female sex
                        (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) to pass their lives among them
                     (since the evil one's attack <pb type="vol" n="553"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="351"/>upon saints is generally
                     made through women even when they are absent, how much more therefore in their
                     presence!), even if so be we<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a25" target="#n25" n="25"/>
                     continue to run with caution after spiritual things. But now let us withdraw
                     into the desert beyond this</quote>. While the blessed men were ashamed on
                  account of the saint's serious character, she herself addressed them in these
                  words; and when they heard it they gave thanks to God; and they undertook to build
                  and prepare for them a place in the vicinity of that village, while she herself
                  intended to move farther up country; and they stood up and opposed her, saying:
                     <quote>For you, mother, in a city, if you dwell in it, it is a desert to
                        you;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a26" target="#n26" n="26"/> but look at these souls
                     who are hanging upon you<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a27" target="#n27" n="27"/>
                        </quote>. Then she gave way to them; and they built an enclosed monastery for
                  them and a tower inside it; and they took up their abode in it. But the blessed
                  woman through strength proceeding from Grace received mighty power over fiends,
                  since they would thenceforth set themselves in array against her night and day in
                  the form (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τύπος</foreign>) of human beings, and they would
                  come against her with all varieties of weapons; and she like a strong man who <pb type="vol" n="554"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="352"/>despises the sickly men who threaten him would mock at
                     them.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a28" target="#n28" n="28"/> And the fame of her
                  strength was heard everywhere, so that the fame of her perfection instigated us
                  also to see her as well as the holy men who were there, fifteen years after she
                  had settled in the same desert.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a29" target="#n29" n="29"/>
                  And, when we had been privileged to see her that I do not like to name a woman, I
                  was amazed at the words of solemn feeling and of the wisdom of God that proceeded
                  from her mouth during the space of more than twenty days that I was with these
                  saints, going and coming, in order to hear her speech and her delightful
                  conversation; and I was unable to see her head held erect, or a feature of her
                  face (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>) except the tip of her nose only;
                  so sorrowful was she and tearful. And she took upon herself to speak to us about
                  this world how it is in the grasp of error, and how men see their fellows rotting
                  and decaying and putrefying within graves, and the loathsome worm creeping about
                  in the midst of their putrefying remains, and they who see these things are led
                  astray by the vanities of this false world, and how again the thought of the
                  rapidly-approaching terrible hour of the dissolution of this world does <pb type="vol" n="555"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="353"/>not rise in men's hearts, and that they are about to
                  stand before the terrible judgment-seat (<foreign xml:lang="grc">βήμα</foreign>)
                  ol God, saying, <quote>It is a great absurdity that we hear of the pit of fire,
                     and the abysses of flame, and the darkness, and the rest of the torments, and
                     we do not lay it to heart and ask mercy while we have the opportunity as a
                     means of escaping from these things</quote>. This divine woman would repeat in
                  our presence many things yet more terrible than these, and we were brought into a
                  state of great wonder at her speech. Then there was given to her also the gift of
                  healing, so that every infirmity or disease upon which she stretched out her hand
                  was healed. While we were there, a certain great and God-loving blessed man was
                  living in a place in the desert that was not far from them; and the fiends used
                  openly to set themselves in array against him; and he used to see their struggle
                  with the blessed woman. and she his. But, since she was stronger than he, she both
                  prevailed and had no fear whatever of the fiends, and she had become firm and
                  immoveable like adamant, insomuch that the demons themselves used to cry to her,
                     <quote>This is a woman, but she has become stone, and from flesh iron</quote>.
                  These things the demons used to say to her. And, <pb type="vol" n="556"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="354"/>inasmuch as she was so firm, that blessed man, whenever the visions pressed hard
                  upon him, used to come to her as to a strong person; and while I was there, he
                  came, stricken and smitten in his mind and perturbed. And when she saw him she
                  understood; and she asked him <quote>Why are you distressed, father?</quote> But
                  he continued saying: <quote>The fiends have been mighty and have taken away my
                     wits, since the whole week we have been more than ordinarily involved in a
                     struggle; and this night and day they showed me terrible sights of fear, and my
                     heart was shaken and my wits were taken away and I was confounded; and from
                     fear I fled; and I am afraid to enter my cell on account of the sights that I
                     saw. And now I will leave that place</quote>. She on hearing it shook her head,
                  saying: <quote>Come see persons that are called men, and not only men but also
                        <persName>Christ</persName>'s bondmen. Is it right that you should be called
                        <persName>Christ</persName>'s bondmen? You have in this way reckoned
                        <persName>Christ</persName> your Lord to be feeble, and by your own frailty
                     have made the mighty and invincible power of <persName>Christ</persName>, which
                     cast down and overthrew and brought to naught all the power of Satan, appear
                     less than that of the fiends, so that <persName>Christ</persName> now seems to
                     be a runaway and one that <pb type="vol" n="557"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="355"/>can be overcome by the
                     demons, and they are found to be strong and vanquishers of the power of God.
                     How are you a disciple of him who said: <quote>Ye shall trample on all the
                        power of the enemy</quote>?<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a30" target="#n30" n="30"/>
                            <!-- There seems to be an extra inverted comma in Brooks. --> You have
                     distressed me by causing the fiends to rejoice. If necessary, were it not for
                     other reasons,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a31" target="#n31" n="31"/> you should only
                     last night have been hearing the shapes<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a32" target="#n32" n="32"/> and voices of the struggles of the demons which they showed me, and
                     have been marvelling<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a33" target="#n33" n="33"/> at them.
                     And for my part I know that the Lord's power surrounds my weakness like a wall
                     of bronze, and there is no other power that can resist it</quote>. While the
                  weak woman was boldly saying these words in our presence, we looked at one
                  another, while she did not see either of us. Then she said confidently to the
                  blessed man: <quote>In the name of the Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> rise
                     and return to your cell; and he as his custom is will make all the power of the
                     evil one weak before you</quote>. But the blessed man, being struck with shame
                  at the woman's words and trembling greatly from his shame, consented to go. And,
                  when <pb type="vol" n="558"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="356"/>we had risen up from before her and were speaking
                  and expressing astonishment at her spiritual strength and her courage, I said to
                  him: <quote>How is it that this blessed woman's face (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>) is not visible?</quote> He on his side said to me:
                     <quote>One day while we were speaking I said to her <quote>For what reason do
                        you hide your face from us?</quote> And she made oath to me, saying:
                        <quote>He who by his grace laid his yoke upon me knows, our brother, that
                        since I took his yoke upon me, which is to day twenty-five years ago, I have
                        not seen a man's face (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>), and do
                        you desire me to see yours now?</quote>, and I on my side said to her:
                        <quote>For our Lord's sake tell me the truth. Are you for your part afraid
                        lest you should yourself suffer harm from the sight of a man, or lest he
                        should suffer harm from the sight of you?</quote> And she said <quote>For
                        both reasons</quote>.</quote> And thus in astonishment at the saint's habits
                  of life and the endurance of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2092">Susan</persName> the virgin of <persName>Christ</persName> we departed from
                  that place, praising God. </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-27">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-27.1" n=""> The history of a blessed virgin of
                  <persName>Christ</persName> whose name 
                  was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2092">Susan</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a34" target="#n34" n="34"/> 
                  is ended. </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 339, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Mss. om.; see Introd., p. X.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 339, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>I Cor., I, 29.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 340, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Eph., VI, 12.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 340, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Gal., III, 28.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 340, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., XIII, 24.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 340, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Arzanene.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 341, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. Eulogia.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 341, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. writing, i.e. to read(?). To make the meaning clearer the scribe of B
               has inserted (speech).</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 341, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Luke, II, 19.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 341, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>The scribe of B has inserted <hi rend="singleQuotes">about 7 years
                  afterwards</hi>, probably because the notion of a child of 8 setting off alone for
               Jerusalem staggered him, though he thereby makes the words <hi rend="singleQuotes">in
                  the same days</hi> meaningless. That she was really only 8 is scarcely credible,
               and is probably one of the author's loose statements.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 341, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>Ps. V, 9.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 341, n. 6</orig>
                    </choice>B '4'. V. D. and L. wrongly <hi rend="singleQuotes">quadraginta</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 342, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>B ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">and mother</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 342, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>This is appy. the meaning of here, as V. D. and L. and P. Smith take it; but
               the word expresses size of intensity, and, though it is not infrequently applied to
               ascetic practices in the sense of 'severe', it is a great stretch of language to use
               it of a monastery in which severe asceticism is practiced. In ch. 58 (f. 133 v'b) it
               is applied to a monastery in the sense of 'extensive'; but it seems out of place
               there.</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 344, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>B ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">to the implicity of Chalcedon</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 344, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>519 (sce. p. 352, n. 2). The persecution in Palestine probably began sooner
               than in Mesopotamia, where Monophysites were in a large majority.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 345, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 345, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 209, n.2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 346, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 190. At p. 209 the desert of Mendis is said to be 12 miles from Mar
               Mensas.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 346, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>B <hi rend="singleQuotes">women</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n21" target="#a21" n="21">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 347, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Gen., XXI, 20, 21.</note>
                <note xml:id="n22" target="#a22" n="22">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 349, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Bread twice cooked like our biscuit, and therefore hard and capable of being
               kept a considerable time. The meaning perh. is that they were to bring 7 cakes every
               Sunday.</note>
                <note xml:id="n23" target="#a23" n="23">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 350, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ch. 13.</note>
                <note xml:id="n24" target="#a24" n="24">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 350, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>She had therefore left the cave after the 3 years, and it seems likely that
               it was the same cave which Thomas of Amida afterwards occupied (p. 191), though it is
               there called a pit.</note>
                <note xml:id="n25" target="#a25" n="25">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 351, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>B 'they' (fem.).</note>
                <note xml:id="n26" target="#a26" n="26">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 351, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n27" target="#a27" n="27">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 351, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>B <hi rend="singleQuotes">like creepers on walls</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n28" target="#a28" n="28">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 352, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Cf. p. 340.</note>
                <note xml:id="n29" target="#a29" n="29">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 352, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>J.'s visit to Egypt was in 534 (see Introd., p. IV); hence we may place
               Susan's stay in Palestine from 509 to 519; see p. 344 to p. 356.</note>
                <note xml:id="n30" target="#a30" n="30">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 352, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>must come from root (<foreign>se movit</foreign>) which P. Smith gives to
               Neo-Syr. only (V. D. and L <hi rend="singleQuotes">
                        <foreign>arrepentos</foreign>
                    </hi>). P. S. refers to this passage under =
                  <foreign>insipidus</foreign>; but this makes no sense.</note>
                <note xml:id="n31" target="#a31" n="31">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 355, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Luke, X, 19.</note>
                <note xml:id="n32" target="#a32" n="32">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 355, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>B. om., probably because the scribe did not understand these very obscure
               words. For <hi rend="singleQuotes">you following B has 'I'.</hi>
                </note>
                <note xml:id="n33" target="#a33" n="33">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 355, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n34" target="#a34" n="34">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 355, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">would have marveleld</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n35" target="#a35" n="35">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 356, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
