<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/825">Hala</title>
                <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/824"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/826"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/825 -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-33" n="33">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-33">
                    <head type="main">Next the Thirty-Third History, of a Blessed Man Whose Name Was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1769">Hala</persName> the Zealous From the
                     <placeName>Monastery</placeName> Called That of the
                     <persName>Edessenes</persName>.</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-33.1" n="1"> This excellent blessed man therefore was thus called by a
                  name which was also completely fulfilled in him, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1769">Hala</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> the zealous, a man who was in truth zealous and humble
                  and ascetic and a teacher, and perfect in all the practices of religion. Now this
                  blessed man lived in one of the convents of the <persName>Amidenes</persName>
                        <pb type="vol" n="593"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="391"/>which is called that of the
                     <persName>Edessenes</persName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/>
                  and I was also in intercourse with him for a space of some years, and during the
                  days of my association with him I was with my whole soul thoroughly amazed at his
                  keen zeal and his strenuous course of life, and his constant energy and his
                  vigilance in every good work, and (that we may use an expression which sums up
                  all) in the fervour of his love toward God, and his humility and his zeal that
                  imitated that high one who by his humility taught the pattern (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τύπος</foreign>) of it to his disciples. This zealous man
                  therefore from the very beginning of his training chose for himself to perform all
                  the menial tasks required for the needs of his convent, and besides this he
                  resolved not to see a stranger enter the convent without associating himself in
                  careful attention to his wants; and thenceforth he was constantly engaged in this
                  pursuit all the day, being like a trader with many classes of merchandise, so
                  that, although his trade fail in one, he can spend money on another, that an
                  opportunity may be found for profit to come in, in that he never saw a poor man
                  come to the gate of his convent without imparting to his necessity if only some
                  small thing, or yet seeing a poor sick<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> man without associating himself in careful <pb type="vol" n="594"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="392"/>attention to his needs. So therefore one might see that this saint never ceased
                  bringing in profit, and every day the business of the spiritual trade was never
                  lacking to him, were it from strangers or from needy persons, or from sick persons
                  lying outside and without consolation from any quarter. And besides these things
                  he was constant in sweeping and washing the latrines (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σελλίας</foreign>?) of the momastery every day, and sweeping the whole
                     <placeName>monastery</placeName> and brushing away the ashes. And, when the
                  time came when he knew that the servitors<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> had put a cauldron on the fire to cook the dish and had cleansed the
                  herbs, he would go and sweep out the scullery, and take it<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> outside; and after taking it outside he would sit down
                  and collect the scouring, down to a little leaf only about a finger long that had
                  an animal in it, and he would wash it, and he would go in and beg of the
                  servitors, and they would give him a pot, and he would set it on the fire; and
                  further he would make entreaty of the steward, and he would give him a little oil,
                  and he would cook that rejected portion in such a way that a man would be
                  attracted by the mere smell of it, and that he would leave the choicest portion,
                  and eat of it; and he would go and ask for a little bread, <pb type="vol" n="595"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="393"/>and wine if any was to be had, and so he would take it out to the sick
                  and afflicted and needy persons lying by the gate. And on a day when the servitors
                  had no herbs he himself, in order not to trouble the gardeners, would go outside
                  or go into the garden, and he would pick a wild herb that was of no use and bring
                  it and make a dish and lentils<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> and
                  take it out to the poor people. And again, when he was sitting at table, he had
                  made a basket (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σπυρίδα</foreign>) and a jar, and it was
                  placed by him; and the greater part of what came to him he would put there, while
                  he was also the cause of others imitating him and themselves also putting their
                  cups into his jar and their portions into his basket (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σπυρίδα</foreign>); and he would take them secretly and carry them out to the
                  needy persons, and thus he would relieve many souls, and they would bless him out
                  of the whole of a perfect heart, and pray for him. And so he was constant in
                  following this course day and night, holding no conversation with men, except if
                  it was needed for the purposes of his service; but, when he was going out and when
                  he was coming in, a psalm never departed from his mouth; and, even if he was
                  speaking to someone, <pb type="vol" n="596"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="394"/>one word and the next the man would
                  see his lips move. And, if he ever had a moment during which he was resting from
                  the service of the saints, he had recourse to the Scriptures, so that, if a night
                  and a day was devoted to his reading without interruption, it was not enough to
                  satisfy him with reading; for he was very erudite in the Scriptures and in
                  doctrinal (?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> reading. And he had a
                  band of disciples; and at the conclusion of nocturns he would take his disciples,
                  and would go to the refectory, or wherever it might be, and so they would read and
                  recite the service till daybreak; and at daybreak he would eagerly betake himself
                  to his ministration, going out several times although he had nothing to take out,
                  and visiting the poor people lying at the gate before the time, and consoling and
                  comforting them; and so all the needy and strangers used to look out for the sight
                  of him, because that alone was enough to console them. But, as soon as they were
                  seated at the tables, he would rise and pretend to laugh 'as to how he alone was
                  to satisfy his need (?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> saying,
                     <quote>Who has anything to give <pb type="vol" n="597"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="395"/>to my Lord
                        <persName>Jesus</persName>? Is there anyone who has a morsel for the
                     fledglings of my Lord <persName>Jesus</persName>?</quote>, and he would make
                  many even secretly take and give him something, so much so that some of those in
                  authority were filled with resentment against him, saying, <quote>We have one gate
                     set up, that we may together look after everyone. Why do you go
                     outside?</quote> But he would listen and kept silence, or laughed with the man
                  whoever he might be, saying, <quote>Forgive me, sir. I went out and saw these
                     brothers of Lazarus. I went out and looked at the fledglings, and they are in
                     want of a morsel of food</quote>. And so he was at last assailed by reproaches
                  from all sides, but especially from the steward, since he used to trouble him
                  greatly and beyond measure, so that, if they assisted him, the steward had no
                  bread or wine, and the servitors no cooked food that reached mealtime without
                  having gone out to the gate. And accordingly they heaped indignation and abuse
                  upon him, and threw his cups and his plates to the ground. And he on his side
                  would be in no way angry or wrathful or annoyed and would say, <quote>Why is it
                     necessary that I should be abused?</quote> But sometimes too one of the
                  servitors or the steward would be vexed, and they would show indig<pb type="vol" n="598"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="396"/>nation against him; and he on his side would thus drink in everything
                  and put up with it, and laugh, so that his very patience would shame the man
                  whoever he might be; and he would by no means depart till he had supplied his need
                  from him, saying, <quote>I am grieved for my Lord <persName>Jesus</persName>,
                     because he is hungry and has no quarter whence to get food; otherwise I should
                     not be troubling you</quote>. And so he would receive it, and then depart. And
                  thus he would intently and eagerly look after the poor and the sick without
                  remission and without lassitude. And strangers who came in he would receive inside
                  and would refresh and wash and anoint them and would lay their rugs besides all
                  the other attentions, and they would lie down. And he himself would after a short
                  rest for his body go and stand all night in a corner (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γωνία</foreign>) and recite the service and take their clothes and give them
                  changes, and would scald and wash and darn and repair them, and so he would give
                  them to them; and for this reason they used to call him 'Mar so-and-so the
                  zealous. But after a period of some years during which the blessed man had been
                  devoting himself to this great ministration, there came the persecution which
                  disturbed everyone,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> and the
                  convents removed <pb type="vol" n="599"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="397"/>after all their property had been taken
                  from them, and the rest<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> stored in
                  certain places; and they no longer had an abundance of the things which their
                  needs required in everything. And the blessed man was much distressed at this,
                  because he possessed no changes of clothes for the strangers nor rugs; and he
                  would disregard the fact that they were themselves in distress, and vex himself
                  over the strangers; and accordingly he would contrive to obtain some worn-out old
                  coats, and wash and darn them; and he would go out to the dungheaps and pay no
                  attention to the jeers both of those inside and of those outside, and thus he
                  would collect rags and flocks of wool, and would bring them and washt hem, and cut
                  them up, and make cushions and fasten them together and lay them out; and when a
                  stranger came he would dismiss him<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/>
                  and lay a rug for him and make him lie down. And so he found this method of
                  carrying out his own employment, not giving up this strenuous pursuit in peace or
                  in persecution, in the city or in exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>). After a time he had a brother,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> and he continued pressing him to go and pray at
                  Ephesus; and he for his part was unwilling to do so, and his brother by urging him
                  induced him to set out and go. And, since he was <pb type="vol" n="600"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="398"/>weak<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> from the feebleness
                  caused by asceticism and moreover from the approach of old age, he fell into a
                  serious illness for a long time, and therefore, inasmuch as some blessed men among
                  the members of their <placeName>monastery</placeName> were in the royal city,
                     they<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> went up thither in order to
                  take the old man, and so he entered the community gathered together at that time
                  by the queen who<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> had been gathering
                  together persecuted men from all quarters and looking after them, in that they had
                  been placed by her in the palace (<foreign>παλάτιον</foreign>) called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2793">Hormisda</placeName>, where many distressed
                  and poor persons and strangers lay by the gate night and day.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> But the blessed man, when he saw
                  these, and an opening had been found for him also to give, thenceforth like a poor
                  man who loses one of his great possessions, and decides in his mind that it will
                  never be found again, and suddenly sees it and is astonished and glad, so was it
                  with this blessed man also,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> while
                  he thenceforth doubled the earlier work, first by the leavings that he got from
                  everyone and by his own portions (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μοίρας</foreign>), and
                  afterwards by the persistent effrontery (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χρώμα</foreign>)
                  with which he would ask everyone after they had been showing resentment and
                  indignation against him and saying: <quote>Mar so-and-so the zealous</quote>, and
                  so he would perfectly carry out all the ministration to the needy with <pb type="vol" n="601"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="399"/>superfluity, washing away the excrement of all that community
                  and bringing them water, though he held the rank of a presbyter. And, while it was
                  said there as it had been said before that he was a lover of vain glory and acted
                  on account of men, he alone as if unaware of it sought that one object, to relieve
                  persons in trouble, till everyone was astonished at him and they gave thanks to
                  God, to whom be glory and honour and worship to the Father and to the Son and to
                  the Holy Spirit now and always and for ever and ever Amen and Amen! </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-33">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-33.1" n="2"> The history of a blessed man whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1769">Hala</persName> the zealous from the
                  <placeName>monastery</placeName> called that of the
                  <persName>Edessenes</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/>
                  is ended. </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 390, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Hala = sweet; but appy. the propriety of the name applies only to the
               nickname <hi rend="singleQuotes">the zealous</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 391, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 221 and ch. 58 (f. 130 r' b).</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 391, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>H <hi rend="singleQuotes">sick or poor</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 392, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 62, n. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 392, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. the refuse.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 393, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 394, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Or <hi rend="singleQuotes">special</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 394, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>This is very obscure; and, as H omits the words, the scribe would seem to
               have been puzzled by it (see p. 355, n. 2. and Introd., p. VIII). V. D. and L.'s
               translation <hi rend="singleQuotes">ac si desiderium suum iam explevisset</hi> cannot
               be got from the text. The meaning appy. is that he could not get what was wanted
               without the help of others.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 396, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Since J. seems to have known him before the expulsion, the 2nd expulsion
               (536/7) must be meant.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 397, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 397, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. to the rest; see p. 402, l. 8.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 397, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 398, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 398, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Hala and his brother (?).</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 398, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 398, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>See ch. 47.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 398, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>Sic syr.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 399, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. <hi rend="singleQuotes">Mar Hala (his prayer be with us
               Amen!)</hi>.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
