<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/835">Tribunus</title>
            <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/834"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/836"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/835 -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-44" n="44">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-44">
               <head type="main">Next the Forty-Fourth History, of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3155">Tribunus</persName> Who in Habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) Was A Layman and a Count, but in the
                  Performance of Practices of Excellence Complete and Perfect.</head>
               <ab xml:id="section-44.1" n="1"> This excellent blessed man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3155">Tribunus</persName> therefore, who in a
                  lay station carried out spiritual practices, was by his birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from the district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/493">Sophanene</placeName>, from a village called
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2756">Beth Rwmntʾ</placeName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> a man who from an early age had been
                  taught religion, and was constantly occupied in fasting and prayer and constant
                  attendance in churches and monasteries with the great and excellent blessed men,
                  and used to hear and learn the psalms and the Scriptures, even as his parents also
                  set themselves to teach him to read and write Greek, and he besides Greek learned
                  Syriac also,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> and meditated, as it
                  is written, <quote>on the law of the Lord day and night</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> While then he was constantly
                  occupied in reciting service and reading the Scriptures in Greek and Syriac, and
                  while his parents desired to yoke him in worldly intercourse with a wife, and
                  expected that he would also be their heir, because he was indeed their only child,
                  and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> advised him to take a wife,
                  as she had been <pb type="vol" n="662"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="460"/>betrothed and provided, he on his side
                  opposed, and he would answer his parents, saying, <quote>As for me why should I go
                     and fall into the turmoil of this world, and give material to sin and death? If
                     I indeed obey you, then I shall also be bound by the world and many sins, and,
                     if it happens that I beget children, they will be spoil for death, and I shall
                     again sit mourning for them</quote>; and the many other things which, as he
                  often repeated in our presence, he would answer to his parents, so that they were
                  reduced to great distress, because they saw that the devout young man so despised
                  the world and all that is in it; since indeed they relied upon riches, houses and
                  estates and lands, and male and female slaves, and saw that he who they thought
                  was heir of these things spurned and despised them, and would not consent to look
                  at them at all, but was constantly occupied with religion and spiritual
                  employment, and used to have recourse to saints who were stylites and recluses and
                  laboured in the excellent life, and attached himself to them, and was taught, so
                  that thenceforth they held him as a beloved son in all the convents, and
                  especially in the devout <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2778">convent of
                     Fyṭr</placeName> the devout and great blessed men <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">Habib</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName>, who shine at the
                  beginning of these histories<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> like
                  rays of light; so that after the decease of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3763">Habib</persName> the <pb type="vol" n="663"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="461"/>mighty in spiritual strength, when his perfect disciple <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName> at last earned the
                  privilege of succeeding him in the administration, and also of ascending the
                  pillar and accomplishing the course of his practices on it, and, when this blessed
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName> had for a
                  period of some years while in an earthly body been engaged in heavenly and sublime
                  employments on a column between earth and heaven, by the envy of the enemy of
                  righteousness a persecution was stirred up against him by those who honoured the
                  synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, and that so violent that they brought
                  the blessed man down from his pillar, and he was expelled with all his convent;
                  and he, when these things were inflicted upon him, without delay hastened to the
                  royal city to utter a reproof on account of these things, as have<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> been recorded by us at short length
                  in the histories relating to these things; and he took the devout <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3155">Tribunus</persName> with him in lay attire
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) as an interpreter of the Greek
                  tongue. And so he went up with him, and lived with his disciples and with him,
                  imitating their practices and occupied in spiritual employment; insomuch that he
                  was consequently desirous of being admitted to the devout monastic habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) also, and the blessed men would not allow him,
                  saying <quote>It is <pb type="vol" n="664"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="462"/>better both for you and for us that
                     you should go in and out of the city and the palace (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>) as a layman, and carry communications (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άποκρίσεις</foreign>) for us, and not go about the city clad
                     in the habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) and cause the habit
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) to be made an object of
                     mockery</quote>. And so he performed the service of the old man and of his
                  convent all the days of his<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> life,
                  insomuch that he gained easier entry and more freedom (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>), and they even thrust the office of a count on him under
                  constraint by his<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> command, saying,
                  <quote>This will be no impediment to your practices; and, when you wish, it is
                     easy for you to give up the office. But for the sake of our communications
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άποκρίσεις</foreign>) take it upon you</quote>. And
                  so under constraint he accepted an earthly employment, while the whole of his own
                  mind and energy was constantly occupied in heavenly employments and bound up in
                  them. When after some years during which he had served the blessed man the blessed
                  man departed from the world, then the excellent blessed man remained in the cell
                  in which he dwelt in the city, accomplishing the labour of his practices on a
                  great scale, having also added to his spiritual labours the extra labour of
                  hospitality and the relief of the poor, living and delighting also in voluntary
                  poverty, and rejoicing in it, so that, if it happened also that there was a
                  superfluity of anything <pb type="vol" n="665"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="463"/>in his cell, he would set
                  himself to scatter it among the needy. Since many of the chamberlains and of the
                  distinguished members of the senate (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σύγκλητος</foreign>)
                  were acquainted with him because of the blessed man,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> and moreover loved him on account of his venerable
                  manner of life, and used to beg him to do them the favour of dwelling with them,
                  or even only to stay with each of them, and to receive some gift from them, so
                  also he would flee and shrink as from the perpetration of an evil act, saying,
                  <quote>My sins are enough for me; and to share in other men's sins,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> or to refresh myself by the sweat
                     of others I will never consent</quote>. And so he was constant in maintaining a
                  life of retirement and the performance of righteous acts, though he had reached
                  old age, still hoping to attain the habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>), passing most of his days in this our convent and that of the
                  blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1524">Zʿura</persName>, while he
                  also practised handiwork for his needs, some carpentering; and moreover he made
                  partridge-cages (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κλωβός</foreign>) and sold them, and
                  gained his living, with his two slaves, who also served him devoutly; for, when
                  they went out to monasteries or anywhere, then they also continually practised
                  vigils and fasting and <pb type="vol" n="666"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="464"/>recitation of service and
                  constant prayers in company with all the members of the convent; and, when they
                  were remaining continuously in the cell, the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3155">Tribunus</persName> was constantly
                  occupied in the same way night and day, and what is especially deserving of
                  admiration is that he rejoiced in poverty and took pleasure in scarceness; so
                  that, if it happened that at any time he actually had a superfluity, he was much
                  displeased at this, and set himself to scatter and to spend his superfluity; so
                  that he took pleasure in scarceness, giving thanks. I wish therefore to set down
                  and place on record. something about a temptation of his and about the man's
                  courage and the conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) which he
                  sustained. This man then had once thought of changing his place of residence; and
                  he went out and was going round the mansions, looking for a tenement convenient
                  for him to live in; and, having found him<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> written and fixed up on the door of a certain mansion, he asked for the
                  porter (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όστιάριος</foreign>) to go up and show him the
                  tenement. And, since the porter (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όστιάριος</foreign>)
                  himself was not there, but as if by the opposition of Satan his wife was present,
                  who was a young woman and was very worldly in her appearance,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> she said to him <quote>Come with me
                     and I will myself show <pb type="vol" n="667"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="465"/>you the rooms that are
                     advertised</quote>. And, when she had taken the key (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κλείδα</foreign>) and gone up and opened them, they both went in. And, as he
                  was going round to look, while she on her side was displaying a snare of sin
                  before him, a sinful passion was aroused in her, and she went on madly laughing in
                  his face, while she also seized him, and began as if by the kisses of sin to grasp
                  him and entice him to fall with her. And, as he was rebuking her and flinging and
                  casting her hands off him, she on her side all the more as if by the machination
                  of the devil, who was desirous of catching the brave man by a snare, and setting a
                  blemish on his beauties and staining him, he<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> yet more entered into her, making her madly grasp the
                  blessed man, while she also threw herself in front of him to tempt him to
                  lasciviousness, intertwining herself with him with all the lasciviousness and
                  violence of impurity and adultery, using<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> foul words which we do not wish even to write down and pollute the ears
                  or mind of the hearer and record. But the man armed with the divine power flung
                  and threw her off and withdrew himself from her, reproving and rebuking her
                  sternly and saying, <quote>The Lord rebuke you, woman, and the fiend who clothed
                     you in so much shamelessness and wickedness that you should dare to defile the
                     path of <pb type="vol" n="668"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="466"/>intercourse with your husband, and hold
                     intercourse with another in violation of the law (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμος</foreign>), and think to stain me the sinner with you</quote>. And so
                  this brave man like <persName>Joseph</persName> the just fled and left that house
                  and all that neighbourhood in great trepidation, so that he would relate these
                  things to us and to many others, about the battle and conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) which he had, and about the machination of the
                  evil one who was bitter against the wise merchant in order to make spoil of his
                  merchandise. And so, being illustrious for the excellence of this manner of
                  living, he ended his life heroically, bearing good testimony, and he too as well
                  was laid in the sepulchre of our convent. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-44">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-44.1" n="2"> The history of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3155">Tribunus</persName> the count is ended.
               </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 459, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Perh. read <hi rend="singleQuotes">Rumane</hi> (pomegranates).</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 459, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Appy. his own language was Armenian.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 459, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>Ps. I, 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 459, n. 4</orig>
               </choice>Ms. om.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 460, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ch. 1. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 461, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sic syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 462, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sc. Zʿra's.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 462, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sc. Zʿra's.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 463, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Cf. p. 175.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 464, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>This was perh. used of any house where rooms were to be left; but in Bar
               'All (quoted in P. Smith. s. V. ) (<foreign>ostiarius</foreign>) is rendered
               (innkeeper).</note>
            <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 464, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>See p. 224, n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 465, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sc. the devil. Sic syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 465, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Ms. om. The text is here very corrupt.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
