<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/839">Severus, Theodosius, Anthimus, Sergius and
                    Paul, Patriarchs</title>
                <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/838"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/840"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/839 -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-48" n="48">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-48">
                    <head type="main">Next the Forty-Eighth History, of the Five Blessed Patriarchs Who Distinguished
                  Themselves in Exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>) in the Time of the
                  Persecution.</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-48.1" n="1"> It seemed to us a necessary thing and one that is very
                  proper that by means of written memorials the history also of the perfect blessed
                  fathers and great and spiritual pastors, the arch-fathers, the five patriarchs,
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName>, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/784">Theodosius</persName>, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1592">Anthimus</persName>, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1463">Sergius</persName>, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1977">Paul</persName>, should be given to the
                  knowledge <pb type="vol" n="685"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="483"/>of posterity in writing, among whom the
                  blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName> like a
                  valiant and heroic man first distinguished himself in mighty and intense conflicts
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of persecution, having been chased
                  from the city of Antioch, and departed to the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>, and withdrawn to the
                  deserts of Egypt, while he carried out to the full the monastic model in which he
                  had before also lived a life of austerity and poverty, and he engaged in a
                  splendid conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of contention against
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/579">Julian of
                     Halicarnassus</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>
                  Besides him moreover the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/784">Theodosius</persName> also besides was chased and departed from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>. While these were in
                     banishment,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> the blessed
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1592">Anthimus</persName>, who was
                  bishop of the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3059">Trebizond</placeName>, was summoned<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> to the royal city, and on account of the excellence of his mode of life
                  he was raised to the throne (<foreign xml:lang="grc">θρόνος</foreign>) of the
                  royal city itself; and, when he had retained the administration of that great
                  throne (<foreign xml:lang="grc">θρόνος</foreign>) for a considerable number of
                     years,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> and had heard and learned
                  about the persecution of the blessed men <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/784">Theodosius</persName>, and investigated and learned the reason of their
                  banishment, which is the evil faith of the synod of Chalcedon, he chose for
                  himself like the great Moses to undergo affliction with his brothers, and not for
                  a short time take his <pb type="vol" n="686"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="484"/>pleasure<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> among the evil impieties of Chalcedon. And so he spoke
                  much with the king and made entreaty to him with regard to the peace of the
                  churches, and with regard to summoning his brothers, and, when no attention was
                  paid to him, he took his pall and laid it on the altar before the king himself and
                  departed, while he also wrote letters to the two patriarchs, as they also composed
                  synodical letters to him;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> and thus
                  they made union with one another, and all the party of the believers was affected
                  with great joy. But, when the queen saw the king's wrath against the blessed
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1592">Anthimus</persName> on account
                  of what he had done, and his great threatening, she took him and hid him in a
                  chamber in her palace (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>), in order that
                  men might not know what had befallen him, except only herself and two chamberlains
                  her accomplices, while even the king and everyone else might think that she had
                  removed him and banished him entirely outside the city. And so for this reason the
                  blessed man was in great peace, while he also performed his honourable labours and
                  his great practices; because he had in fact been a monk before and he was so
                  afterwards also, who never tasted bread, and also never drank wine, and had passed
                  twenty-five years in this great abstinence, it having been in fact the whole time
                  of the episcopate and of <pb type="vol" n="687"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="485"/>his patriarchate; and thus he
                  carried out the rule even after his expulsion also down to the end of his life,
                  when he had also completed a space of ten years in hiding, until many thought that
                  he was dead, until the time of the queen's death,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> and so he was discovered and made known, and he was
                  received by the king, while he also made peace with him, and held him in great
                  honour, till the end of the blessed man's life, and he used to make entreaty with
                  regard to the peace of the church. But the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName> had before these things
                  been summoned by the king to the royal city on account of the peace of the church;
                  and under great pressure from everyone he came, saying, <quote>Since it is
                     everyone's will lo! I will go up, but it is impossible that anything whatever
                     will be done by those who are in power</quote>; and so he went up, and passed
                  two years<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> a labouring and teaching.
                  And, when he saw that his statement that nothing would be done was being
                  accomplished, he went back to the southern regions of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>, constantly occupying
                  his time in the desert in retreat and asceticism and studying the writings of the
                  fathers, and perfectly carrying out great labour and an abstemious life. And, when
                  he had completed a period of some years in <pb type="vol" n="688"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="486"/>his
                  banishment, he fell into a sickness; and afterwards they carried him from the
                  desert to a city of Egypt called Ksoi,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> and there he ended the course of his conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>), and went to the Lord.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/>
                    </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-48.2" n="2"> But the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/784">Theodosius</persName>, patriarch of
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>, also had
                  been bravely contending in the conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>)
                  of persecution for a considerable time, during all the lifetime of king <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName>, and did so after his
                     death,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> even to the present time,
                  which is the year eight, hundred and seventy-seven,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> (a new king having also succeeded in the same year,
                  who is <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName>'s
                  sister's son, who also promises with the help of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/784">Theodosius</persName> to bring about the
                  peace of the church), having carried on a contest for about thirty years in exile
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>) from place to place and from country
                  to country. And<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> he also as well
                  ended the course of his practices in the same year, in the same royal city, nine
                  months after the death of the same <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName> the king,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/>
                  nothing whatever having been done in the matter of the union of the church. And he
                  completed thirty-one years and a half<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> in the conflicts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of <pb type="vol" n="689"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="487"/>persecution and exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>) from
                  place to place, having also gained distinction and renown all over the
                  commonwealth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πολιτεία</foreign>) of us
                     <persName>Romans</persName>, and he went in heroic fashion to the Lord. A
                  period of some years therefore after the death of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName> the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1463">Sergius</persName> succeeded him in
                  orthodoxy (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθοδοξία</foreign>),<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/>, who was by his birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) a man of Thella<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/> a learned and well-read mam, and among men renovned and well-known and
                  honoured, and as regards God devout and given to fasting and a Nazirite, and a
                  keeper of vigils, and a lover of quietude, and of reading the Scriptures and the
                  exposition of the fathers, so that he was skilful in his speech, and a man of
                     understanding.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/>
                    </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-48.3" n="3"> This man therefore, having attained ordination (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροτονία</foreign>) to the patriarchate while in the royal
                  city, and presided over the church, teaching and comforting and edifying and
                  establishing everyone in the truth for three years after he had received the right
                  hand of the high-priesthood of Antioch, ended his course, and was carried from the
                  life here to our Lord in the same royal city. After three years from this man's
                  decease a certain <persName>Alexandrine</persName> whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1977">Paul</persName> attained the
                  high-priesthood of the same see, that is <pb type="vol" n="690"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="488"/>outside in
                  banishment; who also down to the present day after king <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName>'s death is in the
                  body with archbishop <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/784">Theodosius</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/>
                    </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-48">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-48.1" n="4"> The history of the five blessed patriarchs who
                  distinguished themselves in exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>) in
                  the time of the persecution is ended. </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 483, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>'Zach Rh'., IX, 9-13.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 483, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>Theodosius was expelled after Anthimus, but at the time of A.'s
               accession he had been driven out by the Julianists.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 483, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Or
                  <hi rend="singleQuotes">called</hi> (sc. to the bishopric).</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 483, n.
               4</orig>
                    </choice>Really 10 months (June, 535-Mar., 536).</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 483, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>S.
               was banished 17 years before the appointment of Anthimus, but during A.'s episcopate
               he was in C P., and was forced to leave at the time of his expulsion.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 484, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Hebr., XI, 25.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 484, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>'Zach. Rh.', IX, 21-26.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 485, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Theodora lived 12 years after A.'s deprivation. In the Eccl. Hist.
               (Land, p. 339) J. says that he was 7 years in hiding.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 485, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>Really 355-Mar., 536 ('Zach. Rh.', IX, 15). It seems clear that J.
               had never seen S., and therefore left CP. before his arrival (Dyakanov, p. 49); but I
               cannot follow Dyakonov in rejecting the statement of 'Zach.' that S. arrived in ind.
               13, and therefore before 1 Sept., 535.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 486, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Xois (Ptol., IV, V, 50; Steph. Byz., s. V.; Plin., V, 9).</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 486, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>8 Feb., 538.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 486, n.
               3</orig>
                    </choice>14 Nov., 565.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 486, n.
               4</orig>
                    </choice>565/6.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 486, n.
               5</orig>
                    </choice>This sentence and the following, inconsistent with the preceding and
               with the end of the ch., are clearly a later addition of the author; see Introd., p.
               VII.</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 486, n.
               6</orig>
                    </choice>This would place his death in Aug., 566; but 'Dionysus', who usually
               follows John, places it on 19 June, and in the Coptic calendar he is celebrated on 22
               June.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 486, n.
               7</orig>
                    </choice>This must be reckoned from his expulsion by the Julianists in Feb.,
               535.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 487, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>I.e., in the Monophysite succession, as opposed to the Chalcedonian
               patriarchs.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 487, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>Constantina.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 487, n.
               3</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 489.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 488, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>See ch. 50.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
