<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/840">Jacob</title>
                <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/839"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/841"/>
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- See spear/840 -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-49" n="49">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-49">
                    <head type="main">Next the Forty-Ninth History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> the Bishop and Brave and
                  Valiant Combatant (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγωνιστής</foreign>) ..</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-49.1" n="1"> It would not therefore be easy for any one to approach
                  the task of relating the history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> without fear, a history
                  which transcends all the extent of the limits of narrative, a man whose story is
                  higher than all words and all understandings; but out of love of truth we will
                  through our poor language and in our contemptible writing make both a memorial of
                  a few of his own excellencies and a picture of the exhalation of his spiritual
                  beauties. This saint therefore and veritable man of God from his boyhood, while he
                  also was by his birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/200">Thella</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> was trained in the celebrated convent of the monastery
                  called that of Fsiltha,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> but some
                  cause <pb type="vol" n="691"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="489"/>summoned him together with the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3258">Sergius</persName> whom we mentioned
                     above,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> who also attained the
                  honour of the high-priesthood through the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName>, with him first to go up to
                  the royal city on account of the faith.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> And, when they had been received with great honour by the believing
                  queen, and she had given them also a house and the rest of what they needed,
                  thenceforth the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> dwelt alone in a little cell, in great retirement and arduous
                  labours, and asceticism beyond measure, and in extraordinary poverty moreover in
                  mode of life and in clothing, since he would cut one thick and ugly cloak of
                  withes (?) into two, and out of its halves make what was required for his clothing
                  and his scanty covering,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> and,
                  though the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3258">Sergius</persName> also as well did as he did and associated himself with him
                  in fasting and vigil and constant recitation of service, yet he fell very far
                  short of the standard of his retirement and his severe practices, on account of
                  the communications brought by many who used to come to them and with whom he was
                  required to speak; but the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> entirely refused to take part in these things, and refused
                  also to appear during the <pb type="vol" n="692"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="490"/>day outside his cell. But,
                  when he had been engaged for a period of about fifteen years in these labours in
                  the same royal city in his cell, then by the provision and at the instigation of
                  the believing queen he was under great pressure summoned to the episcopacy,
                  together with another blessed man from the country of
                     <placeName>Arabia</placeName> whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3266">Theodore</persName>; because the party of
                  the believers had diminished and a deficiency had moreover arisen in the order of
                  the priesthood over all the commonwealth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πολιτεία</foreign>) of the party of the believers. And, when both had received
                  the high-priesthood, that is the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> that of the city of
                     <placeName>Edessa</placeName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3266">Theodore</persName> that of
                     <placeName>Hirtha</placeName> of the Saracens,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> then he armed himself with divine strength, and went
                  out to the work of his ministry, while he thenceforth began to pour out the
                  priesthood derived from him copiously over the regions in all the eastern
                  districts, like a great river in the days of <persName>Nisan</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> having entered upon the high road of
                  heroism at a vigorous spiritual pace without ceasing or resting night and day,
                  while in accordance with the saying of the apostle he clothed himself in the
                  breastplate of righteousness, and girded his loins with the perfection of faith,
                  and took hold of the shield of salvation,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> while he was at all times. carrying on a contest on behalf of the truth
                     <quote>on the right hand and on the left, <pb type="vol" n="693"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="491"/>in glory
                     and in dishonour</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> And so
                  in the upper and lower countries, while he was running the vigorous course of
                  heroism without ceasing from the Persian frontier even as for as the royal city of
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/586">Constantinople</placeName>, and
                     <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName> and all
                  the countries, and fulfilling the work of the ministry to all the orthodox
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθόδοξοι</foreign>) believers, not only by organizing
                  the clergy and the giving of the priesthood, but also by consoling and comforting
                  and edifying and strengthening and teaching all the party of the believers
                     everywhere;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> so that consequently
                  his fame was carried over all quarters, and in every country and city; so that all
                  the synodite bishops from all sides were exasperated, and made threats against him
                  to arrest him and tear him in pieces. And, while they were running after him with
                  menaces in all quarters, he was sheltered by the divine grace, and was not
                  delivered into the hands of his pursuers, and of those who sought his life.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> For, whenever he went to any
                  district, he would complete all the work of his ministry in one night perhaps and
                  one day, and would pass the next night thirty or forty miles or more farther on;
                  and, whenever news of him was heard in one district, and his pursuers went out
                  after him, the brave man would be found in his heroism fulfilling his work in <pb type="vol" n="694"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="492"/>another district, while those who were running after him
                  to the right and to the left were found beating the air (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άήρ</foreign>), and,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/>
                  exasperated and biting their fingers, they would turn back with great shame,
                  filled with bitterness and confusion and gnashing their molars against the man
                  mighty in his Lord, and that while news of him was flying about to-day in one
                  quarter and tomorrow in another; while for his part he resolutely refused to allow
                  even a travelling-companion to carry any gold<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> or silver or bronze with him, or any food upon the
                  journey, though he would travel extended stages (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μανσίων</foreign>) at a vigorous pace, since on many days they would traverse
                  more than the miles of the stage (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μανσίων</foreign>),
                  while he would not consent to the fast and abstinence being broken; insomuch that
                  on many days men could not travel with him and minister to him more than a short
                  time, since they could not hasten on with his old age and support and endure his
                  abstinence; while he also would not consent to avail himself of the use of an
                  animal for riding or for driving, but he used to accomplish his travelling on
                  foot, since besides being strengthened by divine grace he further also possessed a
                  sound body by nature. And thus he would accomplish the course along the road of
                     <pb type="vol" n="695"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="493"/>righteousness, and would make an addition to the
                  party of the believers every day in every place, among <persName>Greeks</persName>
                  and among <persName>Syrians</persName>; so that his fame which was in every place
                  sorely exasperated the adversaries, and disturbed them and made them run after him
                  over the roads and districts and quarters. And, when the report of him reached
                  this place, the news of him would further rouse excitement over an unlimited space
                  in one day, while consequently pursuers and horses would run after him in droves
                  from all sides, meeting one another; insomuch that as chance would have it those
                  who were pursuing him often met the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> himself, and asked him
                  about himself, saying, <quote>Have you heard any secret news of that deceiver
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> anywhere
                     there?</quote>, and he on his side would name to them a place no small distance
                  behind him, saying: <quote>Yes, I have heard from some men who were saying that he
                     was in such-and-such a place, and was going about there; and, if you set out,
                     perhaps you will catch him.</quote> Having heard<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> these things from him as a piece of secret information
                  and supposing him<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> to be a partisan,
                  they would leave him himself, and run after him in accordance with the story that
                  he had told them.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> And so their
                  outward eyes were closed <pb type="vol" n="696"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="494"/>as well as their inner ones,
                  that they might not recognise the blessed man, while it was not these only who
                  were exasperated and disturbed by the news of him, but also the king himself, who
                  gave no small amount of gold to those who promised to capture the blessed man,
                  bishops and many monks and several laymen; so that many, when they saw his
                  intentness and his eager desire and the gift that he gave for the capture of the
                  blessed man, and that everyone who promised to capture him received from him a
                  large quantity of gold, as much as he asked, used consequently to deceive him, and
                  promise and receive gold, from two hundred and three hundred darics, and go out.
                  And there are some of them who while they were making search with great diligence
                  in every place, in deserts and on mountains and in cities and in villages, were
                  dazed and wearied, while they were unable to find the bondman of God on account of
                  his abstemiousness,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/> though these
                  things continued to be carried on in this way for many years, indeed even till
                  after king Justinian's death, while the blessed man was strengthened in his Lord,
                  and was confident like a lion, and accomplished his ministry, causing the
                  priesthood to flow like great rivers over the whole world of the Roman dominions;
                  so that, if a man take upon himself to say that a hundred thousand were ordained
                  by him, <pb type="vol" n="697"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="495"/>I do not think he will depart from the truth;
                  even as no small number of bishops and two patriarchs<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/> also received ordination (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροντονία</foreign>) from him and from others who were with him as is
                  enjoined in the canons. First he took two admirable blessed men whose names are
                     <persName>Eugene</persName> and <persName>Conon</persName> and entered the city
                  of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>, and there
                  with other bishops he made them also as well bishops, and so he went out; and with
                  them he heroically performed the work of the ministry, which has been going on
                  even down to this first year of the reign of Justin the king,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/> though he has now reached an
                  honoured old age, though he does not fall short of the work of youth. For, as we
                  declared at the beginning of the history that is concerned with him that the
                  history that is concerned with him cannot be related in accordance with what he
                  is, so also we state now at the end, having recorded a small portion of the
                  conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of the blessed man's contests
                  and of his pursuits and his work for the glory of God, who chose him and
                  strengthened him and set him up in his church in the time of the persecution, in
                  order that we may all be assisted by his prayer together with that of all the
                  saints Amen and Amen! </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-49">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-49.1" n="2"> The history of the brave and valiant blessed man
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> the bishop and
                  combatant (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγωνιστής</foreign>) is ended. </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 488, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>Constantina.</note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 488, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Sc.
                  <hi rend="singleQuotes">the quarry</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 489, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>P.
               487.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 489, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>According to the spurious life (see Appendix) for a conference with
               the Chalcedonians; but, if he became a bp. in 542 (ch. 50) and lived 15 yrs in C.P.,
               he must have come in 527, which is before the time of the conferences.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 489, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>See
               p. 319, n.2. The meaning may also be that he used half for clothing and half for a
               night-covering. From this attire he got the nickname <hi rend="singleQuotes">Burd'aya</hi> or <hi rend="singleQuotes">Burd'ayna</hi> (the man of the patchwork
               garment); cf. p. 423.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 490, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Also called Hirtha d Nu'man (p. 145). The mention of Theodore and
               his see had been omitted in the ms. and is supplied from ch. 50.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 490, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>April.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 490, n.
               3</orig>
                    </choice>Eph., VI, 14-17.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 491, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>II
               Cor., VI, 7. 8.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 491, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>The sentence is left unfinished.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 491, n.
               3</orig>
                    </choice>Jer., XLIV, 30.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 492, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 492, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>So I emend from the interpolated life (see Introd., p. XIV, n.
               7).</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 493, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Ms. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 493, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>The same story is told of Simeon of Beth Arsham (p. 145).</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 494, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>This appy. means that he was able to travel so rapidly because he
               travelled so light and did not get stop to take food.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 495, n.
               1</orig>
                    </choice>Sergius and Paul.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 495, n.
               2</orig>
                    </choice>566.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
