<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/844">Priscus</title>
            <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/843"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/845"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/844 -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-53" n="53">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-53">
               <head type="main">Next the Fifty-Third History, of the Divine Blessed Man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2024">Priscus</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>
               </head>
               <ab xml:id="section-53.1" n="1"> [....] we came to the conclusion that this was rather
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μάλλον</foreign>) one of those poor in spirit to whom
                  a blessing is given by our Lord,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/>
                  and he conducted himself in this way in spiritual knowledge in order to attain to
                  excellence. Then, having learned that he did not beg for anything from anyone, we
                  sent him a <pb type="vol" n="180"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="526"/>present of one <foreign>tremissis</foreign>
                  by a <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3720">certain gentlemen</persName>
                  who was occupied with us in God's service, that it might assist him to supply his
                  needs, and in order that we might thereby discover the object that he had before
                  him. But this man who was in very truth poor in spirit on seeing the
                  <foreign>tremissis</foreign> began to run away at a rapid pace, since he was in
                  fact not advanced in years; and the man who brought the
                  <foreign>tremissis</foreign> to him began to run after him, adjuring him to
                  stop. But the blessed man, having put a distance between himself and many (?),<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> stopped on account of the
                  adjurations, saying to him, <quote>Wherefore, man, are you worrying yourself and
                     worrying me the poor man?</quote> He said to him, <quote>The abbot (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άββάς</foreign>) sent you this present because he heard that
                        you were in need. Take it and supply your need</quote>. That man said
                  <quote>For my part I do not need this. But say to the abbot (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άββάς</foreign>), Run that you may attain.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> If you have one follis, I will
                     take it</quote>. Then, having seen that he had run away from the
                  <foreign>tremissis</foreign>, he gave him ten <foreign>folles</foreign>; and he
                  on his side stretched out his hand and took one <foreign>follis</foreign>, and ran
                  away. And so that man came, and related all these things to us. Then we were
                  assured that that poor man was a spiritual person, and a bondman of God, and was
                  poor of his own will for the sake of eternal life. After these things in the time
                  of the winter-cold. <pb type="vol" n="181"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="527"/>having seen that he was uncovered
                  and sore bested, we bought him a tunic and a cloak, and sent them by that man,
                  begging him to put them on and warm himself during the winter. But he on seeing
                  them turned his face away, and showed displeasure against him, saying, <quote>Go
                     your way, man, wherefore do you worry me the poor man?</quote> The man who was
                  sent by us answered him, <quote>The abbot (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άββάς</foreign>) out of charity and because of the hardness of the winter
                     bought them and sent them to you</quote>. He on his side says to him: <quote>Go
                        say to the abbot (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άββάς</foreign>), Send things that
                        last, and do not try to concern yourself about stripping naked lest you be
                        stripped naked<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/>
                     </quote>. And so
                  he would not consent to accept them. And from that time the man who was with us
                  began to mark times and observe him, because he too was an earnest and zealous
                  man, and by his birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) a Cappadocian. And
                  one day, as was that poor man's custom, he went secretly outside the city to some
                  enclosed garden-land hidden by trees and reeds to pray; insomuch that that
                  gentleman observed him, and secretly went out after him, standing facing him; and
                  he saw him standing in prayer with his hands stretched out to heaven, and suddenly
                  an awe-inspiring spectacle that was laid upon his face (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>), and flashed like lightning, and rays of fire were
                  proceeding <pb type="vol" n="182"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="528"/>from his face (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>), and an awful bow of fire that was stretched out above him
                  while he stood within it, and a great light surrounded him. And, when that man saw
                  this awful spectacle on that poor man as he was praying, he was frightened, and
                  fell on his face on the ground. And after a little time he rose and fled and came
                  to us at a great pace, shaking and trembling and weeping: insomuch that we
                  ourselves were alarmed at the sight of him, and were brought to a state of sudden
                  fright, inquiring what was the cause of his agitation and fright. And he swore to
                  us by God the Ruler of all the ages, <quote>I saw all this spectacle on that poor
                     man, without falsehood or any exaggeration; and my heart quaked, and my limbs
                     shook, and I fled, leaving him standing thus in that awful splendour, and I
                     fled,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> so that I never again
                     had the power and the boldness to lift my eyes toward him.</quote> And during
                  the whole of the day he was in a condition of stupor and tremor and perturbation
                  from that awful spectacle; but at night he went and found him in the place where
                  he used to sleep, and he fell at his feet, weeping and trembling from his fear.
                  But the blessed man knew the cause of his fear, and said to him: <quote>Wherefore,
                     man, did you come out after my poverty, to inquire into things which do not
                     concern you?</quote>. And, adjuring him by the living God, he continued <pb type="vol" n="183"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="529"/>beseeching him to inform him what he was. And he also
                  required oaths from him that he would not make any disclosure or give any
                  information to men about him. And he on his side said: <quote>Only from the abbot
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άββάς</foreign>) I cannot conceal it; but to others
                     I will give no information whatever.</quote> Then he answered him, adjuring him
                  and saying: <quote>Do not make demands or inquiries of me about many things; it is
                     enough for you to know that I am a stranger and a poor man, and for the sake of
                     the hope of my eternal life I am enduring labours and buffetings in strange
                     lands, and in this poverty in which you now see me; and not I only, but we are
                     seven brethren who are secretly labouring in this fashion, and once in the
                     whole week we meet together in one place, and receive consolation in one
                     another's company, and comfort and edification; and thus each of us returns to
                     his place and to his employment. I have given you the information; see that you
                     do not make yourself the cause of my moving from this city, in which I have
                     much peacefulness, and especially the fact that I am reckoned a madman by them,
                     and there is no one who speaks with me or who worries me. And beg the abbot
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άββάς</foreign>) that, though these things are
                     known to him, he will leave me as I am, and not show any difference toward
                     me.</quote> The man who was with me having repeated all these <pb type="vol" n="184"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="530"/>things to me, I sent and begged him, if possible, to come to us
                  secretly at suppertime, and eat with us,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> and he would not consent, sending me a message that we should attend to
                  things that are helpful and lasting. One night I was suddenly attacked by the
                  disease of fever; and in the morning, when the man who was with me who used to go
                  to that poor man saw him,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> as he
                  swore with fearful oaths by God, <quote>Before I on my side spoke to him, he first
                     said to me: <quote>The abbot (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άββάς</foreign>) was
                        attacked by fever during the night. Go say to him, <quote>Wherefore did you
                           eat dry food and drink a vinegar-posset (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πόσκα</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> with
                           cold water?</quote>
                     </quote>. And, when I on my side said to him,
                     <quote>Sir, who showed you this?</quote>, he said to me <quote>My heart
                        showed me that he did so, and in consequence of the vinegar and the cold
                        water he fell ill</quote>
                  </quote>; so that, when that man came, and informed
                  me of these things, I was struck with great astonishment and wonder, and I gave
                  thanks to God who dwells in his saints. With regard to many other characteristic
                  things which that man used to relate that he saw in that poor man, and moreover
                  that one of his companions came to him and saw him with him, and he himself
                  refused to speak to him, in consequence of the large number of these we have on
                  account of the length <pb type="vol" n="185"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="531"/>of the history refrained from
                  speaking. But, when we had departed to another place, that saint ended his course
                  in the same city and was buried; and, when we came and heard of it, we were much
                  distressed at having been deprived of his society, even at second-hand. And we
                  made great endeavours to discover the coffin which held his holy remains; and in
                  consequence of the great pestilence which had occurred<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> and the numbers that were laid above him we could not
                  do so. These things we have recorded for the glory of God who strengthens and
                  helps all that trust in him. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-53">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-53.1" n="2"> The history of the divine blessed man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2024">Priscus</persName> is ended. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 525, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>The beginning is lost.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 525, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Matth., V, 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 526, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>I can make nothing else of this. We require <hi rend="singleQuotes">put a
                  great distance between himself and his pursuer</hi>. It is probably a phrase for
               <hi rend="singleQuotes">run very fast</hi>. V. D. and L. have <hi rend="singleQuotes">procul</hi> for the whole clause.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 526, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>I Cor., IX, 24.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 527, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>The meaning perh. is that whoever wears earthly clothes will eventualy be
               left naked through their wearing out. V. D. and L 's <hi rend="singleQuotes">
                  <foreign xml:lang="la">curare nudatum</foreign>
               </hi> is not in the Syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 528, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sic syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 530, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>As this was not later than 542 (see below), J. was probably living in the
               house of Probus (see Introd., p. VI).</note>
            <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 530, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>The sentence is left unfinished, and the sense completed in another
               form.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 530, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>This word (= <foreign>posca</foreign>) is not known in Gk., but the Syr.
               implies in a Gk. form.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 531, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>542.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
