<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/845">Caesarea</title>
            <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/844"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/846"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/845 -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-54" n="54">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-54">
               <head type="main">Next the Fifty-Fourth History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2621">Caesaria</persName> the Patrician,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> Who Began and Through God's Help
                  Ended Heroically and Excellently.</head>
               <ab xml:id="section-54.1" n="1"> The history therefore of this woman also, great before
                  God and before men, was one that could not but excite great admiration, a woman
                  who from a great royal race<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> brought
                  herself down to humiliation undertaken for <pb type="vol" n="186"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="532"/>the sake of
                  God and the promised life and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> to a
                  mean position, and betook herself to the habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) of the solitary and monastic life and sought refuge in
                  it.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> In admiration therefore and
                  confessing that we are not capable of compassing the beauties of the history of
                  this blessed woman, we set ourselves for the sake of God's glory and the profit of
                  the hearers to record as it were a small measure taken from the sea of spiritual
                  riches, addressed to those who love matters of spiritual profit. This divine
                  blessed woman therefore, who was called by name <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2621">Caesaria</persName>, and by her birth
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) came originally from the city of
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/178">Samosata</placeName> [....]<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> to do, when we came to her the in
                  city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> so that when she saw us she was
                  filled with great joy, and received great consolation. But we found her engaged in
                  severe labours of recitation of service and of quietude and intense supplication,
                  and constant prayers and frequent genuflexions and asceticism beyond measure, and
                  especially in the case of a woman like this <pb type="vol" n="187"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="533"/>who had been
                  reared in endless luxuries, and had grown accustomed to royal habits, who suddenly
                  came to be cut off from all these things, and subjected herself to asceticism
                  beyond measure, so that she completely cut herself off from eating bread, and
                  every other day she would feed on cooked herbs with salt and vinegar without oil
                  and moist rolls, and she used to sleep on sackcloth on the ground, but on the
                  sabbath and the first day of the week under pressure from the bishops and many
                  blessed men she consented that a little oil should be put on the herbs for her; so
                  that, having found her living in all this asceticism and hardship, we continued
                  blaming her and advising her to give up high things and embrace moderate things,
                  lest being unable to endure she might either lose her strength or fall into severe
                  illness and be forced from necessity (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άνάγχη</foreign>) to
                  give it all up. But the blessed woman, when she heard us speak of illnesses,
                  continued praying and saying: <quote>Would that God had granted me bodily
                     illnesses all the days of my life, in order that I might possess health of soul
                     only.</quote> Moreover, since she thirsted after the spiritual gain of the
                  excellent life, though she was wise and learned in the reading of the Scriptures
                  and of all the fathers, it pleased her greatly to ask <pb type="vol" n="188"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="534"/>and inquire<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> about the passions of
                  the soul and of the body and about thoughts, so that after spiritual conversation
                  all day we spent many nights in this way in discussion and helpful speech, while
                  the blessed woman condescended to make confession and say, <quote>I have here more
                     than seven hundred volumes in number of all the fathers, to which my intellect
                     and my attention have been devoted for many years, insomuch that now my mind
                     has no rest and my soul also is stirred with passion night and day to hear from
                     you the word of God, and about discernment of passions and observance of
                     commandments, and about the other spiritual things.</quote> One day, while we
                  were sitting occupied in speech and divine conversation, suddenly that blessed
                  woman fell on her face on the ground before me, filling me with amazement and
                  alarm by suddenly doing this, while I said to her, <quote>Wherefore have you done
                     this, and laid a weight upon me the mean one? be so good as to rise and tell me
                     what it is that you command</quote>. But she would not consent to rise, saying,
                  <quote>I will not rise hence unless you give me your word before God that you
                     will agree to my request and do what I require of you.</quote> And, being
                  troubled in my mind because she was lying on her face, I said to her: <quote>Be so
                     good <pb type="vol" n="189"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="535"/>as to rise, and what you command, if it is
                     within my power and capacity, I will do.</quote> And so she reluctantly rose;
                  and she began to request me, saying: <quote>Now that I have left my house and my
                     property and come out to settle down in retreat and weep for my sins, and here
                     my soul is in the same turmoil, I make this entreaty of you, to save my soul,
                     and go privily to the inner desert and search out for us a place in which there
                     is a well of water, and come and take me secretly with one chamber-woman and
                     one chamberlain only that we may settle down in retreat, and be quit of the
                     evil things of this world, and of all its turmoil, for I thought to escape from
                     it but have not yet succeeded.</quote> When therefore we heard that she
                  intended to do these things, we would not promise to agree to her request, and to
                  be ourselves the ministers of these plans, because we saw that they were
                  unnecessary, and they were beyond her capacity and strength and condition; and,
                  besides many arguments that we arrayed before her on these matters, we were afraid
                  lest this ardour and the plans came from the evil one, while we further explained
                  and showed her that these plans if put into effect by her would even bring danger
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κίνδυνος</foreign>) upon her, the danger of the
                  destruction involved in the scattering of all the souls that had gone out with
                  her. Then in distress and <pb type="vol" n="190"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="536"/>tears she said, <quote>It is
                     from these very persons above all that I seek to flee.</quote> And we continued
                  admonishing her very strongly in order to suppress her thoughts, saying,
                  <quote>Know that you are an old and feeble woman, and your nature is not strong
                     enough to hold out against these thoughts of yours and endure and struggle; for
                     neither indeed has the assault of temptations yet fallen upon you, and you have
                     not been tried by<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> the cunning of
                     the fiends; and therefore we advise you to give up these plans, being satisfied
                     with having left your country and your house and gone out into a strange land
                     to dwell in the monastery that you have built.</quote> With great labour
                  therefore we succeeded in restraining her ardour from going out into the inner
                  desert, while she showed vexation and annoyance toward us because we did not yield
                  to her in this matter. And so, when she had built and completed the monasteries in
                  a grand and admirable style, and had bought a large gold-mine (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χρυσωρυχείον</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> for them,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> she made one
                  <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2762">a monastery for men</placeName>,
                  and one for <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2761">women</placeName>, in
                  which she herself also thenceforth performed severe and sublime labours, for
                  fifteen years, though she declined the headship of the same monastery, but sent to
                  another monastery, and took thence a certain blessed woman great in <pb type="vol" n="191"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="537"/>her modes of life whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3201">Cosmiana</persName>, and her she appointed
                  archimandritess, she herself submitting to her like an insignificant and poor
                  sister. And so she continued to labour till the end of her life, which happened
                  after fifteen years.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> And so she
                  completed the course of her practices heroically, bearing great testimony and
                  undergoing mighty conflicts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>). And she died
                  and was laid in this <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2761">monastery</placeName>, which even to the present day is called the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2761">monastery</placeName> of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2621">Caesaria</persName> the patrician. These
                  few memorials taken from the blessed woman's labour and practices we have recorded
                  for the glory of God and the profit of those who are desirous of spiritual profit. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-54">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-54.1" n="2"> The history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2621">Caesaria</persName> the patrician is
                  ended. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 531, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>To whom a large production of the extant letters of Severus is
               addressed.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 531, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>A native of Samosata can hardly have come of an imperial family; but her
               husband may have been of imperial descent.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 532, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ms. om.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 532, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>When Sev., Select Letters, X, 7, was written, C. wished to leave her husband
               and live in ascetic life, but S. discussed her. Either therefore he was unsuccessful,
               or her husband afterwards died.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 532, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>A leaf or two leaves lost; see Introd., p. VII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 532, n. 4</orig>
               </choice>Hardly on his 1st visit in 534, as Dyakonov (p. 47) supposes, but on his 2nd
               in 541. If C had adopted the ascetic life in Sev.'s lifetime, one would have expected
               to find some mention of it in his letters. See also p. 538, n. 2, and p. 544, n.
               1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 534, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>See p. 39, n. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 536, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ms. om.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 536, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Ms. <hi rend="singleQuotes">krwsrwn</hi>. I adopt the conjecture of V. D.
               and L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 536, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>Masc., sc. the inmates of the monasteries.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 537, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Circ. 556.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
