<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/846">John and Sosiana</title>
            <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/845"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/847"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/846 -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-55" n="55">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-55">
               <head type="main">Next the Fifty-Fifth History, of an Excellent Woman and of Her Husband, Who
                  Were Chamberlains of the Same Glorious Patrician,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/> Whose Names Are <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1820">John</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3020">Sosiana</persName>, Who Lived Lives of
                  Excellence.</head>
               <ab xml:id="section-55.1" n="1"> This perfect woman <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3020">Sosiana</persName> therefore, when her
                  husband departed from <pb type="vol" n="192"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="538"/>the world, whose name was
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1820">John</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> after they had lived together thirty
                  years, and as is said lived all these years in purity, never holding carnal
                  intercourse with one another, but living in devoutness and honour and holiness,
                  occupying themselves in fasting and prayer, and genuflexion and recitation of
                  service and watching by night, while hair-mats were laid down for them each apart,
                  and in this way they passed the whole length of the night-hours, kneeling and
                  lying on their faces, and weeping in prayer and mighty crying to God, without this
                  becoming known to many. When then this excellent <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1820">John</persName> departed from the world,
                  bearing this great testimony, and moreover <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2621">Caesaria</persName> the patrician also as
                  well whom we mentioned above had gone out to the desert, i. e. first to
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> this excellent blessed woman <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3020">Sosiana</persName> therefore laded three of her slaves with all her husband's
                  splendid clothes, great cloaks (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χλαινίδια</foreign>) of
                  pure silk (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όλοσηρικόν</foreign>) and valuable raw silk
                  garments (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μέταξα</foreign>), with colours - and pictures
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πικτούρα</foreign>),<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> and <pb type="vol" n="193"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="539"/>the other clothes of
                  high price, and sent them to our meanness,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> adjuring and beseeching us, <quote>Let all these be cut into such sizes
                     as you think fit, sir, and let handsome crosses and corners (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γωνία</foreign>) be put upon them, and let them be made into
                     cloths and veils, and distributed among the holy altars as you shall decide,
                     because I made this vow to the Lord God.</quote> We then on seeing these things
                  marvelled greatly, thinking in ourselves, <quote>The thing would not be right that
                     we should cut up articles of clothing each of which is well worth more than a
                     pound (<foreign xml:lang="grc">λίτρα</foreign>) of gold,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> but rather (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μάλλον</foreign>) that these should be sold for a great price, and given to
                     the poor<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/>
                  </quote>. And so with
                  this thought in our mind we went to the excellent woman herself, in order to give
                  her this advice. But the excellent woman fell upon her face, saying, <quote>Sir,
                     since I made this vow before God, that all the fine clothes belonging to myself
                     and to my husband whose soul is at rest should be made into cloths and veils,
                     and crosses and gilded corners (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γωνία</foreign>) should
                     be put upon them, and they should be distributed among the holy altars of God,
                     together with all the silver which God gave us, for the sake of the love of God
                     whom I have loved be my helper, <pb type="vol" n="194"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="540"/>and perform this
                     service for me also as well, because this also as well is of God; and divide
                     these among all the churches and monasteries which God established through
                     you,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/> or wherever God puts it
                     into your mind; and from the poor, as far as in me lies, I trust in God that
                     nothing will be taken away by me; since for my part I have no one except God my
                     Lord and my Creator and my Saviour and my Life-giver</quote>. And from that
                  time stitchers were summoned and came; and cloths and veils and napkins (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μανδήλη</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/> were cut out according to the size of each article of clothing; and men came
                  who were occupied in gilding and decorating them in a marvellous manner, and
                  inscribing her own name and her husband's, while she also continued to bring clean
                  and marvellous linen cloths and Persian cambrics, and they were all overlaid.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/> And, when all her husband's clothes
                  had been cut up, she went on to bring her own fine clothes in no small number, and
                  the woven gold also was upon them, and fine figures made of various silks and raw
                  silks (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μέταξα</foreign>), and pure silk (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όλοσηρικόν</foreign>), and so on. And, while we were again
                  thinking, <quote>Perhaps it would have pleased God more that they should be sold
                     and given to the poor</quote>, and were saying so to her and she on her part
                  was insisting on cutting them up, we were frightened by our Lord's expression in
                  the gospel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">εύαγγέλιον</foreign>) about the fine ointment
                  of <pb type="vol" n="195"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="541"/>great price which the woman poured on his head, when
                  also the advice and desire of <persName>Judas</persName> the traitor which he
                  proferred contrary to what was right and proper was blamed,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/> and we ceased advising that woman so and standing in
                  the way of her wish. And, when all her valuable clothes had been used up, until
                  she was left with the cheap ordinary clothes that she was wearing only, when we
                  were finding fault with her in this matter, that she might leave herself what she
                  needed, yet we did no good whatever, since she said, <quote>Do not pity me in this
                     matter, sir, since I have not a single day in the life of the body beyond this
                     year; and, if I spare these, whence do I know if courtezans (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πόρναι</foreign>:) will wear them, and I on my part shall be
                     called to account for them?<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/>
                  </quote> And on hearing this declaration, which she plainly made in advance
                  about the end of her life, we said : <quote>If this has been revealed to you, you
                     do rightly in sending all that you have in advance</quote>. When all her
                  precious articles of clothing had been used up, and we had begun out of the
                  multitude of them to distribute to the east and to the west everything that came
                  to hand, then she brought her silver which amounted to many pounds (<foreign xml:lang="grc">λίτρα</foreign>), and it was given up and chalices and patens
                  were made, and many dishes (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πίνακα</foreign>) and spoons,
                  and they were distributed by <pb type="vol" n="196"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="542"/>us everywhere, as God
                  knows, while she also with her own hands distributed all the rest of the contents
                  of her house to all who were in need, while the blessed woman rejoiced and gave
                  thanks to God. But we on our side were noting the time which she fixed beforehand
                  with regard to her end, to see if it was near as she had stated. And, when the end
                  of that year approached, five days before, she fell into an illness; and she sent
                  and called us, begging us to set forth incense, and make expiation for her,
                  saying, <quote>Sir, pray for me, for the sinner; for lo! after five days I am
                     going to our Lord, to make answer (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άπολογία</foreign>)
                     for my sins. But for God's sake remember me the wretched one in your acceptable
                     prayers to God</quote>. And thus while we were constantly with her on the fifth
                  day as fixed by what she had said she fell asleep in peace, while everyone was
                  overcome with astonishment; and they thanked and praised God, and ran to receive a
                  blessing from her holy body. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-55">
               <ab xml:id="trailer-55.1" n="2"> 
                  The history of some excellent 
                  persons, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1820">John</persName> 
                  and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3020">Sosiana</persName>, is ended. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 537, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Ms. masc., but, as Caesaria is clearly meant, I have emended the text; cf.
               p. 543.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 538, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>The sentence is left unfinished, and the sense completed in another
               form.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 538, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>This is not inconsistent with ch. 54. C. did not go to live a hermit life in
               the inner desert, but left Alexandria and lived in her convent in the desert. Since
               S. sent the things for the churches and monasteries founded by J., i.e. during his
               mission to Asia (ch. 47), which did not begin till 542 (see Introd., p. V), C.'s
               household was appy. broken up not long before that time; see p. 532, n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 538, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>So I read with two slight emendations. V. D. and L. conect the words with
               <foreign xml:lang="grc">γόνυ</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="la">pectus</foreign>
               and render <hi rend="singleQuotes">
                  <foreign xml:lang="la">genualibus et
                     pectoralibus</foreign>
               </hi>, but neither word is known in Greek, and the
               context requires that the words should refer to the value of the garments, not their
               use or shape. The 'pictures' would be not pictures proper, but embroidery; cf. Virg.,
               <title>Aen.</title>, III, 48 <hi rend="singleQuotes">
                  <foreign xml:lang="la">picturatas auri subtegmine vestes</foreign>
               </hi>. See p. 540, l. 15. The word
               <foreign xml:lang="grc">πικτούρα</foreign> however is not known in Greek.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 539, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>It is clear from this that S. was living in CP., and we may therefore infer
               that C. lived there also, and that Severus made her acquaintance during his residence
               there in 508-11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 539, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Circ. £45 = fr. 1135.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 539, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>Matth., XXVI, 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 540, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>During his missionary expeditions in Asia Minor; see ch. 47.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 540, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>I. e., altar-cloths, veils for the sacred vessels, and purificators.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 540, n. 3</orig>
               </choice>Sc. with gold.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 541, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>John, XII, 7, 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 541, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Cf. p. 285, l. 17; p. 550, n. 1.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
