<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/847">Peter and Photius</title>
            <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
            <editor role="creator"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                  <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                  <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                     <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2026-03-02</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
            <editor role="general"
               ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <relatedItem type="previous">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/846"/>
            </relatedItem>
            <relatedItem type="next">
               <ptr target="https://syriac-library/848"/>
            </relatedItem>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/847 -->
         <div type="work" xml:id="work-56" n="56">
            <div type="section" xml:id="section-56">
               <head type="main">Next the Fifty-Sixth History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2011">Peter</persName>, Who Himself Also Was
                  Chancellor and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3014">Photius</persName>
                  the Chartulary With the Rest of His Companions, From the Same Household.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>
               </head>
               <ab xml:id="section-56.1" n="1"> The history of the excellent blessed men <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2011">Peter</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3014">Photius</persName> also besides is
                  therefore worthy of being committed to written records; men who were themselves
                  the first, even before the blessed patrician Caesaria herself, to prepare the way
                  for that household, in that both of them together were thought worthy to despise
                  the world, and treat all its affairs with contempt, and go out and go to the
                  desert. And, in order that they might first be instructed and taught in a convent
                  and in the subjection of monasticism, they entered a great and renowned <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2777">convent</placeName> in the Ennaton<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName> which is called that
                  of the Fathers and were received in it, giving themselves to humility and
                  submission and poverty and obedience, and sorrow and fasting and prayer, and
                  watching and manual work, men who had been accustomed to a high and luxurious
                  life, who suddenly came to abstinence and the other labours, so much so that all
                  the inmates of that convent great and small used to marvel at them, and were
                  astonished at their type of life and sorrow and <pb type="vol" n="198"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="544"/>tears,
                  and their humility and obedience; so that at the time when we came to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>
                  <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> we went to that convent to see them for the sake of
                  the blessed men themselves, inasmuch as we were acquainted with them, and moreover
                  on account of the report of their manner of life, when they felt great joy, and
                  would discuss with us fights against thoughts and the other works of excellence.
                  When then they had completed about eighteen years in that monastery in spiritual
                  practices, the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2011">Peter</persName> had<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> a
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3654">brother</persName> and a
                  <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3655">sister</persName> wearing the
                  lay garb (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>), as they too were living a
                  great life in practices of excellence, so that they and their <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3656">slaves</persName> used to learn the
                  psalms, and kept hours of prayers and service as in a monastery of recluses, while
                  they also directed their steps to the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2718">Smyrna</placeName> for the sake of the
                  quietude of a strange land, and there thenceforth they lived a religious, devout,
                  pure life, so that all that city used to marvel at them and at their practices.
                  They therefore used to write and worry the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2011">Peter</persName> to come and visit them
                  and encourage them, and let them be consoled and comforted by one another, which
                  the blessed man was also constrained to do, not for the sake of bodily <pb type="vol" n="199"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="545"/>relationship, but because he knew that they were spiritual
                  persons in manner of life. But, when he had come and seen them and comforted them,
                  he set his face to return to his monastery, and they would not let him, weeping
                  and adjuring him by the living God not to leave them; and thus he was constrained
                  to stay. And, when he had completed five years with them, he was raised by force
                  to the bishopric;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> and, when he had
                  completed four years, he departed from the world with his other <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3654">brother</persName>, having lived a
                  spiritual and divine life. But their <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3655">sister</persName> the holy old woman
                  remained in the bodily life a long time, down to the writing of this history,
                  having further multiplied her spiritual practices many times. </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-56">
            <ab xml:id="trailer-56.1" n="2"> The history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2011">Peter</persName> the chancellor and
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3014">Photius</persName> the
               chartulary is ended. </ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 543, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Sc. that Caesaria.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 543, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>See p. 325, 384.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 544, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>This must have been on his 2nd visit to Egypt (541), for he had known them
               before, which must have been in CP. (p. 539, n. 1), where he had never till after his
               visit to Egypt in 534. Further, since they were in CP. in 535 and left it before
               Caesaria, his visit to Caesaria in Egypt must also have been in 541; see p. 532, n.
               4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 544, n. 2</orig>
               </choice>Sic syr. Cf. p. 397, l. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
               <choice>
                  <reg/>
                  <orig>p. 545, n. 1</orig>
               </choice>Of Smyrna (p. 503). Since he was ordained with the author, the date was not
               earlier than 558 (p. 508, n. 1, and Introd., p. V.), and therefore, if the figures
               are correct, he left CP. not later than 535, but as J. saw him in CP. in 535 (p. 544,
               n. 1), it was not earlier than that year, so that his ordination and J.'s are fixed
               to 558.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
