<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/849">Jacob Baradaeus</title>
                <title level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9501">Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/74">John of Ephesus</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="translator">E. W. Brooks</editor>
                <editor role="creator"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED --></idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0//">
                        <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                     License (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                        <p>This work incorporates public domain material from the following work(s): <listBibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <!-- What goes here and what goes in the sourceDesc? -->
                        </bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <note type="license"> used under a Creative Commons Attribution license <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date>2026-03-02</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title><!--The Syriac Library--></title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Lives of the Eastern Saints</title>
                <editor role="general"
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
                <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
                <idno type="syriacaWork">http://syriaca.org/work/9501</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem type="previous">
                <ptr target="https://syriac-library/848"/>
                </relatedItem>
                <relatedItem type="next">
                    <ptr target="https://syriac-library/850"/><!-- Is this correct? Is 850 properly part of JoE Lives of the Eastern Saints -->
                </relatedItem>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>John of Ephesus. Lives of the Eastern Saints. Translated and edited by E. W. Brooks.
               Patrologia Orientalis 17–19. Firmin-Didot, 1923.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
         <!-- NOT IN SPEAR. Please just wrap persName and placeName elements around those names. Thanks. -->
            <div type="work" xml:id="work-59" n="59">
                <div type="section" xml:id="section-59">
                    <head type="main">The History of the Habits of Life of the Saintly <persName>James</persName>
                  Metropolitan of <placeName>Edessa</placeName> and of the Countries of
                     <placeName>Syria</placeName>, Who Was Also Entrusted With The Supervision of
                  the Churches of <placeName>the East</placeName>, and Received Ordination From the
                  Blessed <persName>Severus</persName> and <persName>Theodosius</persName> of
                     <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, and
                  Became an Upholder of the Faith, Written by the Saintly <persName>John</persName>
                  of <placeName>Asia</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>.</head>
                    <ab xml:id="section-59.1" n="1"> Since then God had mercy on his people, and sought to
                  give them help. the Lord stirred up the spirit of king
                     <persName>Justinian</persName>, and put into his mind the plan <pb type="vol" n="229"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="575"/>of letting the patriarchs and bishops examine the subject of the faith
                  before him and in his presence; and he ordered both parties, the orthodox
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθόδοξος</foreign>) and the
                     <persName>Chalcedonians</persName>, to meet in the royal city of
                     <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, in order that the general questions
                  might be examined in the king's presence<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/>.
                  And, when the order went forth, many assembled from all quarters; and the holy Mar
                     <placeName>Severus</placeName> also went up and <persName>Theodosius</persName>
                  of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/>, who
                  themselves alone and a few bishops with them were left among the orthodox
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθόδοξος</foreign>), and they stayed in the royal
                  city, because the king detained them for a long time. And, all the believers being
                  desirous of sending eloquent and learned men to the conference, they occupied a
                  little over a year in choosing men from the convents and the cities and sending
                  them to the blessed <persName>Theodosius</persName> the <pb type="vol" n="230"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="576"/>patriarch. Now there was living a short time before in the small city of
                  Constantina which is <placeName>Thella d Mauzlath</placeName> among the citizens a
                  presbyter whose name was <persName>Theophilus Bar Maʿnu</persName> a good and
                  religious man, one of the reverend clergy of his city; and, since he had lawfully
                  taken a wife in marriage, and they had no children, he and his consort, having
                  fasted and prayed, made a vow to God that the first son who should be born to them
                  they would give to the Lord in <placeName>the holy convent of
                     ʾsṭrlyṭys</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/> by the city of
                     <placeName>Thella</placeName>, which is the monastery of
                     <persName>Fsiltha</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/>. And God
                  heard him, and gave him a son, and he called his name <persName>James</persName>;
                  and, when he had grown a little. his parents handed him over to the same monastery
                  of <persName>Fsiltha</persName> through the devout Mar
                     <persName>Eustace</persName> presbyter and archimandrite.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> And, when<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> his
                  training was completed, he used to practise perfect modes of life surpassing the
                     <pb type="vol" n="231"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="577"/>strength of men; and in the course of his employment
                  in the monastery he would fast three days at a time and at last seven days, and
                  again at last twenty-one; and all who saw him were held in great astonishment at
                  the way in which he repressed the powerful impulses of boyhood. But many times his
                  mother wished to bring him into the world, and he would not yield to her
                  persuasion; and she used to urge him greatly, because she had no heir except him;
                  but his father wished his promise to be carried out<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8" target="#n8" n="8"/>. And, being much pressed by his mother, he said to her:
                     <quote>Cease speaking to me, O my mother, do not weary me. Do you not
                     understand that I have betrothed myself once for all to
                        <persName>Christ</persName> the immortal bridegroom?</quote>, and, when even
                  so she did not cease, he spoke to his own master and his teacher
                     <persName>Eustace</persName> and said: <quote>My teacher and father, pray for
                     me to God that he may either take my soul from me or impose silence upon my
                     mother.</quote> And his master said to him: <quote>The Lord will effect
                     deliverance if he is pleased with you.</quote> And a year later his mother
                  died, and in the third year his father also; and the wealth which they possessed
                  they left to their own son <persName>James</persName>; and they left two <pb type="vol" n="232"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="578"/>slaves and a large amount of property (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ούσία</foreign>). But the divine <persName>James</persName>, as
                  soon as he saw that his parents were dead, called his two slaves, and set them
                  free; and he gave them the house with the property (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ούσία</foreign>) and the chattels and he did not take even one
                     <foreign>mina</foreign>; for he used to say <quote>Let the things of the world
                     be given to the world.</quote> And after a short time, when he had received
                  deacon's orders in his same monastery, he would cause himself to copy the pattern
                  of the angels' watchfulness, embracing the immaterial observances of the angels
                  with much fasting and constant vigil, and day by day adding to his divine
                  practices. But he refused to let himself be seen outside his cell at all during
                  the day; and all the believers used to betake themselves to him on account of the
                  fame of his practices; so much so that even from the frontier of the
                     <placeName>Persian territory</placeName> those who had various infirmities used
                  to flock to him; and as soon as they were resting in his monastery they were cured
                  without seeing him. For he would visit many by long journeys<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9" n="9"/>, having seen them beforehand by the vision of the Holy
                  Spirit, and be seen by them in a dream and they would be healed of their
                     diseases<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10" target="#n10" n="10"/>; insomuch that he often<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a11" target="#n11" n="11"/>
                        <pb type="vol" n="233"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="579"/>showed himself to queen <persName>Theodora</persName>
                  herself wife of <persName>Justinian</persName> king of the
                     <persName>Romans</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a12" target="#n12" n="12"/> as in a
                  dream holding a golden paten (<foreign xml:lang="grc">φιάλην</foreign>) in his
                  hands and giving the armies of the <persName>Romans</persName> living<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a13" target="#n13" n="13"/> water to drink; and accordingly the
                  miracles which he performed caused all the world to marvel. The bands of the
                  Christian <persName>Saracens</persName> attached to the
                     <persName>Romans</persName>, having once been attacked by insanity, and having
                  heard about the man's holiness, sent their king<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a14" target="#n14" n="14"/> whose name was <persName>Hereth Bar Gabala</persName> with
                  their magnates to him, in order that God might visit them through him; and
                     <persName>Hereth</persName> took gold with him with offerings to give the saint
                  if God<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a15" target="#n15" n="15"/> would visit them through him<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a16" target="#n16" n="16"/> by his prayers. But as for the blessed
                     <persName>James</persName>, the whole of their affair having been revealed to
                  him by God, when they had crossed the river <placeName>Euphrates</placeName> to
                  come to his monastery, the saint appeared to the <persName>Saracens</persName> in
                  his habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) at full morning, and said to
                     <persName>Hereth</persName>: <quote>Why, O barbarian<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a17" target="#n17" n="17"/>, did you doubt of the gift of God? Go return to your
                     land, you and your magnates, and release the man from <placeName>Mt.
                        Sinai</placeName> whom someone is detaining in your camp, and you will <pb type="vol" n="234"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="580"/>immediately be delivered from the distress; for it is
                     because of him that you were afflicted. But henceforth Satan will not be
                     permitted by the Lord to work destruction among you, until you enter the camp.
                     And <quote>thy money go with thee</quote>
                            <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a18" target="#n18" n="18"/>, since we have no desire to possess aught beside
                     God.</quote> And, this openly-shown vision having caused
                     <persName>Hereth</persName> the king and his magnates to marvel, he went back
                  to his camp, and upon asking he found that from the hour that the blessed man said
                  to him, <quote>The devil shall not work destruction in your camp</quote>, from
                  that very hour and that very day they<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a19" target="#n19" n="19"/>
                  were cured. And they asked and inquired over the whole of his camp, and they<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a20" target="#n20" n="20"/> found a certain monk who was bound inside
                  a tent; and he released him and sent him to <placeName>Mt. Sinai</placeName>; and
                  the man who had bound him in his tent<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a21" target="#n21" n="21"/> he
                  slew with the edge of the sword; and day by day <persName>Hereth Bar
                     Gabala</persName> was yearning to see the saint. But the blessed man would
                  quietly labour with arduous labours and exercise himself in marvellous endurance
                  in the way of modes of life and of clothing; for he would cut a thick ugly cloak
                  into two, and he clothed himself <pb type="vol" n="235"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="581"/>with half of it and
                  covered himself with half of it;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a22" target="#n22" n="22"/> and he
                  would not change this raiment for a considerable time, not in summer nor in
                  winter, until it appeared to be all rags;<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a23" target="#n23" n="23"/>
                  for he would say <quote>It is better for the soul to clothe itself in practices of
                     excellence than for the body to luxuriate in things that drag to
                     perdition</quote>. Being therefore resplendent in holiness he used to astonish
                  many by miracles. Two barren women from the city of <placeName>Thella</placeName>,
                  being distressed by the deprivation of children, and who were looking for the
                  fruit of their wombs more than the breath of the air (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άήρ</foreign>), and had gone to many places to seek assistance, resolved to go
                  up to the same saint at the time when he was present in his monastery; and they
                  went out from the city to go to his convent. When they had reached and crossed the
                  river <placeName>Harba</placeName> that is between the monastery and the city, a
                  revelation was made to the saint by the divine Spirit; then (<foreign xml:lang="grc">είτα</foreign>) he sends a deacon of his to them to tell them to
                  return to the city; <quote>For our Lord</quote> (he says) <quote>will give you
                     children if you confess his holy name</quote>. And they on hearing these words
                  returned to the <pb type="vol" n="236"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="582"/>city. And the saying of the saint was
                  accomplished; for after one year our Lord gave them children, and afterwards sons
                  and daughters, and they continued praising the name of God.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a24" target="#n24" n="24"/>
                    </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-59.2" n="2"> But, after a considerable time had past, and he was
                  radiating light in this world like a bright sun, he was chosen by the grace of God
                  to go up to the royal city, to argue on behalf on the faith in conjunction with
                  certain saints and father<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a25" target="#n25" n="25"/>. He was
                  unwilling to do so, but nevertheless he was going up in obedience to a vision
                  which appeared to him, the holy Mar <placeName>Severus</placeName> the
                     patriarch<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a26" target="#n26" n="26"/> and Mar
                     <persName>John</persName> bishop of <placeName>Thella</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a27" target="#n27" n="27"/>, who came to him and gave him a pastoral
                  staff and said to him with a threat, <quote>Rise go with the companies of
                     believers and feed our sheep, and keep them from the wolves</quote>; and
                  thereupon he took a small gospel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">εύαγγέλλιον</foreign>)
                  and set out to go on foot to <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>. And there
                  joined him from his monastery a certain well-tried and divine man who was called
                     <persName>Sergius</persName>, who after a time was made a bishop by the blessed
                  man himself. And, when the two had gone to the royal city and arrived <pb type="vol" n="237"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="583"/>there, the report flew about in the city, <quote>Father
                        <persName>James</persName> has come</quote>; and, when
                     <persName>Theodora</persName> the queen heard it, she received them with much
                  honour, and she gave them a house and the rest of what they required. But the
                  blessed man was eloquent and educated and skilled and exercised and practised,
                     and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a28" target="#n28" n="28"/> he was versed in the Greek
                  language as well as the Syriac to a specially high degree, and he read the Holy
                  Scriptures in both languages; and, when he carried on debate with the chiefs of
                  the heresy there in their own assembly, he put them all to flight, while he also
                  through the mighty flashes of the divine doctrines (<foreign xml:lang="grc">δόγματα</foreign>) exposed their tricks and frauds against the truth of the
                  faith, and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a29" target="#n29" n="29"/> he took possession of a little
                  cell, and in it conversed with God<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a30" target="#n30" n="30"/>
                  continually. The blessed <persName>Sergius</persName> also<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a31" target="#n31" n="31"/> lived an ascetic life, but he fell<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a32" target="#n32" n="32"/> far short of the standard of the high and divine practices
                  of the holy <persName>James</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a33" target="#n33" n="33"/>. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-59.3" n="3"> When then dense crowds of believers came to the royal
                  city, bishops and monks and clergymen, and laymen zealous for religion, they used
                  to boast of <pb type="vol" n="238"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="584"/>the same saint, insomuch that
                     <persName>Hereth Bar Gabala</persName>, king of the
                     <persName>Saracens</persName>, when he heard it, came himself also to the royal
                  city; and because the party of the believers had diminished under persecutions and
                  tortures, <persName>Hereth Bar Gabala</persName> and some fathers with him begged
                  the God-loving queen <persName>Theodora</persName> to give them leave to make two
                  or three bishops in <placeName>Syria</placeName> (for there was not a bishop to be
                  found in the whole of <placeName>Syria</placeName> except three<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a34" target="#n34" n="34"/>, one on the mountain of Marde, and one in
                     <placeName>Persian territory</placeName>, and one who had gone into<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a35" target="#n35" n="35"/>
                        <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>). And, since the believing queen was desirous of
                  furthering such measures as would be of assistance against the <persName>synod of
                        <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>
                        </persName>, she ordered them to make the
                  bishops. Then two well-tried men were chosen by the holy patriarch
                     <persName>Theodosius</persName> of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> and the
                  fathers who were with him to be bishops, one this divine<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a36" target="#n36" n="36"/>
                        <persName>James</persName> for the city of <placeName>Edessa</placeName> and all
                  the rest of <placeName>Syria</placeName> and <placeName>Asia</placeName>, and
                  another whose name was <persName>Theodore</persName> for the city of Bostra<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a37" target="#n37" n="37"/> in the south, and
                     <placeName>Palestine</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a38" target="#n38" n="38"/>, and
                     <placeName>Arabia</placeName> as far as <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>. The
                  divine <persName>James</persName>, having received the bishop's office from the
                  blessed <persName>Theodosius</persName> by the advice and permission of the queen
                  (for after he had left his see he was afraid to ordain. <pb type="vol" n="239"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="585"/>bishops<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a39" target="#n39" n="39"/> without permission of the
                     crown<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a40" target="#n40" n="40"/>), then accordingly<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a41" target="#n41" n="41"/> armed himself with religion, and clothed
                  himself in the breast plate of righteousness<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a42" target="#n42" n="42"/>, and extended his course not only in the districts of
                     <placeName>Syria</placeName> but also in those of the whole of
                     <placeName>Armenia</placeName>, and of <placeName>Cappadocia</placeName> and in
                  the districts of <placeName>Cilicia</placeName>, and the whole of
                     <placeName>Isauria</placeName>, and of <placeName>Pamphylia</placeName> and
                     <placeName>Lycaonia</placeName> and <placeName>Lycia</placeName> and
                     <placeName>Phrygia</placeName> and <placeName>Caria</placeName> and
                     <placeName>Asia</placeName> and the islands of the sea,
                     <placeName>Cyprus</placeName>, <placeName>Rhodes</placeName>,
                     <placeName>Chios</placeName>, <placeName>Mitylene</placeName>, up to the royal
                  city itself; and he propagated and expanded all orthodoxy (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθόδοξος</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a43" target="#n43" n="43"/>, and made
                  priests, and filled the ranks. And not only did he marshal priests and supply all
                  quarters, but he did not even neglect churches that were at a distance; and the
                  Lord put it into his mind, and he contrived means of adorning the church of God.
                  And, since there is a prudent canon that without three bishops or four no bishop
                  shall be instituted, he considered the matter and took with him two monks who had
                  a reputation. for excellence of life, one from <placeName>Cilicia</placeName>, and
                  one from <placeName>Isauria</placeName>, and took them <pb type="vol" n="240"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="586"/>to the royal city. And he received advice and permission from the holy
                     <persName>Theodosius</persName> the patriarch who was at that time residing
                  there by way of exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>), and he directed
                  his path to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, with these two blessed men<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a44" target="#n44" n="44"/>. that he might there consecrate them
                  bishops, because there was no bishop in <placeName>Syria</placeName> except one,
                  nor an orthodox (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθόδοξος</foreign>) patriarch; but of
                  the <persName>synod of <placeName>Chalcelon</placeName>
                        </persName> there wins a
                  patriarch at <placeName>Antioch</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a45" target="#n45" n="45"/>, Ephraim the heretic<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a46" target="#n46" n="46"/>, from the city of
                     <placeName>Amida</placeName>, the wicked persecutor of religion. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-59.4" n="4"> But the holy <persName>James</persName>, when he had
                  completely performed his ministry in all the countries from the royal city as far
                  as the sea-coasts, then thus entered <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>; and when
                  he had been<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a47" target="#n47" n="47"/> in intercourse with the
                     saintly<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a48" target="#n48" n="48"/> bishops there then they
                  admired the saint's austerity, that he had travelled through these countries
                  without an animal to ride, and without a wallet or bronze coins or a purse,
                  according to the commandment received from the blessed patriarch
                     <persName>Theodosius</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a49" target="#n49" n="49"/>. And
                  accordingly the saintly bishops<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a50" target="#n50" n="50"/>
                  assembled, and made the two blessed men who were with him bishops, one whose name
                     <pb type="vol" n="241"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="587"/>was Conon in Tarsus a city of
                     <placeName>Cilicia</placeName>, and the other whose name was
                     <persName>Eugene</persName> in the city of <placeName>Seleucia</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a51" target="#n51" n="51"/>; and further for
                     <placeName>Syria</placeName> two, <persName>Antony</persName> and
                     <persName>Antoninus</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a52" target="#n52" n="52"/>. And he
                  took them with him and set out for <placeName>Syria</placeName>; and in accordance
                  with the provision of the canons he made metropolitan in <placeName>the city of
                     Laodicea</placeName> a divine man whose name was <persName>Dimet</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a53" target="#n53" n="53"/> from the holy convent of
                     <persName>Aphthonia</persName>, and another whose name was
                     <persName>John</persName> from the <placeName>monastery</placeName> of Mar
                     <persName>Bwzy</persName> of <placeName>Seleucia</placeName> in
                     <placeName>Syria</placeName>; and <persName>John</persName> from <placeName>the
                         monastery of the house of Mar <persName>Bassus</persName></placeName> in
                        <placeName>Kenneshrin</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a54" target="#n54" n="54"/>; and another whose name was <persName>Sergius</persName> in
                  the city of <persName>Charrhae</persName>, from the monastery of the house of
                     <persName>Aphthonia</persName>; and another <persName>John</persName> from the
                  monastery of Mar Hananya of the city of <placeName>Sura</placeName>. And, when
                     he<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a55" target="#n55" n="55"/> had, as described, set up bishops
                  and priests in various cities, afterwards they went up to the royal city; and
                     he<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a56" target="#n56" n="56"/> made patriarch for
                     <placeName>Antioch</placeName> in<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a57" target="#n57" n="57"/>
                        <placeName>Syria</placeName> a man whose name was <persName>Sergius</persName>
                  from the city of <placeName>Thella</placeName>, who was residing in the royal
                     city<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a58" target="#n58" n="58"/>, and was illustrious for
                  religious learning; and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a59" target="#n59" n="59"/>, having completed
                  three years, he departed from the world. After a time he<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a60" target="#n60" n="60"/> ordained as his successor an Alexandrine whose <pb type="vol" n="242"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="588"/>name was <persName>Paul</persName>. And in
                     <placeName>Amida</placeName> he made a man whose name was
                     <persName>Eunomius</persName> from the city of <placeName>Amida</placeName>
                  metropolitan, who had been expelled with the clergy of the same
                     <placeName>Amida</placeName>, and was in the royal city; and he made many
                  bishops for <placeName>Egypt</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a61" target="#n61" n="61"/>.
                  And afterwards the blessed men set out for the districts of
                     <placeName>Asia</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a62" target="#n62" n="62"/> for the
                  second time; and he made four bishops, one in <placeName>Ephesus</placeName> and
                  in the whole of <placeName>Asia</placeName>, me the sinful
                     <persName>John</persName> the Syrian, the converter of the pagans, and author
                  of the Ecclesiastical History, who am from the house of Mar
                     <persName>John</persName> at <placeName>Amida</placeName>; and in the city of
                     <placeName>Smyrna</placeName> a man whose name was
                     <placeName>Photius</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a63" target="#n63" n="63"/> and
                  another <persName>John</persName> in the city of <placeName>Pergamum</placeName>;
                  and <persName>Peter</persName> in <placeName>Dorylaeum</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a64" target="#n64" n="64"/>; and also in the island of
                     <placeName>Chios</placeName> a divine man and worker of miracles whose name was
                     <placeName>Kashish</placeName>, a member of my monastery of Mar
                     <persName>John</persName> at <placeName>Amida</placeName>; and for
                     <persName>Dara</persName> he made <persName>John</persName> bishop a divine man
                  from the monastery of <placeName>Karthamin</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a65" target="#n65" n="65"/>. And in the whole <pb type="vol" n="243"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="589"/>world he
                  appointed eighty-seven<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a66" target="#n66" n="66"/> bishops, and two
                  patriarchs. And, being armed with divine strength, he would go out to his
                  ministry, and would pour out the priesthood over the countries of <placeName>the
                     East</placeName> like a great river in the days of
                     <placeName>Nisan</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a67" target="#n67" n="67"/>, having
                  entered upon the road of heroism at a vigorous and spiritual pace, and according
                  to the saying of the apostle clothed himself in the breastplate of righteousness,
                  and girded his own loins with the perfection of faith<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a68" target="#n68" n="68"/>; and he was at all times carrying on a contest on behalf of
                  the truth <quote>on the right hand and on the left in glory and in
                     dishonour</quote>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a69" target="#n69" n="69"/>. And he would run at
                  a vigorous pace through the upper and lower countries, from the <placeName>Persian
                     territory</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a70" target="#n70" n="70"/> even as far as
                  the royal city, and <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> and the countries between,
                  and fulfil the work of his ministry not only by organizing the clergy and giving
                  the priesthood, but by consoling and comforting, and edifying and strengthening in
                  teaching all the party of the believers. Once when he was travelling through the
                     districts<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a71" target="#n71" n="71"/> he came to a mountain-range
                  called <placeName>Izla</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a72" target="#n72" n="72"/>; and
                  he went into a village called <placeName>Gumtha</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a73" target="#n73" n="73"/>; and, while he was in the village, <pb type="vol" n="244"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="590"/>a certain Jewish<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a74" target="#n74" n="74"/> sorcerer was there,
                  who was deceiving the people by his sorceries. When the blessed man heard about
                  the same Jew<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a75" target="#n75" n="75"/>, he ordered them to bring
                  him before him; and, when he came, he spake and said to him <quote>Wherefore, O
                     impious man, are you doing iniquity and wrong, and opposing the right ways of
                     the Lord?<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a76" target="#n76" n="76"/> Accordingly you shall be
                     silent, and not hear nor speak unless you confess
                     <persName>Christ</persName>.</quote> And the same hour his tongue withered and
                  his ears were stopped, and he became like a stone. And, when the people stood in
                  great astonishment, Satan came out from under the feet of that Jew in the form of
                  an Ethiopian, and he wailed with a loud voice and said, <quote>Out upon you,
                     bishop <persName>James</persName>; for from your boyhood you have been a
                     vexation (?) to me</quote>. And the holy <persName>James</persName> rebuked
                  him; and he left the village with his hands laid upon his head. And the blessed
                  man spake, and said to the proprietors of the village : <quote>Satan has fled, be
                     enlightened in the Lord</quote> . But the proprietors of that village had gone
                  astray in the heresy of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>; and he stayed there a
                  long time in order to correct them. But afterwards he came to the city of
                     <placeName>Edessa</placeName>; and, when the believers there had been refreshed
                  by his words, then it happened that suddenly a son of a <pb type="vol" n="245"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="591"/>great family of the place whose name was <persName>Theodore</persName> died
                     suddenly<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a77" target="#n77" n="77"/> within his chamber; and he
                  caused much sorrow to the city by his death. And, when the blessed man heard the
                  wailings and weeping and sobbing, he asked those who were near and said,
                     <quote>What is this outcry whereby the city has been disturbed?</quote>. And
                  they said to him: <quote>A son of great family, <persName>Theodore</persName>, has
                     died suddenly; and we say that it is on account of the sins of his
                     parents.</quote> The holy blessed man answered and said to them: <quote>Not so,
                     but in order that God may be glorified through him</quote>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a78" target="#n78" n="78"/>. And he went on his feet to that dead
                  man's house; and the citizens were laughing and saying: <quote>What, pray, are
                     this fellow's patches after?</quote>. But he did not give way to their words;
                  but he knelt upon the ground in prayer; and on rising he said in presence of the
                  multitudes of the city, <quote>In the name of our Lord <persName>Jesus
                        Christ</persName>, one undivided nature, who was crucified for us on the
                     cross, rise walk<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a79" target="#n79" n="79"/>
                        </quote>. And, as the
                  saint spoke, that young man woke as if from sleep and stood up; and when his
                  parents and kinsmen asked him, <quote>How did it happen to you?</quote>, he said
                  to them; <quote>A man of fire came upon me while I <pb type="vol" n="246"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="592"/>was
                     lying on my rug, and moved his hand and took my soul from me; and I saw this
                     saint, and two old monks, who were making request of God on my behalf; and the
                     man of fire was sent with them, to obey every order that they gave him.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a80" target="#n80" n="80"/> But believe on this saint, and receive
                     all blessings from him</quote>. And many believed and were convinced by the
                  blessed man. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-59.5" n="5"> Again another time, while he was visiting the churches
                  and the monasteries, he wished to go and visit two brothers who were residing in
                  the convent of the holy <persName>Mar Kayuma</persName>; and the full evening had
                  now almost arrived; and, when half of the sun's disk had set, he showed ardent
                  desire before God in the vehemence of his spirit, and said: <quote>O su, servant
                     of the creatures of God,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a81" target="#n81" n="81"/> wait for me
                     till I enter that convent.</quote> And the sun waited and did not set till he
                  entered that convent. And, when the members of that convent asked him, and say<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a82" target="#n82" n="82"/> to him, <quote>Our father, what is this
                     miracle of the sun?</quote>, then he answered, and said to them: <quote>Are you
                     so dull that you do not remember the words of our Lord who said, <quote>If
                        there be in you faith as a <pb type="vol" n="247"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="593"/>grain of mustard, ye
                        shall tell this mountain to fall into the sea and it shall be
                        done</quote>
                            <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a83" target="#n83" n="83"/>?</quote> Afterwards he
                  went in and found one of the brothers there seriously ill, and he said to him,
                     <quote>Do you wish to depart to our Lord, or be left for repentance?</quote>.
                  And he said, <quote>I desire to fly away<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a84" target="#n84" n="84"/>
                        </quote>. And he said to him: <quote>Therefore to-morrow morning you shall
                     depart to our Lord<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a85" target="#n85" n="85"/>
                        </quote>. And all
                  the night he was engaged in reciting service on behalf of that brother; and at the
                  hour of matins he ended his life. But the other brother he duly fortified like a
                  mighty man, and said to him <quote>Our Lord will not give you life except for one
                     year. However lay up the provisions needed for departure</quote>. Having left
                  that place, and gone round the cities and countries, he came to
                     <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, and his mighty power was indeed shown. A
                  certain citizen's daughter, a virgin, suddenly fell under the power of an evil
                  fiend, and was crying and foaming; and, when he had anointed her with the oil of
                  prayer, that demon departed from her. And, whenever the proper policy was being
                  decided, he used to tell the victorious king all the actions that were going to he
                  enacted throughout the commonwealth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πολιτεία</foreign>)
                  of the <persName>Romans</persName>; <pb type="vol" n="248"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="594"/>so that in
                  consequence of his performance of miracles his fame was wafted to all quarters
                  like choice spices (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρωμα</foreign>), and the victorious
                  kings of the <persName>Romans</persName> and of the <persName>Persians</persName>
                  and remote peoples heard the fame of the same saint's miracles, and all the
                  bishops of the heresy of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> from all sides were
                  indignant against him, and sought to seize the blessed man and tear him<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a86" target="#n86" n="86"/> in pieces. And, while they were running
                  after him with threats in all quarters, he was sheltered by the divine grace, and
                  was not delivered into the hands of his pursuers and of those who sought his
                     life<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a87" target="#n87" n="87"/>; for, when he wished to go to any
                  district, he would complete the whole work of his ministry in one night perhaps
                  and one day, and on the next day he would by the divine grace be found thirty
                     and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a88" target="#n88" n="88"/> forty miles away. And, wherever he
                  wished to add to his ministry, he would go by the Spirit of God to the district
                  which he wished<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a89" target="#n89" n="89"/>, without wearying; for he
                  never rode an animal in his life all the time of his activity. In<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a90" target="#n90" n="90"/> the days when he was staying in his
                  convent, a certain man among the citizens of <placeName>Thella</placeName> used to
                  go up to the <pb type="vol" n="249"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="595"/>saint in religious discretion, that he
                  might be blessed by the blessed man and ask his prayers; and he had followed this
                  practice for a long time. But this man had a co-sponsor<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a91" target="#n91" n="91"/> who was a presbyter in the order (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τάγμα</foreign>) of the church. When then the presbyter saw his co-sponsor
                  going constantly to the blessed man, he said to him: <quote>Therefore do you
                     neglect your employment day by day, and suffer loss by giving your time to
                     going to Mar <persName>James</persName> the bishop? It is enough for you to be
                     blessed once a month.</quote> But his co-sponsor, when he heard these things,
                  continued pressing the presbyter to make the journey to the same saint with him,
                  to show him the miracles of the man of God; and one day the presbyter gave him
                  pleasure and consented to go with him. But Satan the hater of good things on
                  seeing the two co-sponsors going in earnestness and in divine love to be blessed
                  by the blessed man showed them an apparition (<foreign xml:lang="grc">φαντασία</foreign>), in order that they might not again come to the saint's
                  own presence; and, when they reached the door of his cell in the monastery, they
                  saw that a girl beautiful to look at came out from his presence merry and
                  laughing, and, when, that presbyter saw her, he said to his co-sponsor: <quote>See
                     to whom you are urging me to come and <pb type="vol" n="250"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="596"/>be
                     blessed</quote>; for he was scandalized. And on coming in to the blessed man,
                  and seeing no one with him they were both more scandalized, since they had seen a
                  woman coming out of his cell while he was alone. But the man who was constantly
                  going up to him, overcome by abundance of love, revealed before the blessed man
                  himself the scandal that had troubled their minds, and began to say to him:
                     <quote>Sir, I urged this presbyter to come to you with me, to be blessed by
                     your holiness; and he saw that a woman met us who was coming out from your
                     presence, beautiful to look at, merry and laughing, and this our companion was
                     much scandalized; and even I too was scandalized at seeing something
                     unusual.</quote> But that divine man on hearing it knew immediately that that
                  false appearance of a woman was an apparition (<foreign xml:lang="grc">φαντασία</foreign>) of a fiend; and he thought <quote>It is not right that
                     these men should be left scandalized</quote>; and he asked them, and said:
                     <quote>Shall you know that woman if you see her?</quote> And they said
                     <quote>We shall know her well.</quote> Then he ordered them to pray; and he
                  himself, having knelt down, continued entreating God, who wishes for the life of
                  men, by his secret power to force the fiend who had appeared to these men in the
                  form of a woman to come and appear in the same guise (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>) which they <pb type="vol" n="251"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="597"/>had seen. And suddenly
                  that woman stood among them, looking gloomy. And the blessed man asked them,
                     <quote>Is this the woman whom you saw?</quote> And they said, <quote>It is
                     certainly she.</quote> And, while they still supposed that it was a woman clad
                  in flesh, the saint breathed upon her and made the sign of the cross, and said:
                     <quote>Go to perdition, evil fiend, and be not a stumbling-block to
                     believers.</quote> And as he spoke that woman became like smoke, and vanished
                  from before them. And, when the men who had been scandalized saw this, they feared
                  with great fear, and praised the power of God which dwells in his saints; and they
                  went down to their city rejoicing, and repeating the praises of God. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-59.6" n="6"> The blessed man then, having remained in his monastery,
                  was for a short time<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a92" target="#n92" n="92"/> making entreaty to
                  God for the salvation of the whole church. For at that time he would fast for
                     twenty<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a93" target="#n93" n="93"/> days and then eat; and he would
                  eat sitting.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a94" target="#n94" n="94"/> But one day while he was
                  eating he fell asleep; and his disciple spoke and said: <quote>Father, rise and
                     sleep a little time on a mat also</quote>. And he said to him: <quote>If, my
                        son,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a95" target="#n95" n="95"/> you request the angels to
                     sleep, you do rightly in requesting me. The holy armies cease not from
                        praise<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a96" target="#n96" n="96"/>, and do <pb type="vol" n="252"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="598"/>you desire me to remain silent through sleep?</quote> (for he used
                  not to sleep like men, but kept watch all his life; and, if he happened to fall
                  asleep, he would sleep a little time while sitting<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a97" target="#n97" n="97"/>). One<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a98" target="#n98" n="98"/> day a woman
                  from a village called <placeName>Theltha</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a99" target="#n99" n="99"/>, in the territory of <placeName>Thella</placeName>, since
                  she had had children and they had died and no children remained to her, came to
                  the same blessed man with her domestic slaves; and the blessed man gave her
                  unction through prayer, and she had many children. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-59.7" n="7"> Again on account of men's sins there was a drought caused
                  by lack of rain over the whole of <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName>, and
                  especially in the land of <placeName>Thella</placeName>, insomuch that the rivers
                  became dry. But, when people saw this, many villages and hamlets assembled and
                  made an agreement to come to the same blessed <persName>James</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a100" target="#n100" n="100"/>. And they came to his monastery and found
                  him; and, when they had spoken with him, he prayed and wept, and he placed his
                  head between his knees. And, while they were standing before him, the atmosphere
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άήρ</foreign>) became dark, and the clouds poured rain
                  upon the earth, for <pb type="vol" n="253"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="599"/>three days and three nights; and all
                  the people praised God, and departed thence rejoicing. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-59.8" n="8"> What shall I say about the multitude of miracles which
                  the bondman of God performed in creation? for he used to do mighty works like the
                  holy apostles. And to those who were pursuing in order to catch him be caused much
                  astonishment; and often they would meet him and ask him, saying,
                     <quote><!-- Missing from Brooks -->Have you seen that blessed<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a101" target="#n101" n="101"/>
                            <persName>James</persName> the deceiver who is dressed in patches?</quote> and
                  he would turn them back to a district which he had passed through and say:
                     <quote>He was at such-and-such a place yesterday evening; but pursue after
                     him</quote>. For the report of him would be flying about to-day in some
                  village, and to-morrow in another; and he himself would not accept any gold or
                  silver or bronze whatever, nor would he allow his travelling-companion to carry
                  any, nor money or food to eat; and every day he would travel a stage (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μανσίων</foreign>) covered at a vigorous pace, while he would
                  not consent to the fast and severe abstinence being broken; so that men could not
                  travel with him for a number of days and minister to him more than a very short
                     <pb type="vol" n="254"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="600"/>time; for they could not endure the hardship of his
                  angelic mode of life. For he used to travel on foot like an active man<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a102" target="#n102" n="102"/>, and had no need to use an animal; and,
                  while he was strengthened by divine grace, his body also was sound by nature; but
                  he was dry like a stone<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a103" target="#n103" n="103"/>. However every
                  day he would make an addition among the believers; and his beneficence
                     everywhere<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a104" target="#n104" n="104"/> would sorely provoke the
                  adversaries; and consequently droves of pursuers with horses and horsemen would
                  pursue after him, and would meet one another, and perhaps he would also be present
                  among them, and they would not see him; so that, when king
                     <persName>Justinian</persName> heard of it, he promised something great to
                  those who would bring<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a105" target="#n105" n="105"/> him to his
                  presence; and many men received three hundred darics each to<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a106" target="#n106" n="106"/> bring him; and they would seek him diligently on mountains
                  and in deserts and in villages, while they did not find the bondman of God<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a107" target="#n107" n="107"/>; and he was pouring out the priesthood <pb type="vol" n="255"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="601"/>copiously in every district and city; so that, if anyone
                  say that a hundred thousand priests were ordained by him, I do not think he will
                  stray from the truth. But he raised up the faith of the church that had almost
                  disappeared, and he contended powerfully against heresy, and lifted up the head of
                  the church that was bowed down. For before the blessed man's time the believers
                  had been more than ten years without receiving the oblation, or having their
                  children baptized<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a108" target="#n108" n="108"/>; for a priest could not
                  show himself at all. And the holy blessed man both filled
                     <placeName>Syria</placeName> with bishops and priests and magnified and
                  strengthened the horn of the church that was laid low, and made bishops and
                  priests in <placeName>Persia</placeName>; and he used to send encyclical letters
                  to them that were full of confirmation of the orthodox faith. For he was powerful
                  in divine doctrine, and practised in defending the confession of orthodoxy
                     (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθόδοξος</foreign>); and by speaking from the
                  Scriptures he used to silence the heretics, since not even advocates (<foreign xml:lang="grc">συνήγορος</foreign>) and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a109" target="#n109" n="109"/> glib-tongued men were able to repress his words. And from that time every city
                  and village and convent of monks used to repeat <quote>
                            <persName>James</persName>,
                        <persName>James</persName>
                        </quote>; and, if the merciful<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a110" target="#n110" n="110"/> God <pb type="vol" n="256"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="602"/>had not had
                  pity on his church and raised him up in it, it would almost have disappeared. For
                  he stood up and preserved the faith of the apostles which was handed down by
                     <persName>James</persName> the first bishop of
                  <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, and filled the whole church with beauties, and
                  consequently, when the parties of the orthodox (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθόδοξος</foreign>) and of the heretics met one another, they would ask,
                     <quote>Who are you?</quote>; and the orthodox (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθόδοξος</foreign>) would answer, <quote>We for our part are of the faith of
                        <persName>James</persName> the first of the apostles (and he was termed
                     brother of our Lord in the flesh)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a111" target="#n111" n="111"/>,
                     which this divine <persName>James</persName> also proclaims to us</quote>;
                  while the adversaries would answer, <quote>Of Ephraim of
                        <placeName>Amida</placeName>
                        </quote>, or <quote>Of <persName>John</persName>
                     of <placeName>Srwm</placeName>
                        </quote>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a112" target="#n112" n="112"/>
                  (the patriarch opposed to God)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a113" target="#n113" n="113"/>; and hence
                  throughout <placeName>Syria</placeName> and in the countries of
                     <placeName>Persia</placeName> and of the <persName>Armenians</persName> the
                  expression became current <quote>We are of the faith of
                     <persName>James</persName>
                        </quote>; and in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>
                  and in <placeName>Egypt</placeName> again the expression became current, <quote>We
                     are of <persName>Theodosius</persName>
                        </quote> so that on this account the
                  believers of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> were named
                     <persName>Theodosians</persName>, and the <persName>Syrians</persName>
                        <persName>Jacobites</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a114" target="#n114" n="114"/>. And the
                  blessed man by his manner of life and by his innocence, <pb type="vol" n="257"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="603"/>and by his keen zeal against the enemies, and great contests (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) endured from his boyhood and down to his old age
                  showed himself a cherisher and upholder of the faith, and a worker of divine
                  miracles. Once, when he was secretly travelling to <placeName>Mt.
                     Sinai</placeName> in order to visit the saints, with one of his disciples to
                  attend upon himself, and had reached the desert region in the days of the month of
                     Ab<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a115" target="#n115" n="115"/> in the burning heat of the sun, and
                  was walking very vigorously with divine singing for more than forty miles in a
                  protracted fast, his disciple became thirsty, and began to feel faint; and he was
                  afraid to tell his master. But, when he had become desperate and lost hope of
                  life, he called to his master, saying: <quote>My father, help me. Thirst for water
                     has killed me<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a116" target="#n116" n="116"/>
                        </quote>. And the blessed
                  man on turning and seeing that he was already finished said to him: <quote>Pray
                     and beg mercy from God until I come to you</quote>. And he went from him to a
                  little watercourse that was near them; and he went down on his knees, and offered
                  supplication to the merciful<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a117" target="#n117" n="117"/> God, and as
                  the old man spoke that place shot out a spring of water. Then he called his
                  disciple and said: <quote>Drink and satisfy your<pb type="vol" n="258"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="604"/>self out
                     of the gift of our God</quote>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a118" target="#n118" n="118"/>. And he
                  drank and was strengthened. And they travelled on thanking God for his kindness. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-59.9" n="9"> But, after he had returned from <placeName>Mt.
                     Sinai</placeName> and come to his convent, <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a119" target="#n119" n="119"/>he went to visit the districts<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a120" target="#n120" n="120"/>. Now, since the church of the metropolitan city of
                     <placeName>Amida</placeName> had been razed to the ground and fallen when the
                     <persName>Persians</persName> devastated the city<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a121" target="#n121" n="121"/>, and had been rebuilt by order of the crown, the citizens
                  wished the blessed man to consecrate it; and they came to him begging him to go
                  with them; and, having consented to go,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a122" target="#n122" n="122"/>
                  he on his part ordered them to go before him; and he himself entered the city
                  after them. And a certain woman, one of the great persons of the city, was lying
                  with paralysed limbs by the city gate; who when the saint passed by her continued
                  crying and saying, <quote>Sir, have mercy upon me</quote>; and he reached toward
                  her, and took hold of her hand and said: <quote>May our Lord<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a123" target="#n123" n="123"/>
                            <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> heal you my daughter</quote>; and immediately
                  she was cured<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a124" target="#n124" n="124"/>, and went into the church.
                     <pb type="vol" n="259"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="605"/>And having entered the church he consecrated it in
                  the customary way. And to many who were in the congregation God showed a miracle;
                  for, while he was standing in the holy place, they saw<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a125" target="#n125" n="125"/> hosts of angels who were dancing and uttering praise within
                  the sanctuary and rejoicing in a song of praise. And after consecrating the church
                  and ordaining priests and deacons there he departed from among them, having
                  informed them that they were about to suffer tribulations. Then (<foreign xml:lang="grc">είτα</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a126" target="#n126" n="126"/> after a
                  short time certain persons in various cities and in villages under the pressure of
                  the authorities denied the faith of the church, and went over to the
                     <persName>synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>
                        </persName>; but they are
                  forthwith chastised for the purpose of correction. For God sent upon the whole of
                     <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName> on account of the sins of men, especially
                  upon <persName>Charrhae</persName> and <placeName>Edessa</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a127" target="#n127" n="127"/> and <placeName>Amida</placeName> and
                     <placeName>Maiferkat</placeName>, raging madness and blindness of heart, and
                  the population became possessed by demons, except a few, but especially at
                     <placeName>Amida</placeName>. Men wailed and jumped, and were <pb type="vol" n="260"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="606"/>mad and ran as if horsemen were riding after them; and they barked
                  like dogs, and howled; and in their madness they bit their flesh; and, while at
                     <placeName>Maiferkat</placeName> and at <persName>Charrhae</persName> and at
                     <placeName>Edessa</placeName> it was a small matter, in the city of
                     <placeName>Amida</placeName> great madness prevailed, especially among boys and
                  girls. When then the citizens saw these things they were overcome with affliction
                  at thinking what a horrible thing<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a128" target="#n128" n="128"/> had
                  happened to their city, and they were running to the same saint, and begging him
                  with many tears to visit them. But the saint answered and said to them: <quote>How
                     do you wish the Lord to have mercy upon you when you deny his Godhead and
                     divide the one and indivisible into two natures? But, if so be you will obey
                     me, God will visit you</quote>. And they said: <quote>We will do your will, our
                     father; only deliver us from this grievous infliction</quote>. And he granted
                  their request, and rose and went to the city of <placeName>Amida</placeName>. But,
                  when he entered<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a129" target="#n129" n="129"/> the city, those who had
                  gone mad began to run away from the sight of him and seek refuge under <pb type="vol" n="261"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="607"/>walls; and having gone into the inside of the church he brought
                  incense and set it before the altar; and he ordered them to carry it over all the
                  streets of their city and the houses, and on the walls of the city all round; and
                  the day was the first day of the week. But, after he had offered the oblation and
                  celebrated the awful mysteries, men began to come to their senses and recover
                  their intellects and praise God. And again at the vesper hour he set down incense,
                  and prayed; and all that night he was offering petition to God on their behalf.
                  And at morning on the second day of the week there remained not a soul in that
                     city<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a130" target="#n130" n="130"/> which had not been cured and come
                  to its senses, and those who had been afflicted<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a131" target="#n131" n="131"/> began to utter exclamations of praise to God, giving thanks
                  and praise, and begging mercy from him. Then the blessed man ordered them to
                  clothe and cover<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a132" target="#n132" n="132"/> themselves in black for
                  several days. And so he left the city with high reputation<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a133" target="#n133" n="133"/>, while all the multitudes praised God the lover of mankind;
                  and he went to <placeName>Maiferkat</placeName> and to
                     <placeName>Thella</placeName> and to <placeName>Edessa</placeName>, and to
                     <persName>Charrhae</persName>; and he visited them in the same <pb type="vol" n="262"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="608"/>way; for there was not<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a134" target="#n134" n="134"/> a dead
                  man among those who had been afflicted. And he came and went into his monastery
                  for a few days; and one night he called the<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a135" target="#n135" n="135"/> blessed men the members of his convent, and said to them <quote>My fathers and
                     my brothers, let us sorrow for the Lord's people, since it has been bereft of
                     the" blessed pastor <persName>Theodosius</persName> patriarch of
                        <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> and he has gone to the tents of the
                     saints; for this night he committed his spirit to God</quote>. Now that year
                  was the year eight hundred and eighty-seven of
                     <placeName>Alexander</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a136" target="#n136" n="136"/>. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-59.10" n="10"> Again too in the period before this, when
                     <persName>Khosrau</persName> son of <persName>Kawad</persName> the Persian king
                  came and laid waste the cities and villages on the
                     <placeName>Euphrates</placeName> and ravaged and destroyed
                     <placeName>Batnae</placeName>, he came also against
                     <placeName>Edessa</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a137" target="#n137" n="137"/>, and
                  encamped against it to take it, and, when he was unable to do so<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a138" target="#n138" n="138"/>, of craft in destruction whose name was
                  Cometas, a spy, who used to teach <persName>Khosrau</persName> all kinds of evil
                  plans against <placeName>Syria</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a139" target="#n139" n="139"/>, advised him to order his <pb type="vol" n="263"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="609"/>forces to build houses<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a140" target="#n140" n="140"/> against the city and to reduce it to
                  straits as he actually did<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a141" target="#n141" n="141"/>. But, when the
                  citizens heard of this contrivance, they were running to the same holy
                     <persName>James</persName>; for he<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a142" target="#n142" n="142"/> had
                  arrived in the city a short time before, and it became known to discerning men
                  that God had brought him to save the city. And accordingly the
                     <persName>Edessenes</persName> came to him and said: <quote>Our saintly father,
                     offer supplication to God, that he may save it<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a143" target="#n143" n="143"/> from this man and the<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a144" target="#n144" n="144"/> impious kingdom</quote>. And the blessed man said to
                  them: <quote>Fear not, ye of little faith<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a145" target="#n145" n="145"/>. Only believe in our Lord. This night God will drive him away like
                        <persName>Sennacherib</persName> from <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>; and
                     at daybreak none of the <persName>Persians</persName> shall be found in your
                     borders</quote>. And the blessed man prayed all that night; and at midnight
                     <persName>Khosrau</persName> saw<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a146" target="#n146" n="146"/>
                  horses of fire, and horsemen<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a147" target="#n147" n="147"/> clad in
                  flame saying to him: <quote>Rise depart from our city; and, if also you have not
                     done so when the sun rises, we will slay you and all your army</quote>. And,
                  when this vision had appeared to <persName>Khosrau</persName>, a stern. <pb type="vol" n="264"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="610"/>voice cried<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a148" target="#n148" n="148"/> and
                  alarmed his forces and they retired from the city in great fear<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a149" target="#n149" n="149"/>. Then the saint's word was being carried
                  into effect, and the Lord saved that city by his prayers. Now there was in the
                  same city among the distinguished men a certain blind man; and he heard of the
                  blessed man's miracles, and went to him by the help of some of his servants, and
                  said to him <quote>Sir, have mercy upon me as your Lord had mercy on
                        <persName>Timaeus Bar Timaeus</persName> the blind man, and grant me in his
                     name to see light, in order that his name may be glorified because of
                     me</quote>. And, when the blessed man heard these words, he wept for sorrow;
                  and he was strongly moved in his spirit<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a150" target="#n150" n="150"/>
                  and said: <quote>Come near to me and see the Lord's glory</quote>. And he came
                  near to him; and he placed his right hand on his eyes and said, <quote>Our Lord
                        <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, fashioner of our frame, indivisible, one,
                     Only one, in thy name may the pupils of this thy bondman see light</quote>. And
                  the same hour that blind man saw; and the multitudes marvelled, and they praised
                  God and continued saying: <quote>Truly this is a divine man</quote>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a151" target="#n151" n="151"/>. And he left the city and went to <pb type="vol" n="265"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="611"/>greet the blessed men of the divine convent of Bar
                     <persName>Aphthonia</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a152" target="#n152" n="152"/>; for he
                  loved it greatly on account of its virtues; and, having entered the convent, he
                  both filled up the ranks of the priesthood and did what was customary<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a153" target="#n153" n="153"/> (for it had recently been built). But one
                  day, while he was offering the oblation, a certain <persName>Saracen</persName>
                  who had recently been baptized was present there; and he saw that fire came down
                  from heaven, and saw tongues of flame hovering over the oblation, and hosts of
                  angels with bowed<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a154" target="#n154" n="154"/> head before the divine
                     sacrifice<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a155" target="#n155" n="155"/>; and he saw that, whenever
                  anyone received the oblation, they wrote his name in the book of life; and that
                  barbarian believed, and praised God. </ab>
                    <ab xml:id="section-59.11" n="11"> And the blessed man left the convent and went to visit
                  the churches in <placeName>Asia</placeName>; and he visited all the believers<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a156" target="#n156" n="156"/> with the divine word, and proclaimed the
                  news of the gospel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">εύαγγέλλιον</foreign>) to near and
                  far. Having appeared in the world like the great <persName>Paul</persName>, and
                  completed his ministry, and perfectly kept the faith<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a157" target="#n157" n="157"/>, he assisted God's church for a space of forty years. Having
                     <pb type="vol" n="266"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="612"/>received ordination during the years of
                     <persName>Justinian</persName> king of the <persName>Romans</persName>, he was
                     living<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a158" target="#n158" n="158"/> down to the years of Tiberius
                  the king the successor of <persName>Justin</persName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a159" target="#n159" n="159"/>: and during these forty years his steps did not pass away
                  from the paths of righteousness, nor his tongue from the divine words. But, when
                  he had reached advanced old age, a certain scandal-causing calamity sprang up in
                  the church, through the fact that <persName>Paul</persName> the patriarch and the
                     saint<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a160" target="#n160" n="160"/> also were zealous for the
                     Lord<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a161" target="#n161" n="161"/>; and, in order that a scandal
                  might not arise within the church, the blessed <persName>James</persName> made a
                  secret resolve for the sake of the correction of the believers to go as far as
                     <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a162" target="#n162" n="162"/>; and
                  he took with him eight other bishops<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a163" target="#n163" n="163"/> and
                  hastened to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> as I said; for his intention was a
                     secret<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a164" target="#n164" n="164"/> from everyone. And, as they
                  were journeying along the road, they reached a large monastery on the frontier of
                     <placeName>Egypt</placeName> called that of <placeName>Casium</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a165" target="#n165" n="165"/>. And, when they had gone into the
                  monastery and put up<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a166" target="#n166" n="166"/> and prayed, the
                  saint spoke and said to those with him: <quote>Pray, my brothers, since the Lord
                     showed me that here I and three of you will depart <pb type="vol" n="267"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="613"/>from the life of time</quote>. And after he had said these words at daybreak
                  one of the bishops who were with him died, who was formerly archimandrite of the
                  convent of <placeName>Karthamin</placeName>
                        <ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a167" target="#n167" n="167"/>; and the holy old man stood up and<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a168" target="#n168" n="168"/>
                  offered the oblation for him. And again <persName>Sergius</persName> his
                     <foreign rend="italics">syncellus</foreign> who also had become a bishop fell sick and died.
                  And after three days he himself<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a169" target="#n169" n="169"/> delivered
                  up his soul to God, on the day on<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a170" target="#n170" n="170"/> which
                  God commanded it; and again after him his<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a171" target="#n171" n="171"/>
                  deacon also, and all these in twelve days, so that men were reduced to
                  astonishment and wondered. And the report went out over the countries that the
                  light of the church had been extinguished<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a172" target="#n172" n="172"/>. And his companions, overcome with wonder, returned to
                     <placeName>Syria</placeName> in great sadness. But the monks of the convent of
                     <placeName>Casium</placeName> laid<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a173" target="#n173" n="173"/> the
                  blessed man in a coffin (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γλωσσόκομον</foreign>) and took
                  possession of him<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a174" target="#n174" n="174"/> with great honour. Then
                  the whole of <placeName>Syria</placeName> sorrowed over the old man's death; and
                  many came to his monastery and were visited. And the people of the<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a175" target="#n175" n="175"/> city of <placeName>Thella</placeName> also
                  suffered many distresses <pb type="vol" n="268"/><pb type="running" rend="brackets" n="614"/>at being deprived of the
                  saint's bones; and so they were always asking for his prayers; and the power of
                  God would visit them; to whom be glory and honour and worship, for ever and ever.
                  Amen! </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="trailer" xml:id="trailer-59">
                    <ab xml:id="trailer-59.1" n="12"> The history of <persName>James</persName> the bishop
                  written by Mar <persName>John</persName> of <placeName>Asia</placeName> is ended.
               </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <noteGrp>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 574, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>In C. the tit.: <hi rend="singleQuotes">A history concerning the holy Mar
                  J., bp. of Edessa (or rather (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μάλλον</foreign>) of all the
                  orthodox), who is known as Burd'ana, and on account of whom also we were termed
                  Jacobites, and it is written by the holy J. of A., the converter of pagans and
                  author of the ecclesiastical histories</hi>, and the text opens with the words <hi rend="singleQuotes">Paise to God who adorned his church with his saints and filled
                  it with the riches and treasures of their relics, and decorated it with the
                  glorious flowers of their practices, which are recorded in their histories, and
                  painted before the eyes of the heart of believers; and, whenever we read of the
                  manner of life of one of them, we are consoled by him as if he were with us and
                  our minds exult in love for him, esp. of this saint who adorned the church by the
                  gifts of grace wherewith he filled it, and delivered himself up for it; of whose
                  practices our feeble speech does not suffice to describe a small fragment; whom if
                  the Lord had not had mercy on his church and raised up, it would have been brought
                  to destruction through the evil persecution of the Diphysites; the beginning of
                  whose story we begin to make clear from examination and study; whom we entreat to
                  help us by his prayers, that we may speak and write all about him. Accordingly
                  from this point we begin to place the memorial of his history on record</hi>. S.
               marg. <hi rend="singleQuotes">This history is of J. Burd'ana, and not of James of
                  Edessa, the interpreter of the Scriptures, since the Edessene's time was known to
                  be (?) the year 1054, and Burd'ana died in the year 889.</hi>
                </note>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 575, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>N (Introd., p. XIII) has here an Arabic note. <hi rend="singleQuotes">This
                  is the story of James Burd'ana the liar the cursed heretic. And he has made the
                  whole narrative (?) mendacious and false</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 575, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sev. left CP. about 9 mos. before Th. arrived, and the conference was held
               at a much earlier time.</note>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 576, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C''strtlys'. We should perh. read 'stratelates', and suppose S. Michael to
               be meant; but his usual title is <foreign xml:lang="grc">άρχιστρατηγός</foreign>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 576, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 488, n. 3.</note>
                <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 576, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C. <hi rend="singleQuotes">This son was brought up by his parents with all
                  care and in all religion; and, when he was 2 or 3 years old, they sent him to
                  school, and he was taught and instructed in all the learning of the church, in
                  Syriac and Greek. And, when he reached the age of puberty, his father took him
                  with a fitting present and brought him to the monastery, and committed him to the
                  hands of Mar Eustace the archimandrite ; and, when he had received the reversed
                  habit</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 576, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 577, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 578, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>I.e., in spirit.</note>
                <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 578, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 579, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C 'Greeks'. The phrase shows that the author wrote after the Arab conquest,
               since otherwise he would have said <hi rend="singleQuotes">the king</hi> only.</note>
                <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 579, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 579, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Mss. <hi rend="singleQuotes">their king sent</hi>; but clearly he went
               himself.</note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 579, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">he</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 579, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">man</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 580, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Acts, VIII, 20.</note>
                <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 580, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">moment the pestilence was stayed and all the
                  sick</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 580, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">he</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 580, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 581, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 489, n. 3. In the genuine life this is referred to the time of his
               residence in CP.</note>
                <note xml:id="n21" target="#a21" n="21">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 581, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">like a pack-saddle, and from this he was
                  named Burd'ana</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n22" target="#a22" n="22">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 582, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C om., prob. because the scribe did not wish to bring J. into any connexion
               with the procreation of children; cf. below (p. 598).</note>
                <note xml:id="n23" target="#a23" n="23">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 582, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>In the original life no reason for the journey is given exc. <hi rend="singleQuotes">on account of the faith</hi>; see p. 489, n. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n24" target="#a24" n="24">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 582, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n25" target="#a25" n="25">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 582, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>C ins <hi rend="singleQuotes">who were both dead</hi>. Both in fact lived
               till 538, and John was present at the conferences (p. 318, n. 3). - The insertion is
               also inconsistent with p. 575.</note>
                <note xml:id="n26" target="#a26" n="26">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 583, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">And, because</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n27" target="#a27" n="27">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 583, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">also further</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n28" target="#a28" n="28">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 583, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">sat</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n29" target="#a29" n="29">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 583, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">with the divine and blessed S., he</hi>
               (sic).</note>
                <note xml:id="n30" target="#a30" n="30">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 583, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>C ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">not</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n31" target="#a31" n="31">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 583, n. 6</orig>
                    </choice>The statement in the original life that S. could not live as J. did because
               he had to attend to visitors is omitted by our author, prob. in order to exalt his
               hero at the expense of his companion.</note>
                <note xml:id="n32" target="#a32" n="32">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 584, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>A misunderstanding of the statement in ch. 24 that (at a much earlier time)
               there were no bps. exc. in these 3 places.</note>
                <note xml:id="n33" target="#a33" n="33">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 584, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">another in</hi>..</note>
                <note xml:id="n34" target="#a34" n="34">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 584, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n35" target="#a35" n="35">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 584, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>In the original life <hi rend="singleQuotes">Hirtha of the
               Saracens</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n36" target="#a36" n="36">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 585, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>In the original (ch. 50) this statement is made on the occasion of the
               consecration of bps. for Egypt by James, and there are no qualifying words.</note>
                <note xml:id="n37" target="#a37" n="37">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 585, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">queen</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n38" target="#a38" n="38">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 585, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">the blessed Th. secretly permitted him to make
                  bps. and perform all the functions of the priesthood. And then the saintly
               J.</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n39" target="#a39" n="39">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 585, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Eph., VI, 14.</note>
                <note xml:id="n40" target="#a40" n="40">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 585, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n41" target="#a41" n="41">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 586, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n42" target="#a42" n="42">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 586, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Mss. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n43" target="#a43" n="43">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 586, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">men and</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n44" target="#a44" n="44">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 586, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">or rather (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μάλλον</foreign> from Christ</hi> (Matth., X, 9). In the original (ch. 20) the
               commandment refers to the communication with the bps.</note>
                <note xml:id="n45" target="#a45" n="45">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 586, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">they</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n46" target="#a46" n="46">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 587, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C ins. (wrongly) <hi rend="singleQuotes">of Syria</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n47" target="#a47" n="47">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 587, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>There is no mention of these in the original life, the names being taken
               from <title>H.E.</title>, IV, 11, where two Antonini are said to have been recently
               (the events recorded happened in 578) consecrated by James for Syria.</note>
                <note xml:id="n48" target="#a48" n="48">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 587, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 502, n. 2.</note>
                <note xml:id="n49" target="#a49" n="49">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 587, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Chalcis in Syria.</note>
                <note xml:id="n50" target="#a50" n="50">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 587, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">they</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n51" target="#a51" n="51">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 587, n. 6</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">of</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n52" target="#a52" n="52">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 587, n. 7</orig>
                    </choice>See above (p. 582).</note>
                <note xml:id="n53" target="#a53" n="53">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 587, n. 8</orig>
                    </choice>C ins<hi rend="singleQuotes">not</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n54" target="#a54" n="54">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 588, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">Ignatius and others</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n55" target="#a55" n="55">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 588, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Mss <hi rend="singleQuotes">Syria</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n56" target="#a56" n="56">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 588, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>In the original text <hi rend="singleQuotes">Peter</hi>. Photius, as we
               learn from ch. 56, was a companion of Peter.</note>
                <note xml:id="n57" target="#a57" n="57">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 588, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>In the original text <hi rend="singleQuotes">Tralles</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n58" target="#a58" n="58">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 588, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>The original text says nothing about Dara, which is out of place in an
               account of the bps. of Asia, but it mentions 2 Carian bps., here omitted. John of
               Dara is probably the same as the bishop who had been archim. of Karthamin mentioned
               on p. 613 from <title>H.E.</title>, IV, 33, and was no doubt consecrated later
               (Dyakonov, p. 78, n. 111). See above, p. 587, n. 2. <hi rend="singleQuotes">Dion</hi>
               however (Kleyn, Bijdrage, p. 73) calls this J. of Karthamin who died in 578 bp. of
               Amida.</note>
                <note xml:id="n59" target="#a59" n="59">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 589, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>In the orginal text <hi rend="singleQuotes">27</hi>; C <hi rend="singleQuotes">89</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n60" target="#a60" n="60">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 589, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>April.</note>
                <note xml:id="n61" target="#a61" n="61">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 589, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Eph., VI, 14.</note>
                <note xml:id="n62" target="#a62" n="62">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 589, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>II Cor., VI, 7.8.</note>
                <note xml:id="n63" target="#a63" n="63">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 589, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n64" target="#a64" n="64">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 589, n. 6</orig>
                    </choice>C ins <hi rend="singleQuotes">of the East </hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n65" target="#a65" n="65">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 589, n. 7</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 419, n. 4.</note>
                <note xml:id="n66" target="#a66" n="66">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 589, n. 8</orig>
                    </choice>I. e. <hi rend="singleQuotes">the trench</hi>, see p. 418, n. 3. This
               however was not a village, but a district.</note>
                <note xml:id="n67" target="#a67" n="67">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 590, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n68" target="#a68" n="68">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 590, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">sorceror</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n69" target="#a69" n="69">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 590, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Acts, XIII, 10, 11.</note>
                <note xml:id="n70" target="#a70" n="70">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 591, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Sic bis.</note>
                <note xml:id="n71" target="#a71" n="71">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 591, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>John, IX, 2,3.</note>
                <note xml:id="n72" target="#a72" n="72">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 591, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>Acts, III, 6.</note>
                <note xml:id="n73" target="#a73" n="73">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 592, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">and he took my soul and restored it to my
                  body</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n74" target="#a74" n="74">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 592, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">and creature of God, in the name of Jesus of
                  Nazareth</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n75" target="#a75" n="75">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 592, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">he found the brethren looking in wonder and
                  astonishment at the sun; and they said</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n76" target="#a76" n="76">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 593, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., XVII, 20.</note>
                <note xml:id="n77" target="#a77" n="77">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 593, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">and be with Christ</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n78" target="#a78" n="78">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 593, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">we shall bury you</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n79" target="#a79" n="79">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 594, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">him in order by reason of the drunkenness of their
                  envy to tear the blessed man</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n80" target="#a80" n="80">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 594, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Jer., XLIV, 30.</note>
                <note xml:id="n81" target="#a81" n="81">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 594, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n82" target="#a82" n="82">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 594, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">he would be found by the grace of the
               Spirit</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n83" target="#a83" n="83">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 594, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>This story has been omitted by the scribe of C., obviously because he
               thought it unedifying.</note>
                <note xml:id="n84" target="#a84" n="84">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 595, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>are men who are godfathers or father to the same child, old Engl. <hi rend="singleQuotes">gossips</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n85" target="#a85" n="85">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 597, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">But, when he came to his monastery, he
               was</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n86" target="#a86" n="86">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 597, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">ten</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n87" target="#a87" n="87">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 597, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n88" target="#a88" n="88">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 597, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n89" target="#a89" n="89">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 597, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n90" target="#a90" n="90">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 598, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">and rise to perform service</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n91" target="#a91" n="91">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 598, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>This story is omitted in C; see p. 582, n. 1.</note>
                <note xml:id="n92" target="#a92" n="92">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 598, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>I.e. <hi rend="singleQuotes">moisture</hi>, hardly Thlatha = three.</note>
                <note xml:id="n93" target="#a93" n="93">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 598, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">holy J. in his cell</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n94" target="#a94" n="94">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 599, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This word is used of any monk or ascetic and does not necessarily mean more
               than our <hi rend="singleQuotes">reverend</hi>; cf. p. 74, l. 1.</note>
                <note xml:id="n95" target="#a95" n="95">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 600, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">as we said above</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n96" target="#a96" n="96">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 600, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">by his labours and abstinence</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n97" target="#a97" n="97">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 600, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">bu his industry in everything he</hi>. It would
               make better sense if we could render <hi rend="singleQuotes">readiness</hi> or <hi rend="singleQuotes">presence</hi> in place of <hi rend="singleQuotes">beneficence</hi>; but is not known in this sense (p. 493, l. 2, <hi rend="singleQuotes">fame</hi>).</note>
                <note xml:id="n98" target="#a98" n="98">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 600, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>In the original life the reward is offered to any who promise to bring him.
               Our author's story is inconsistent.</note>
                <note xml:id="n99" target="#a99" n="99">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 600, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">and promised to</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n100" target="#a100" n="100">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 600, n. 6</orig>
                    </choice>C ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">and returned in shame</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n101" target="#a101" n="101">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 601, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>This statement is not in the original life.</note>
                <note xml:id="n102" target="#a102" n="102">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 601, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n103" target="#a103" n="103">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 602, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n104" target="#a104" n="104">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 602, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>John <foreign xml:lang="grc">έκ τού Σηρήμιος</foreign> near Antioch (Evagr.,
               IV, 38, ad fin.) patr. of CP. 565-77. Ephraim patr. of Antioch died in 545.</note>
                <note xml:id="n105" target="#a105" n="105">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 602, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C om. N has the erroneous marginal note <hi rend="singleQuotes">This is the
                  holy John Maro</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n106" target="#a106" n="106">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 602, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>This name probably arose out of the schism about the deprivation of Paul of
               Antioch and is opposed to Paulites.</note>
                <note xml:id="n107" target="#a107" n="107">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 603, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>August.</note>
                <note xml:id="n108" target="#a108" n="108">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 603, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">I am killed by thirst</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n109" target="#a109" n="109">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 603, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n110" target="#a110" n="110">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 604, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">And the brother came and saw the water in the
                  desolate place in the wildnerness, and he wondered greatly and praised God who
                  hears his saints</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n111" target="#a111" n="111">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 604, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">he exulted and praised the Lord for his gift. But,
                  after they had reached Mt. Sinai, and he had prayed in the holy places, and been
                  blessed by the saints there, he returned to his monastery where he had been
                  trained, and again</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n112" target="#a112" n="112">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 604, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C ins <hi rend="singleQuotes">of the believing peoples</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n113" target="#a113" n="113">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 604, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>In 503, about 50 yrs. before J's time. <hi rend="singleQuotes">Dion</hi>
               however (R.O.C., II, 45) makes the Persians take Amida in 560.</note>
                <note xml:id="n114" target="#a114" n="114">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 604, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n115" target="#a115" n="115">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 604, n. 6</orig>
                    </choice>C ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">and rose</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n116" target="#a116" n="116">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 605, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n117" target="#a117" n="117">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 605, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>This event is related from another source by <hi rend="singleQuotes">Dion.</hi> (Nau in R.O.C., II, p. 487; Kleyn, Bijdrage, p. 71; cf. id., Jacobus
               Baradaeüs, p. 106) without mention of James and dated Ind. IV (556). From <hi rend="singleQuotes">Dion.</hi> it is repeated by Mich. (p. 323) and in Berlin ms.
               Sachau 315 (C.S.C.O., tom. IV, p. 321), and in the latter the intervention of J. is
               added, perh. from our text. In these two sources it is dated in 560. It was perh. an
               outbreak of hydrophobia; cf. <hi rend="singleQuotes">Zach. Rh.</hi>, VII, 14,
               Theoph., A.M. 6008, and above, p. 579.</note>
                <note xml:id="n118" target="#a118" n="118">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 605, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>S om.; see p. 606, l. 3.</note>
                <note xml:id="n119" target="#a119" n="119">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 606, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n120" target="#a120" n="120">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 606, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>S ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">inside the church and</hi>; see below.</note>
                <note xml:id="n121" target="#a121" n="121">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 607, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">among the sick</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n122" target="#a122" n="122">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 607, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">all the citizens</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n123" target="#a123" n="123">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 607, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 489, n. 3.</note>
                <note xml:id="n124" target="#a124" n="124">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 607, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>C ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">and a great procession</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n125" target="#a125" n="125">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 608, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>S om. C in place of this clause has <hi rend="singleQuotes">for none of
                  those who suffered in this affliction died</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n126" target="#a126" n="126">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 608, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">there has been taken from us our</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n127" target="#a127" n="127">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 608, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>576. Really he died in 566; see p. 486, n. 6.</note>
                <note xml:id="n128" target="#a128" n="128">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 608, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>544. But Batnae was taken in 540, when he took ransom from Edessa without
               beseiging it (Proc., <title>Bell.</title>, II, XII, XXVI).</note>
                <note xml:id="n129" target="#a129" n="129">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 608, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>C ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">on account of the numbers of people in it and
                  the strength of the wall, he was troubled; and</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n130" target="#a130" n="130">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 608, n. 6</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">the excellent people of the Syrians</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n131" target="#a131" n="131">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 609, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">outside the wall and towers</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n132" target="#a132" n="132">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 609, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">make (pl.) spoil of it</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n133" target="#a133" n="133">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 609, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">their heart trembled and was disturbed, but the
                  blessed J.</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n134" target="#a134" n="134">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 609, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Sic N. C <hi rend="singleQuotes">us</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n135" target="#a135" n="135">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 609, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">cruel man and his</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n136" target="#a136" n="136">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 609, n. 6</orig>
                    </choice>Matth., VIII, 28.</note>
                <note xml:id="n137" target="#a137" n="137">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 609, n. 7</orig>
                    </choice>N om. C in. <hi rend="singleQuotes">a fearful vision</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n138" target="#a138" n="138">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 609, n. 8</orig>
                    </choice>N om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n139" target="#a139" n="139">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 610, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">he cried with a loud voice</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n140" target="#a140" n="140">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 610, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">and, when the day broke, none of the Persians was
                  found round the city</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n141" target="#a141" n="141">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 610, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>John, XI, 33.</note>
                <note xml:id="n142" target="#a142" n="142">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 610, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>Luke, XXIII, 47.</note>
                <note xml:id="n143" target="#a143" n="143">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 611, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>At Kenneshrin on the Euphrates (<hi rend="singleQuotes">Zach. Rh.</hi>,
               VIII, 5).</note>
                <note xml:id="n144" target="#a144" n="144">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 611, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>Sc. consecrated the building.</note>
                <note xml:id="n145" target="#a145" n="145">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 611, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>N. om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n146" target="#a146" n="146">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 611, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">altar</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n147" target="#a147" n="147">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 611, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">countries</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n148" target="#a148" n="148">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 611, n. 6</orig>
                    </choice>II Tim., IV, 7.</note>
                <note xml:id="n149" target="#a149" n="149">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 612, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n150" target="#a150" n="150">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 612, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">Justinian</hi>. James d. 30 July, 578 (Mich., p.
               364; C.S.C.O., tom. IV, p. 144), and Justin lived till 4 Oct. (<title>H.E.</title>,
               III, 6).</note>
                <note xml:id="n151" target="#a151" n="151">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 612, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">holy Mar. J.</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n152" target="#a152" n="152">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 612, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>C ins. <hi rend="singleQuotes">and contended to death for the
               faith</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n153" target="#a153" n="153">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 612, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>See <title>H.E.</title>, IV, 33, 58.</note>
                <note xml:id="n154" target="#a154" n="154">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 612, n. 6</orig>
                    </choice>Really bps. and 6 others (l.c.).</note>
                <note xml:id="n155" target="#a155" n="155">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 612, n. 7</orig>
                    </choice>N <hi rend="singleQuotes">he also concealed himself</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n156" target="#a156" n="156">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 612, n. 8</orig>
                    </choice>A mountain on the borders of Egypt and Palestine (Amm. Marc., XXII,
               4).</note>
                <note xml:id="n157" target="#a157" n="157">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 612, n. 9</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">kept vigil</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n158" target="#a158" n="158">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 613, n. 1</orig>
                    </choice>See p. 504, n. 3; p. 588, n. 5.</note>
                <note xml:id="n159" target="#a159" n="159">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 613, n. 2</orig>
                    </choice>C om.</note>
                <note xml:id="n160" target="#a160" n="160">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 613, n. 3</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">this divine light of all the world the blessed J.
                  fell sick and died and</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n161" target="#a161" n="161">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 613, n. 4</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">and at the time at</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n162" target="#a162" n="162">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 613, n. 5</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">that the weary man should rest from his labour
                  this second Paul and true disciple and combatant for religion was gathered to his
                  holy fathers and the doctors of the church; and the saint's</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n163" target="#a163" n="163">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 613, n. 6</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">and in all quarters of creation that the pastor of
                  the church had gone to his rest</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n164" target="#a164" n="164">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 613, n. 7</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">buried</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="n165" target="#a165" n="165">
                    <choice>
                        <reg/>
                        <orig>p. 613, n. 8</orig>
                    </choice>C <hi rend="singleQuotes">his</hi>.</note>
            </noteGrp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
